<DLPSTEXTCLASS>
<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Abraham Lincoln quarterly.  [Vol. 1, no. 1]</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>74 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>University of Michigan Library</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, Michigan</PUBPLACE><DATE>2007</DATE><IDNO TYPE="dlps">0599998.0001.001</IDNO><IDNO TYPE="lccallno">E457.7 .A17</IDNO><AVAILABILITY><P>Where applicable, subject to copyright.  Other restrictions on distribution may apply.  Please  go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Abraham Lincoln quarterly.  [Vol. 1, no. 1]</TITLE><AUTHOR>Abraham Lincoln Association (Springfield, Ill.)</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>7 v. plates, ports., facsims. 24 cm.  v. 1-7; Mar. 1940-Dec. 1952.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Springfield, Ill.]</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>The Abraham Lincoln Association.</PUBLISHER>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Electronic text and image data Ann Arbor, Mich. : University of Michigan Library 2006 Includes both image files and keyword searchable text. [Michigan Digitization Project]</NOTE><NOTE>Supersedes the Association's Bulletin.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2teiutf.xsl on 2007-08-16.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="1"><P>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR). No corrections have been made to the OCR-ed text and no editing has been done to the content of the original document. Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 1 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Lincoln, Abraham, -- 1809-1865.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></HEADER><TEXT N="0599998.0001.001"><BODY><DIV1 NODE="0599998.0001.001:1">
<P>
<PB REF="00000001.tif" SEQ="00000001" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="202" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=1"/>
M ARCHrI94Q
Iý 1
MARC  9
14


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000002.tif" SEQ="00000002" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="264" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=2"/>
44                44~4444~
44444~~~
U              44
4             44                        44~444
2. ~
444,4444                44,~4           44444
444444444~         ~4444
4444    ~         4          4
44   444
444      4444      '44444
I     i(                        ~44'    44
44                                                       4
4j                    44        4
444        4~4                                  44
4~444~~4444444                 44                                              44
444             44
44        4
44~ ~ 4 ~, 4~U
4441
4     44444444      444
*~   4444
4         444                                                                       4
444    444           4
44                            4444
4444     4          44
4444                                          44
444                   444   4          44
444444444
44                      44
44  4   444  4  4
~         j~4   444    4       4
4444     44444   44                44444            44
444444444444444~           444  44        4      44444
44444             44   44444      4          4             4
444      44444          ~4     44
4444 4
44                44
4              4
44        44  44
444444             444        4444
4              4444444    44     4   4   44,44          44444      444      44
~4     ~444'4      444444444      4444         44444                4444     4
4444444444        4    4%44   444444        4444       44
44   4    44444(44444444$      44444                                      4
4444          ~(44~                      ~
44444$4444 44444444444444444                      444;      444 444;444     444444   44~44                     44
444 4U44        444444444 444444444444444  4444444444                  4444    44                           4444
~                       444444444444444444444                              44                      44
444444       444   44;    ~J~44444444~444444   44   444   4        444        4444  4444    44        44                          4                                   44
4     44      44 44   4    44~      44444
444       44                           44
44444444                            44
1
4            44
4*444          4
44444     44*4444  44
~..4444444444  444444  4444..
4444444     44444.
444444444444444 44444444444444444444.44


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000003.tif" SEQ="00000003" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="TPG" CNF="788" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=3"/>
THE
ABRAHAM LINCOLN
QUARTERLY
VOL. I *MARCH, 1940 - NO. I


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000004.tif" SEQ="00000004" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="100" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=4"/>

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000005.tif" SEQ="00000005" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="100" N="1" DISPLAYN="1" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=5"/>

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000006.tif" SEQ="00000006" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="798" N="2" DISPLAYN="2" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=6"/>
FROM A PHOTOGRAPH MADE BY ALEXANDER HESLER IN CHICAGO IN 1858


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000007.tif" SEQ="00000007" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="884" N="3" DISPLAYN="3" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=7"/>
THE
ABRAHAM LINCOLN
QUARTERLY
VOL. I * MARCH, 1940 * NO. I
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186i'
BY J. G. RANDALL
I
THE PURPOSE of this article is to examine those incidents and factors that were involved in the
hardest and most far-reaching decision that
Lincoln ever had to make. It is a subject crowded with
vexation; yet it calls for restudy, especially in this
bedeviled age when general war has incredibly come
to a Europe whose every normal instinct and every
memory since 19I4 cries to heaven against it.
Even so did normal instincts cry out when Lincoln
assumed office, but the forces making for peace were
deep lying and inarticulate, while the alarms and agitations tending toward war were precisely of the superficial sort which in a time of emotional excitement may
1 This article is based on a much longer manuscript, still unpublished, which is
elaborately documented. Statements of fact given herewith without annotation are
nevertheless tied down to sources and documents.
3


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000008.tif" SEQ="00000008" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="4" DISPLAYN="4" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=8"/>
4      ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
disturb the balance of rational life and precipitate a conflict that the majority do not want. One of the most
colossal of misconceptions is the theory that fundamental motives bring war. The glaring and patent fact is the
artificiality of war-making agitation.
What were the conditions in I86o-6 which tended to
plunge the nation into war? There was a background of
whipped-up antagonism between what was called, not
altogether correctly, North and South. Basic cultural
differences were facts that the historian recognizes; that
these differences at any time constituted valid reasons
for war is by no means so evident. Cultural differences,
e.g. between Chicago and downstate Illinois, have often
existed in a nation or a commonwealth without producing war. Southerners of Lincoln's day who found the
Union culturally intolerable and who desired an independent Southern nation for that reason were, according to available evidence, a minority; secession per se
would hardly have carried the South. In the absence of
genuine antagonism there had been years of hectic
propaganda which had dramatized "the North" or the
"Black Republicans" as the enemy, or the potential
enemy, of the South, while a small minority of extremists at the North had harped on the idea that Northern
liberty was threatened by a wicked slaveocracy.
In this atmosphere there had occurred a series of provocative incidents which had inflamed passion. Among
these were the mid-century crisis resulting from the
Mexican War, the Kansas-Nebraska act, vigilante war
in Kansas, the Sumner-Brooks affair in the Senate (in

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000009.tif" SEQ="00000009" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="5" DISPLAYN="5" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=9"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186I              5
volving a Southerner's retaliation to a Northern insult),
the Dred Scott decision, the Lincoln-Douglas debates,
the excitement over escaping slaves, resentment caused
by Uncle Tom's Cabin and Helper's Impending Crisis, the
promulgation of propagandist economics in terms of
"King Cotton," the fanatical and meaningless John
Brown raid, the split in the Democratic party, and the
challenging election of a sectional candidate, Abraham
Lincoln. It mattered not that slavery would not in fact
extend into the territories, nor that the whole fuss was
over "an imaginary negro in an impossible place." Basic
facts seemed not to matter. The true situation was that
the Republican party was pursuing a policy ofmoderation and expediency and that Lincoln in the debates had
disclaimed any radical purpose. He had even said that
he did not favor Negro citizenship, nor did he advocate
social and political equality between the races. What
mattered was that people were told on each side that
they had an enemy on the other side. Those who believed this were probably not the majority, but majorities do not make wars. The enmity agitation was of the
sensationally patriotic type that serves quickly to manufacture public opinion. As of i860 this factor constituted
merely a potential danger; events would show whether
it would become dominant. Ominously it seemed that
the minority trouble makers might be the very ones who
would control events.
In the period of intensified excitement that must be
retrospectively called the immediate prewar months,
leaders of the bolder type had taken "a stand." Uncom

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000010.tif" SEQ="00000010" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="894" N="6" DISPLAYN="6" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=10"/>
6      ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
promising positions had been assumed not so much by
the people ofeither section as by groups and individuals.
It was a matter of finding "quarrel in a straw" when
"honour's at the stake." Stands having been taken, that
abused factor called "honor" or "prestige" or "face
saving" demanded that a holocaust of violence be precipitated upon an unwilling nation rather than that
"demands" be examined and adjusted. In such matters
it is easy to forget that adjustment and conciliation are
as honorable as strife and bloodshed, also that honor does
not require dragging in others. There was the usual
superficial talk that war had to come, that it was inevitable, that it was only a question when and where it
would break. There was less of this than is often supposed, but dangerously enough such talk came to the
lips of those extremists who posed conspicuously as
patriots. Ifpeople, however rashly, declare often enough
that war is inevitable, they may ipso facto make it a
reality. Then, having produced war by predicting it,
agitators may strengthen their case by saying "I told
you so." Thus they pose as the hard-headed patriots who
saw what was coming and did not listen to prattle concerning peace.
In the secession crisis itself, along with the tendency
of a few states to involve other states, there had been the
troublous factor of unilateral action. Demands and assumptions had been too readily accepted as accomplishments. Where various parties to a controversy were
involved, one party had taken action, had produced de
facto changes, had assumed at once that full warrant


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000011.tif" SEQ="00000011" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="7" DISPLAYN="7" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=11"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186I

7

existed for those changes, and had proceeded from there
as if the main question in dispute was already closed.
Realities had not been fully faced; too much had been
taken for granted. At a time when the majority of the
slave states were considering conciliation, South Carolina and other cotton states had so acted that one of
two alternatives had to be accepted: either war for an
objective not even desired by the upper South, or surrender at some point by one side or the other. Emphasis
was too soon shifted from the weighing of objectives to
the distaste of surrender and the hurt prestige of abandoning a governmental position. At a time when it was
easy to do so, leaders had told their people that things
must be done at all hazards. They had prematurely
closed doors for adjustment and discarded instruments
by which demands and objectives could be weighed
against hazards. In short, statesmen had been overbold
in the advance stands taken.
Nor was this all. There was at Fort Sumter a particular locale where these advance stands and these ready
assumptions of hazards seemed to be all concentrated
and distilled. Here was an emotionally unstable danger
spot where a mere incident might be suddenly metamorphosed into a war. This meant that war could come
not so much by any deliberate process as by a kind of
explosion. The cart would be before the horse. An act
of war might happen; then the declaring of war, or perhaps the making of war without a declaration, would
follow. People would suddenly rub their eyes and find
that war existed. From that point, however adventi

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000012.tif" SEQ="00000012" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="8" DISPLAYN="8" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=12"/>
8      ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
tiously reached, the overwhelming wish still to pursue
methods of peace would then be hopeless.
II
Against these tensions there were, of course, basic factors tending toward peace. Peace existed. It was a thing
that the nation already had if it could only value it.
There was widespread Northern sympathy for the
South, matched by true Unionism among Southerners.
There were high-minded leaders who counseled moderation, such men as Crittenden, Douglas, Bell, Everett,
Seward, Lincoln, Stephens, Benjamin Hill, Herschel
Johnson, and Alexander H. H. Stuart. Lincoln's Cooper
Union speech at New York in February 1i860, influential
in obtaining his nomination, was a plea for peaceable
adjustment and for a program oflive and let live. Among
the potential influences for adjustment was the upper
South, the region of Virginia, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Arkansas, where Union sentiment combined
strongly with peaceable impulses. Of equal significance
was the vast border region ofMaryland, Kentucky, and
Missouri, where Southernism in the cultural sense coexisted with vigorous Unionism. In sympathy with this
region were the broad areas of Southern Ohio, Indiana,
and Illinois, in which the people were Southern by
origin and thought. Certainly such people would have
no stomach for an anti-Southern war. If they should
fight because pushed too hard, they would do so with
revulsion and indignation at the failure of statesmen.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000013.tif" SEQ="00000013" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="9" DISPLAYN="9" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=13"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186I

9

Throughout the great Yankee world there was the
wish of the masses of the people to go on living their
lives, the desire of millions that leaders find a way to
peace. Petitions rolled in upon Congress urging not
war and vindictiveness but adjustment. Over twenty
thousand signatures were placed on one such petition
from Massachusetts alone. Some who had voted for
Lincoln regretted the fact when they saw the sorry
consequence in terms of Southern agitation. Southern
editors in this period were not all hotspurs; some of
them bespoke a calm mind and a second thought as
they urged that Lincoln's legally valid election in no
sense justified secession. Some went further and hotly
denounced the agitators in their midst who, as they
said, were driving the Southland to destruction while
blocking all action that involved cooperation among
states of the South acting together. Not all leaders of
one "side" denounced the other side. Many a Northern leader asked for moderation in those things that
aroused Southern anger, such as "personal liberty"
laws which hindered the recovery of slaves. Thoughts
of Southern moderates likewise turned to questions of
adjustment. The actual stuff of controversy was amazingly thin. The "issues" were forced and unnatural.
President and Congress were aware of this popular
demand for peace. The outgoing executive was a man
devoted to the use of law against force, a leader in sympathy with the South, yet zealous for the Union and
resolutely determined to resist warmaking activity. At
the turn of the year his cabinet was reconstructed on


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000014.tif" SEQ="00000014" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="891" N="10" DISPLAYN="10" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=14"/>
I0    ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
vigorous Union lines, but both the earlier and later
Buchanan cabinets favored peace measures. Buchanan
was playing for peace at a time when that was the overwhelming wish ofhis countrymen; yet he was denounced
by Southern extremists for not yielding everything to
them. He has been equally denounced by the other side.
Historically, he has had perhaps the worst "press" of
any Chief Executive. The almost universal condemnation of the man has largely been in terms of the repetition of stereotypes; few writers have honestly and thoroughly restudied his policy step by step with his bitter
problem.
As for Congress, adjustment was its main preoccupation as it pondered Buchanan's patriotic plea for reason,
adjustment, and avoidance of war. Not content with
dependence upon Congress, however, certain groups
labored to effect conciliation in terms ofa national convention or a border-state convention planned for Frankfort, Kentucky. There actually met at Washington a
Peace Congress summoned by Virginia for the purpose
of repeating in i86i what had been done in I850 and
thus producing compromise where secession loomed.
The whole situation could perhaps be summed up as
follows: peace forces were real and deep; war tendencies, though largely false distortions, were ominous and
menacing. It was the premature crystallization of
governmental attitudes, together with the trigger-like
character of the situation that portended trouble.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000015.tif" SEQ="00000015" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="11" DISPLAYN="11" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=15"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

II

III
In the months that intervened between election and
inauguration Lincoln himself was hardly the central
and dominant force. South Carolina rushed ahead with
its little secession, envisaged as a Southern movement
but maneuvered and managed as a separate-state movement. The easy device of a state convention with constituent powers gave strong constitutional sanction to
this development, while on the other hand the Unionists
failed to use a broad national convention of the sort
favored by some ofBuchanan's advisers, nor in the South
was there any all-Southern convention to determine
whether secession should be tried. Secession grew state
by state till it engulfed the lower South. Well before
Lincoln's inauguration seven states had gone out of the
Union and had set up their own confederacy. As Federal forts, arsenals, navy yards, and custom houses in
one Southern state after another fell into secessionist
hands, Lincoln said little, and what he did say in moderation and in honest disclaimer of any aggressive purpose
was too often said confidentially.
On the territorial question, magnified far beyond its
significance, he took an unyielding position and tended
to take the Republican platform seriously at a time
when Republicans in Congress withheld application of
their platform and avoided prohibition of slavery in
territorial acts for Colorado, Nevada, and Dakota. A
recent writer, treating the motives of a mid-western
newspaper in promoting Lincoln's election, shows that


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000016.tif" SEQ="00000016" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="891" N="12" DISPLAYN="12" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=16"/>
12     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
conservatism, some might say expediency, was now
dominant in Republican counsels, and that, according to this paper, "the Republican Party... had
nothing to do with... abolishing slavery or bettering
the conditions of the slaves" (Papers in Illinois History,
1938, published by the Illinois State Historical Society,
p. 53)Congress adjourned without having arranged either
compromise or military preparedness. Amid threats and
rumors of assassination plots the homely new President
traveled to Washington. One wonders how in the preinauguration period he had time to think as he dodged
office seekers, greeted multitudes, struggled with heavy
correspondence, conferred with leaders, selected a cabinet and prepared a difficult inaugural. As best he could
he avoided commitment where possible, at the same time
avoiding offense. Especially difficult were his dealings
with such politician-schemers as Weed and Cameron.
At Washington Lincoln was even more moderate than
at Springfield. Thus in the preparation of his inaugural
address in consultation with national leaders the whole
tendency (as shown in many significant deletions and
insertions made in the process of final revision) was toward conciliation and nonaggression. Peaceable adjustment was the main burden ofthe inaugural; "dissatisfied
fellow-countrymen" of the lower South were promised
peace and noninterference if there should be no attack.
At the same time the holding of Federal "property and
places" (though in as unprovocative a manner as possible) was clearly announced. The inaugural was un

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000017.tif" SEQ="00000017" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="897" N="13" DISPLAYN="13" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=17"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

13

favorably received in the South, where it was even
termed a "war message," though Jubal A. Early of
Virginia, speaking in the Virginia convention, referred
to Lincoln's intent to execute the laws as "a guarantee
that he would perform his duty."
IV
As to Sumter, Lincoln faced a dilemma. Fate had
given this fort an undue emphasis. The near exhaustion
of food for the garrison meant that some kind of executive decision would have to be made; Charlestonian
threats made decision doubly difficult; and any conceivable choice of conduct, whether evacuation or reprovisioning, would, in the distorted circumstances of
the time, be bitterly distasteful. It was not merely the
inheritance of Buchanan's dilemma, though it was
partly that; the difference was that under Lincoln a
change of some sort impended, whereas Buchanan could
deal in understandings, deferments, and status quo.
There was also the fact that any step taken by Lincoln
would be watched as an indication of the policy of an
incoming administration.
Of all the forts in the seceded areas of the South the
only important ones still in Union occupation when
Lincoln became President were Fort Sumter at Charleston (other Federal forts in Charleston harbor having
been yielded) and Fort Pickens at Pensacola. Two
others on the Florida coast, Forts Taylor and Jefferson,
were of minor significance. Trouble had been caused,


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000018.tif" SEQ="00000018" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="14" DISPLAYN="14" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=18"/>
14    ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
though avoidance of conflict had been the intent, by
the removal of Major Anderson's Federal garrison from
Fort Moultrie to Sumter at the end of December i860,
and a serious incident had occurred soon after, when
South Carolinian guns had fired upon a United States
supply ship, the Star of the West. The governor of South
Carolina had taken the position that Sumter must be
evacuated and had shown a tendency to deal with the
fort as a Carolinian, rather than a Confederate, affair.
It was not that he expected a Federal attack from Sumter either under Buchanan or Lincoln. He said definitely
that he did not expect this; yet he asserted that South
Carolina, as a matter of sovereignty and status, would
be under the necessity of reducing the fort. He said this
knowing that it would probably mean war. When the
Confederacy was organized the authorities at Montgomery recognized the same necessity while at the same
time respecting Anderson's honor as an officer and hoping that somehow trouble could be averted.
Neither side actually wanted war; yet hopeless deadlock and complete antagonism of position existed. To
the Confederacy and to South Carolina secession and
entire independence of the seceded area were finalities;
to Lincoln the breaking of the Union was unthinkable.
How far either side considered war too high a price
when separation or Union should be put to the ultimate
test it is not so easy to say. Readiness to accept war if
disunion should be resisted was almost axiomatic at
Charleston and Montgomery, as shown by active military preparations in the South; this did not mean that


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000019.tif" SEQ="00000019" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="15" DISPLAYN="15" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=19"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

15

peace (with disunion) would not have been preferred by
secessionists. Such a radical Republican as Zachariah
Chandler, in opposing the Peace Congress, declared
that without blood letting the Union would not be
worth a rush. On the other hand the atmosphere in government circles in Washington under Lincoln as well as
under Buchanan was far from belligerent toward the
South; indeed a number of Northerners seemed to think
that the erring states should go in peace. This attitude is
usually associated with Greeley, or rather Greeley in one
of his moods, but it was by no means confined to him.
Chase, for example (though this is not widely known),
held this view for a time. Some who thought thus considered that secession would be temporary; others were
ready to accept final separation as preferable to war. It
must be remembered that at this stage only a minority
within the South had acted for secession; the upper
South and the slave states of the border were still in the
Union. In border and upper South the emphasis was
upon conciliation.
In contrast to Sumter, though in status the two forts
were analogous, the case of Fort Pickens was psychologically less provocative. The keeping of Pickens on the
Florida coast would probably not bring war; whether
an effort to hold Sumter against South Carolinian and
Confederate opposition could be so managed as to avoid
hostility was a far more serious question. The Sumter
matter had been the subject of negotiation between
Confederate commissioners and Secretary of State
Seward. Intermediaries had provided a kind of back

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000020.tif" SEQ="00000020" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="16" DISPLAYN="16" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=20"/>
16    ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
stairs communication with officials whom the government of the United States would not recognize, and in
this unsatisfactory way Seward's word had actually
been given that the fort would be evacuated. When the
alternative of evacuating the fort or provisioning the
garrison was put to Lincoln's cabinet (March 15) the
answer was in the Seward sense. Five members advised
withdrawal; one (Chase) gave an ambiguous answer;
Blair alone unequivocably counseled holding the fort.
(When cabinet opinions were again taken two weeks
later only Chase, Welles, and Blair definitely favored a
Sumter expedition. Seward and Smith opposed it, Bates
gave an uncertain answer, and Cameron gave no written
opinion.) Military authorities, including General Scott,
head of the army, advocated evacuation and pointed to
the impossibility of defending the position against
Southern attack. The army could not avoid measuring
its resources against the task it was asked to perform. In
the previous two months the forces and armament of
the United States at Charleston had notably decreased
in comparison with those of South Carolina and the
Confederacy.
In all this prewar excitement and tension there were
three things that Lincoln did not do. (i) He did not order
what would now be called mobilization. For the Lincoln case the term is, of course, a misnomer; warlike
operations in the South would have required a vast
increase of existing forces. The militia of the United
States was a shadowy thing, trained reserves did not
exist, and the regular army numbered no more than six

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000021.tif" SEQ="00000021" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="878" N="17" DISPLAYN="17" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=21"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861i1
teen thousand at a time when the holding of Charleston
alone in case of Southern attack was supposed by some
to require twenty thousand. (2) Lincoln did not issue
or inspire any public statements designed to inflame
passion or intensify Northern hostility against the South.
(3) Lincoln did not attempt to retake any of the already
occupied forts in the lower South. Logic based on Union
premises would have required this as much as secession
logic required reduction or Federal abandonment of
Sumter.
Lincoln did not think of his government as merely
that of the North. It was for him the Federal government for the whole nation. That nation, in logic, could
not be broken by unilateral action; to him secession was
a nullity. Yet logic is not always wisdom, and Lincoln
took care to avoid any demand that captured positions
should be reclaimed by force. To give up the few that
remained was a different matter. That would have
looked like a deliberate choice of Federal surrender. Yet
as he pondered the dilemma, exploring all its phases,
Lincoln studied the evacuation of Sumter for what it
was worth. A conference was held with members of the
Virginia convention which was considering secession.
The subject of this conference was the possibility of some
kind of bargain whereby Lincoln would perhaps renounce Sumter while Virginia would renounce secession. The conference was held very late in the Sumter
imbroglio (later than Lincoln hoped) and in fact it came
to nothing; none the less it appears that thought of this
nature had for some time been in the President's mind.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000022.tif" SEQ="00000022" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="894" N="18" DISPLAYN="18" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=22"/>
18     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
To the historian the incident serves not only to underline Lincoln's willingness to explore peaceable methods;
it also brings into view, as Southern writers have shown,
the uneasy conviction of Virginians that a military outbreak would help secessionists. While serving no upperSouthern objective, such an outbreak would unite upper
and lower South in common opposition to "coercion."
By the same token the more extreme secessionists seemed
to desire the outbreak.
The manner in which the Sumter question occupied
Lincoln's mind is shown by his efforts to get information on the spot. Two close friends of Southern origin,
Ward Lamon and Stephen Hurlbut, were sent to
Charleston as the President's informal emissaries to
report on the situation there. The irrepressible Lamon,
profanely anti-abolitionist in sentiment and full of
Washington gossip, managed to convey to South Carolinian authorities the impression that the fort would be
evacuated, as indeed seemed likely in view of Seward's
commitments. A third exploratory visit, that of Gustavus V. Fox of the United States navy, was due to Fox's
own wish to plan a Sumter expedition and to the President's realization that as long as the Sumter problem
remained open the military and naval possibilities
would have to be studied.
V
After painful deliberation and amid conflicting advice and cruel pressure, Lincoln made his decision. One


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000023.tif" SEQ="00000023" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="894" N="19" DISPLAYN="19" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=23"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

I9

can find his own explanation of this decision in the
message to Congress ofJuly 4, 1861. If this message be
considered special pleading, one can study the orders
and events of March and April, 1861. Both the message
and the contemporary orders serve to underscore one
very important factor: the distinction between Sumter
and Pickens. For the Florida fort Lincoln would do one
thing; for Sumter another. This is true whether or not
one accepts the theory that there would have been no
Sumter expedition at all if prior reenforcement of Pickens had been accomplished. It is an instructive exercise
to note how clear-cut the distinction was between the
two forts and how far it extended. (The orders appear
in the Official Records, Navies, I ser., IV, 9o, 107, io8,
227, 228, 232, 234, 235, ff.; Official Records, Armies,
I ser., I, 235 ff.) The Pickens plan was launched more
than two weeks earlier than that for Sumter. The expedition for Pickens was to proceed without delay and to
act for the reenforcement of the fort. Ships meant for
Sumter were given no such orders to reenforce nor even
to sail, but were directed to be "in readiness for sea
service." The Sumter expedition, though made ready
(and of course the preparation of an expedition, though
tentative, required time) was, in Lincoln's own words, to
be "used, or not, according to circumstances." The Pickens expedition, destined for a point where trouble was
not anticipated, would serve, however partially, to underscore Lincoln's announced plan to hold Federal
property. Before starvation actually descended upon the
Sumter garrison, Pickens could be reached, so Lincoln


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000024.tif" SEQ="00000024" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="888" N="20" DISPLAYN="20" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=24"/>
20     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
hoped, and reenforced without an outbreak. No Federal
attack from Pickens was intended, merely reenforcement. This, Lincoln said in hisJuly message, would be a
"clear indication of policy, and would better enable the
country to accept the evacuation of Fort Sumter as a
military necessity."
How far does this statement constitute evidence of
Lincoln's actual willingness to evacuate? Did he in April
think that a Pickens reenforcement would facilitate acceptance of evacuation of Sumter in the sense of an
expedition being sent and the fort not held, or in the
sense of withholding the expedition itself? The implications of the July message are that under a given set of
circumstances (i. e. the prior reenforcement of Pickens)
Lincoln would have renounced the Sumter expedition
entirely, though Nicolay and Hay are very reluctant to
admit any such possibility. On the other hand those
who doubt the message might assert that, once the two
expeditions had been planned, he meant for them both
to sail. This is a conjectural problem. To the extent that
it involves what "would have" been "if things had been
different," it is perhaps unanswerable, though the historian can point to Lincoln's statement that the Sumter
enterprise was tentatively planned for a "conjuncture"
or a "contingency" and that the unexpected Pickens
failure supplied the contingency that caused it to be sent
forward. What can be established is that April 6, the
very day of the Pickens disappointment reaching Washington, was also the time of various facts concerning
the expedition for Sumter. It was the date of readiness


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000025.tif" SEQ="00000025" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="21" DISPLAYN="21" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=25"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

21

for possible sailing as indicated in Lincoln's order of
March 29 when tentative Sumter preparations began.
This meant that up to this date the expedition could
still be held back. It was the date when an important
instruction to Anderson, informing him that an expedition would go forward, was sent by Lincoln, though it
was dated April 4. It was also the date of Lincoln's instructions to Chew to notify Governor Pickens that a
supply fleet would be sent. Finally, it was regarded as
the date beyond which vacillation or uncertainty as to
sending the expedition would hardly be possible because of the low condition of Anderson's supplies. Even
then, April 6 was not the date of the actual sailings for
Sumter, which occurred mostly on April 8 and 9. In
acting as to Sumter Lincoln's extreme reluctance is illustrated by his waiting not merely till the last day, but till
the eleventh hour.
On April 6 Lincoln learned that his arrangements for
Fort Pickens, the order to Captain Vogdes on March 12
which he considered vital in his Pickens-Sumter plans,
had not been carried out. The reason was a kind of
quasi-armistice or understanding concerning the Florida fort made under Buchanan but not considered binding by his successor. Lincoln was reluctant to give up
Sumter unless authority could somehow be upheld in
terms of his inaugural promise, which he thought might
have been done peaceably by holding Pickens; now the
news of April 6 made his complex plan impossible.
Further Pickens orders would have to be sent, and before
the Florida fort could be reenforced the deadline at


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000026.tif" SEQ="00000026" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="22" DISPLAYN="22" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=26"/>
22     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
Sumter, i. e. the exhaustion of supplies, would be at
hand.
Gustavus Fox later stated that on April 4 the President said he had decided to let the Sumter expedition go.
A few days before this, March 30, Fox had been directed
to go to New York, the point of departure, "with verbal
instructions to prepare for the voyage, but to make no
binding engagements." Even after April 4, however,
Lincoln knew there would be a short interval of a few
days before the Sumter expedition would actually sail,
during which time it could be held up by telegraph. It
was at this critical stage, the Sumter expedition having
not yet sailed, that Lincoln learned of the Pickens muddle. The President, under pressure from firm Unionists
and sternly admonished by old Frank Blair that evacuation would be treason, was under the bitter necessity
of exhibiting firmness at some point; Pickens was the
point he had chosen. None of the Sumter orders were
ever as firm as the Pickens orders. The news of April 6,
however, made it impossible to strengthen Pickens in
time to offset the Sumter situation, since the deadline for
withdrawing or feeding the garrison was fast approaching. "In precaution against such a conjuncture," wrote
Lincoln, "the government had... commenced preparing an expedition... adapted... to relieve Fort Sumter, which expedition was intended to be ultimately
used, or not, according to circumstances. The strongest
anticipated case for using it was now presented, and it
was resolved to send it forward."
At Pickens as well as Sumter United States efforts


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000027.tif" SEQ="00000027" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="876" N="23" DISPLAYN="23" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=27"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861              23
were nonaggressive. Colonel Harvey Brown, U. S. A.,
informed General Braxton Bragg, C. S. A., that he
would hold himself on the defensive. Contemporary
records show "how earnest the wish of Colonel Brown
[under orders from Washington] was that no act of
hostility should be committed which might provoke
retaliation or serve as an excuse... for an attack on the
fort.... (Official Records, Navies, i ser., IV, 129,
138.) On April i 2the Florida fort was quietly reenforced
with no firing and no bloodshed. It showed that such a
thing could be peaceably done.
Attention now turns to one of the most important aspects of the whole crisis, i. e. the purpose of the Sumter
enterprise. When finally and tardily released for sailing,
the expedition still had no peremptory orders to reenforce. The full object was to supply the men with food.
Only in case of attack by the other side were additional
troops to be placed in the garrison, or the attempt made
to do so. There was a further thing: to show that hostile
surprise was not intended, Lincoln sent a messenger
(R. B. Chew) to notify Governor Pickens of South Carolina of his nonaggressive purpose to land provisions.
Provisioning was to be attempted only if Major Anderson's flag was still flying over the fort; there was to be no
attack in terms of an attempted retaking. The major, according to war department instructions written by Lincoln, was expected to hold out if possible till the arrival
of the expedition but not to proceed beyond what would
be usual in military life. After acting on the defensive to
the point of satisfying military pride, he was authorized


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000028.tif" SEQ="00000028" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="24" DISPLAYN="24" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=28"/>
24     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
to capitulate if that should be necessary. One aspect of
these orders to Anderson is that they were the kind that
would have to be given unless a large and really formidable force were to be sent to Charleston. They underline the mildness of Lincoln's Sumter undertaking.
The Sumter expedition sailed without the warship
Powhatan, owing to a bungling of orders as between Lincoln and Welles on the one hand and Seward on the
other. Seward managed to keep the Powhatan for the
Pickens fleet, which, as the diary of Montgomery C.
Meigs shows, was a kind of Seward pet. In this he
showed something very much like defiance, or disregard, of the President. This extraordinary conduct of
Seward was of a piece with his previous negotiations
and unauthorized commitments concerning Sumter.
The incident illustrates the looseness of administrative methods in the Lincoln cabinet, and it also shows
Seward's eagerness to justify his sobriquet of "premier"
by assuming what amounted to presidential functions.
As for Lincoln, while giving the closest attention to
the Chew instructions which were drafted in his own
hand, and while keeping his finger on the methods by
which South Carolina would be notified of non-hostile
intent, he had paid little heed to the ships of the expedition itself, even signing orders without reading them.
In orders as to the use of the ships he had emphasized
caution and avoidance of attack.
It must be remembered that, after all, the main question of the day was the challenge ofa new-formed nation
in the South and the complete deadlock caused by the


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000029.tif" SEQ="00000029" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="892" N="25" DISPLAYN="25" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=29"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186i             25
non-recognition of that nation at Washington. Lincoln
was talking and thinking in familiar terms, while secessionists were speaking a novel language of changed
allegiance, consummated dissolution of the Union, and
displaced Federal authority in the lower South. States
other than the seceded ones were regarded as foreign
nations. On February I6, 1861, Mr. Toombs reported
in the Confederate Congress a resolution in which certain action was to be taken "... against all foreign
countries, except the State of Texas." That Lincoln
should avoid such terminology and speak in established
Federal terms was the thing expected of the President
of the United States. Swift moving leaders of Southern
independence spokeofa dissolved union before the country had time to rub its eyes. Some might say that these
opposite stands made of the Sumter situation an unavoidable test case even though at Pickens an analogous
test of the whole issue was being avoided. The heated
feeling stirred up at Sumter must be taken into consideration; yet the oppositeness of governmental positions
might well be regarded as the nub of the Sumter question. When stands had been taken it was as much to the
point to speak of the logic and determination of Southerners as of their emotions.
To Charleston and Montgomery, where dissolution of
the Union was a fait accompli, the mere sending of the
expedition, in fact the mere non-withdrawal from Sumter, was regarded as invasion. The expedition having
been sent, Confederate officers visited the fort; orders
were examined; Anderson predicted evacuation unless


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000030.tif" SEQ="00000030" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="881" N="26" DISPLAYN="26" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=30"/>
26     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
relieved; he also promised that he would not fire upon
Confederate forces unless attacked. Despite Anderson's
nonaggressive attitude Confederate authorities, to whom
the retention of Sumter spelled coercion, saw no choice
but to reduce the fort. The responsibility of four Confederate aides, who consulted Major Anderson in person, received an answer which went as far as the major
could to meet Southern conditions, and gave the order
to fire without referring the matter either to Beauregard
or Jefferson Davis, has perhaps been overstated. The
historian Rhodes believes that Anderson was earnestly
endeavoring to meet Beauregard half way and that the
action of the aides was due to impetuosity rather than
sound judgment. The other side of the question is that
Confederate authorities at Charleston were under orders from Montgomery to reduce Fort Sumter unless it
should be evacuated. Firing began at 4:30 on the morning of April 1 2; over thirty hours of bombardment occurred without loss of life but with heavy damage to the
fort; on April 13 Anderson agreed to evacuate; on April
14 he surrendered with colors flying, bringing away
company property and saluting his flag. Military courtesy and regard for Anderson's feelings had been carefully observed by Southern officers. Thus it turned out
that Sumter was not held. The few vessels of the relieving
fleet that arrived remained at a distance and did nothing
in the Sumter battle. The force sent to Sumter had been
much smaller than that sent to Pickens; nor was this
force to have been landed at all if attack had not occurred. The Sumter menace had been overstated.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000031.tif" SEQ="00000031" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="892" N="27" DISPLAYN="27" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=31"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN i86i

27

VI
Many post-mortems on the Charleston tragedy, some
anti-Lincoln, some otherwise, have been conducted.
Until the Sumter outbreak peace, though not Union,
existed. Until then Virginia and the other commonwealths of the upper South remained firmly within the
United States. Voluntary evacuation at Charleston
would have been a strong force to hold them there,
though what "would have" been the history of the
Union from that point is not so clear. The Sumter clash,
plus Lincoln's call for militia which immediately followed, put the upper South in such a dilemma as between secession and coercion of sister states that withdrawal soon followed. Above all, the tragedy of the
Sumter imbroglio was that in the immediate sequel
it brought war. Furthermore, Lincoln was considered
by Southerners to have broken a pledge; there is no
doubt that Seward had given a promise of evacuation,
and such a promise was considered meaningless unless
it controlled Lincoln. It seems incredible, but it was
characteristic of Seward that he made these commitments without Lincoln's permission. The charge that
Lincoln knew of Seward's promises has never been
proved. The evidence points the other way.
Anger toward Lincoln was now almost universal in
the South; in Southern eyes he had done the thing
which made it impossible for Virginia unionists to hold
their state. So also North Carolina, Tennessee, and
Arkansas. Each side declared that the other began the


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000032.tif" SEQ="00000032" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="895" N="28" DISPLAYN="28" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=32"/>
28     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
war. Southerners argued that Lincoln's provisioning
expedition amounted to invasion; Lincoln and his
apologists held that he meant no aggression in merely
holding a Federal fort. Logic on each side was faultless;
it was only the premises that differed!
As early as August I, 1861, a theory was advanced as
to Lincoln's motive which has become familiar in recent years. In the Tilden manuscripts at the New York
Public Library one finds a letter of that date from John
L. O'Sullivan, spirited Democratic journalist and champion of lost causes, to Samuel J. Tilden, written at Lisbon, Portugal, in which Sullivan argued that Lincoln's
acts were but an "adroit manoeuvre" to draw Beauregard's fire and "precipitate the attack upon Sumpter
[sic]... for... its... effect upon the public feeling of
the North." This theory reappears in an independent
and scholarly article by Charles W. Ramsdell, published
in 1937 (Journal of Southern History, III, 259-288).
The same interpretation was advanced by Edgar Lee
Masters in Lincoln the Man (p. 391). Professor Ramsdell's
interpretation is in terms of a query which, he says,
"must have" arisen in Lincoln's mind: "Could the
Southerners be induced to attack Sumter, to assume the
aggressive and thus put themselves in the wrong in the
eyes of the North and of the world?" Professor Ramsdell
adds in a footnote: "The general idea ofsuch an outcome
was in the air; the contribution of Lincoln himself was
the maneuver by which this desirable solution was
brought about."
It may be well to summarize Professor Ramsdell's
treatment, though no mere summary can do justice to


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000033.tif" SEQ="00000033" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="29" DISPLAYN="29" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=33"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861             29
the fine balance of his article, in which Lincoln is not
censured but in which the bitter difficulties of his position are appreciatively stated. Professor Ramsdell points
to the disgust of aggressive Republicans at rumors of
evacuation, the balancing need to satisfy moderates,
the inability to restore the Union by compromise, the
necessity to "do something," the advantage to Lincoln
of having the Confederates take the initiative, hence the
motive to induce them to do so. Other points are the
Lamon mission as a camouflage to cover an ulterior
purpose, a "mysterious conference" with Republican
governors (supposed to have urged action), representations concerning the alleged refusal by Virginia unionists of his offer to evacuate, and a discrepancy between
Lincoln's July message and the dates of April orders.
The message through Chew to Governor Pickens Professor Ramsdell calls a threat and a direct challenge,
while the timing of the message to arrive April 8, when
excitement raged high as to newspaper guesses concerning the destination of an expedition known to be
preparing, is treated as giving Confederates time to act
before the fleet should arrive. In addition, rationalizations by Nicolay and Hay as to Lincoln putting the
South "in the wrong" are mentioned. Then comes the
capstone with a now famous statement by O. H. Browning, then senator from Illinois. On July 3, 1861, having
talked with Lincoln, Browning wrote in his diary that
Lincoln spoke as follows: "The plan [sending supplies]
succeeded. They attacked Sumter-it fell, and thus,
did more service than it otherwise could."


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000034.tif" SEQ="00000034" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="30" DISPLAYN="30" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=34"/>
30     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
After noting the high spots of Professor Ramsdell's
account it might be expected that the present writer
would use it as a kind of cue for refutation of the theory
propounded. Such is by no means his intention. Anything like preparing a brief to support one "side" or the
other, would be unprofitable and would constitute the
very opposite of historical scholarship. The writer has
the highest regard for Professor Ramsdell's scholarly
survey of the subject and welcomes his contribution.
Certain things may be beyond the reach of historical
proof. At many a point it will be impossible to reconstruct all that went on in Lincoln's mind. It is not so
much a matter of historical controversy as it is of
evaluating the elements in the problem, of noting that
a given incident would look differently to secessionists
and unionists, and of recognizing that finality is unattainable when the same evidence is susceptible of opposite interpretations. Much of the objective evidence
presented by Professor Ramsdell pertains not so much to
something in Lincoln's mind as to the fact of sending
the expedition and the circumstances under which it
was sent. Aside from the Browning remark, the passages bearing upon Lincoln's motive in what he is known
to have done are largely interpretations or questions
which the historian raises. Professor Ramsdell is on
solid ground in concluding that mere non-evacuation
was aggression or provocation from the secessionist
standpoint, at least at Sumter. Whether it was so in
Lincoln's mind in April 186 I is not so easy to say.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000035.tif" SEQ="00000035" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="880" N="31" DISPLAYN="31" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=35"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861              31
The same evidence that Professor Ramsdell uses,
with the possible exception of the Browning remark,
could be given a non-provocative interpretation. Thus
Lincoln's need to "do something" at Sumter without
appearing to force civil war merely underscored the
desirability that the "something" be nonaggressive;
the doing something did not necessarily imply that war
had to happen because of any Lincoln act. The pressure
of peace men upon Lincoln in April 1 861 was at least
as strong as that of Republican radicals. It is as reasonable to consider the Lamon mission a genuine attempt
to study the situation at Charleston as to call it a camouflage to conceal an ulterior purpose. As for Lamon's
predicting evacuation, that could be explained not as
a Lincolnian ruse but as Lamon's overstepping of
authority. The Virginia consultations are treated with
emphasis upon the disputed question whether or not
Lincoln offered evacuation if Virginia would avoid
secession. It might be equally important to emphasize
Lincoln's wish that the consultations had come sooner
and his distress at Virginia's inability to put its unionism
on a stronger basis than a Sumter evacuation when nonevacuation to Lincoln was a peaceful affair. Lincoln's
July suggestion that the Sumter expedition might not
have been sent except for the failure of the earlier Pickens plan is treated by Professor Ramsdell as unsound
because Lincoln's Sumter orders were on April 4 while
news of the Pickens failure came on April 6. Passing
over the fact that the Sumter expedition could still have
been checked on the sixth and did not sail till later, it


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000036.tif" SEQ="00000036" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="899" N="32" DISPLAYN="32" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=36"/>
32     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
may be noted that this part of the discussion misses the
point of Lincoln's alleged provocative intent. To argue
lack of such intent it is not necessary to postulate a nonsending of the expedition; it would be sufficient to show
that, when it was sent, its manner and purpose were
nonprovocative or were considered so.
The inducing-to-attack argument does not proceed
far before it involves a subtle change of emphasis, so
that the very decision to send the expedition is treated
as the aggressive or provocative thing, whereas the
point at issue is whether the feeding of the garrison was
not considered by Lincoln to be compatible with continued peace efforts. The "mysterious" conference with
governors, even if the implied purpose is admitted,
bears not upon provocative conduct in the sending of
the expedition, but rather upon the alleged urging of
the governors that the fort be not evacuated. It is, of
course, well known that from some Northern quarters
Lincoln was urged to avoid evacuation. It is not shown
that the governors caused Lincoln to adopt an intentionally provocative maneuver, nor that they thought in
terms of inducing war by a first shot on the other side.
The mild and cautious message of April 6 to Governor
Pickens is treated as a threat; it does not read like a
threat and could as readily be taken as evidence that
Lincoln was giving a reassurance and a non-hostile
pledge. What Lincoln said in this message was that an
attempt would be made to supply Sumter with "provisions only," and that if there should be no attack there
would be no reenforcement without further notice. It


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000037.tif" SEQ="00000037" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="33" DISPLAYN="33" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=37"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861            33
is suggested that a man of Lincoln's perspicacity would
know that different interpretations would be put on
these words in the North and in the South, but this
hinges upon the previously stated assumption that the
message was deliberately phrased as a thing of subtlety
and double meaning. It would be as reasonable to assume that Lincoln did not know everything about
Southern feeling, that he overestimated Southern
unionism as a promising or active force, that his message meant what it said, and that it was honestly intended to be so strong an assurance of non-attack as to
overcome Southern suspicion and give the Confederacy
the cue for avoiding attack as Lincoln was avoiding
attack. If it be answered that this was impossible, the
rejoinder is that precisely such an avoidance of attack
on either side did occur at Fort Pickens. The historical
problem bears upon the question how much is proved,
and it may be doubted whether proof has been given
that Lincoln actually hoped that the South would put
the worst construction upon his motives. If suggestions
of a Sumter maneuver were "in the air," urgings toward peace were equally so (being strongly supported in
the cabinet) and Lincoln may have thought that emphasis on "provisions only," together with other circumstances, would take from his undertaking the appearance of a hostile maneuver. As to the implication that
Lincoln sought to stir up moderates to "flame out against
the secessionists and in support of the government"
(p. 272), it may be noted that Lincoln's administration
was the target, not the haven, of radicals, and that


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000038.tif" SEQ="00000038" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="880" N="34" DISPLAYN="34" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=38"/>
34     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
deliberate inflaming of sentiment against the South
was precisely the kind of thing that Lincoln commonly
avoided. Nor do Lincoln's conduct and words in March
and April give evidence of such an inflaming; there are
many opposite evidences. His language was that of
restraint, caution, and cooling off. His maner was as
different as possible from that of the famous Prussian
leader in 187o, and one may question the analogy that
has been drawn between the Sumter policy of the American President and the Ems dispatch of which the aged
Bismarck boasted when writing his memoirs. In this
analysis of the points and the evidence, the purpose is
not to dogmatize. All that the writer urges is that investigation has not reached the last extremity, that the
problem of Lincoln's intent is historically difficult, and
that opposite interpretations of known facts are possible.
Vii
There remains the July remark which Browning attributes to Lincoln. "The plan succeeded. They attacked Sumter-it fell, and thus, did more good than
it otherwise could." This diary record, which the writer
called to Professor Ramsdell's attention before it was
published, is a strong link in his chain. Incidentally it is
about the only link that bears specifically upon the
subjective factor of what was going on in Lincoln's
mind. No one who holds the provocation thesis can
be criticised for attaching weight to this remark; rejection of the thesis would probably have to be in spite of


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000039.tif" SEQ="00000039" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="894" N="35" DISPLAYN="35" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=39"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 186I             35
the remark. The facts of March and April have been
reviewed to show that no part of that evidence is incompatible with a nonprovocative purpose; this July
remark is in a somewhat different category.
Of course it could be shown that the Lincoln-Browning conversation occurred on July 3, that the very subject of the conversation was Lincoln's July 4 message,
that the famous remark is reported to have followed
Lincoln's reading of the message to Browning, and yet
that the remark and message would appear to contradict each other. In the message Lincoln said that Southerners knew the government desired to keep the garrison
in the fort, not to assail them, but merely to maintain
visible possession, trusting to the ballot-box for final
adjustment. This is precisely the opposite ofdeliberately
maneuvering a war. The message comes to us direct in
Lincoln's words, while the Browning statement is an
indirect quotation. One is a formal public document;
the other is a fragmentary bit of reported conversation.
They seem to say opposite things. Which is to be believed? Was Lincoln revealing himself in the reputed
remark to Browning, while using a kind of windowdressing in the July message? If Lincoln did so reveal
himself, did the remark not sound a bit queer immediately after a reading of the message to his friend?
Does the message give a basis for doubting the remark,
or is it the other way round? Was Lincoln merely rationalizing when he wrote the public message (which is
possible), or was he rationalizing when in July he proceeded, after eighty days of actual war, to recall to


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000040.tif" SEQ="00000040" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="881" N="36" DISPLAYN="36" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=40"/>
36     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
Browning what he did in April and to state why? It
begins to appear that the historian is in about as much
of a quandary as Lincoln was, unless he actually takes
sides and does some rationalizing of his own. At any
rate these contradictory elements should be noted.
Since the message and the remark, simultaneously
spoken, suggest opposite July meanings, and since the
remark has a considerable margin of vagueness, we are
thrown back upon the March-April evidence, which in
any case is the main field for historical inquiry. When
two expeditions were preparing, the one ultimately
directed to the fort where popular feeling was keenest
and where trouble might be feared was the one in which
the least provocative conduct was chosen. It is not as if
the Sumter provisioning was a made-up incident; it was,
on the contrary, a necessary thing for Lincoln to do in
the line of duty unless he should give up the fort. Essentially itwas a decision not to evacuate a Federal position.
The expedition was merely to maintain the status quo,
so far as that was possible, by giving food to the garrison.
Only in case of Southern attack was there to be forcible
effort to land troops. As it turned out, this attempted
forcible landing of troops, or even supplies, by the fleet
never occurred. None of the government's actual orders
as to Sumter was of a provocative nature. The expedition was sent with publicity and with prior notification
to Governor Pickens. Had the purpose been to trick the
South into firing the first shot, a leakage of information
as to a supposedly secret expedition with hints as to hostile intent would better have served. Instead of this there


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000041.tif" SEQ="00000041" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="37" DISPLAYN="37" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=41"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861              37
was official notification with emphasis upon non-hostile
intent and with a pledge not to reenforce unless attacked. The cryptic remark to Browning, assuming it to
be properly reported, is part of a conversation in which
Lincoln is quoted as saying that "all the troubles... of
his life had not equalled" those which preceded the fall
of Sumter. When and if Lincoln said the "plan succeeded," he referred, as Browning said, to a plan which
he himself proposed of "sending supplies, without an
attempt to reinforce [,] giving notice of the fact to Gov.
Pickins [sic] of S. C." Thus the Browning passage can
itself be quoted to show that, in the substance of his action, Lincoln was as unbelligerent as a leader can well
be.
The plan that "succeeded" was the doing of a nonprovocative thing, for in what he actually did Lincoln
was giving the Confederacy an opportunity to avoid
attack, if that should be their wish. It is not clear just
why Lincoln said it succeeded; most people would think
that if attack on either side had been avoided, that
would have been success. If a result follows the act of a
statesman, it is natural for the statesman to say, months
later, that he foresaw the result and to justify it. One
must appeal from the justification to the earlier fact.
Had the whole wretched quarrel been deferred to the
ballot box, Lincoln would have had an excellent claim
to success in a sense opposite to that of the Browning
quotation, yet that would not have altered the actual
fact of the manner of the April expedition which in its
execution was about as nonprovocative as was possible,


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000042.tif" SEQ="00000042" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="882" N="38" DISPLAYN="38" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=42"/>
38     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
and which, in the Union view, was as appropriate for
inducing ballot-box settlement (by continuing the
status quo and not giving up the whole case) as for war
settlement. The challenge of the provisioning expedition was certainly no greater than the secessionists'
challenge to the Union. In spite of that challenge Lincoln did avoid attack. If conjecture as to Lincoln's possible intent and ruminations be reduced to a hypothetical question, it might be worded thus: Could Lincoln,
after reluctantly deciding to release the fleet tentatively
prepared for Sumter, have determined to manage the
expedition in such a way as to avoid hostile provocation? Those who have studied Lincoln carefully have
become wary of stating his motives and secret thoughts.
Some of them are unknowable, but an affirmative answer to the question just put is entirely consistent with
the facts as seen in the immediately contemporary record, unless the writer is badly mistaken.
It is in the March-April record that the main story is
to be found. Lincoln's orders and instructions, his conversations with Virginians, his slowness in sending the
expedition, his notification to South Carolina, his nonaggressiveness in the final phase, his adherence to inaugural declarations in which avoidance of bloodshed
was stressed, his studious distinction between Pensacola
and Charleston, and his denial that provisioning Sumter would bring war, are facts which the cryptic remark
to Browning is inadequate to refute. Lincoln does not
appear to have been among those who considered war
inevitable. In the July message, as already noted, he


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000043.tif" SEQ="00000043" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="895" N="39" DISPLAYN="39" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=43"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN 1861

39

spoke of the issue being referred to the ballot-box. The
Confederate commissioners in Washington wrote on
March 12, 1861, to Secretary Toombs that Lincoln had
assured a Louisianian that there would be no war and
that the President was determined to keep the peace.
(Pickett Papers [MSS.], Library of Congress.) The Virginians Magruder and Baldwin state that Lincoln rejected the idea that a Sumter expedition meant war
(Atlantic Monthly, XXXV, 443; House Report No. 3o,
39 Congress, I session, p. 104). In respect to Sumter
Lincoln went no further than Buchanan, the man who
has been so roundly denounced for Northern weakness.
That portion of Lincoln's action which has been treated
as provocative was not a whit more forward or severe
than the procedure of his pro-Southern predecessor.
Orders for Lincoln's April expedition were less of a
challenge than those for Buchanan's Star of the West.
Even before Buchanan had sent this ship, South Carolinian commissioners had severely abused him. Unless
one is to conclude that Lincoln was provocative in his
very nonaggressiveness, it is hard to see how the March
and April evidence bears out the theory of provocation.
If even so non-hostile an expedition as Lincoln's was
casus belli to the South (and one must pay high respect
to Professor Ramsdell's analysis of Southern sentiment
on this point), then indeed was Lincoln in a tight place.
Lincoln's prestige was slight even at the North in 1861.
In secessionist circles his very name was assailed and
cursed, his messenger, Lamon, was almost mobbed at
Charleston, and there are evidences, believe it or not,


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000044.tif" SEQ="00000044" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="881" N="40" DISPLAYN="40" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=44"/>
40     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
that even a willing abandonment of Sumter would have
been denounced by some secessionists as an act of
cowardice and an inflaming of Northern frenzy.Among
extremists on both sides everything done by the other
side in March-April 1 86 1 was given some kind of sinister
meaning. The trouble under which the country suffered
was not so much an expedition sent by a President; it
was rather an ugly deadlock and a background of artificial antagonism. It is a tragic thing that often the boldness of extremists seems to be actually assisted by the
very mildness ofmoderates. For this no particular leader
and no special episode was to blame. In the whole pot of
trouble the Sumter situation was but one ingredient.
Eight decades have passed since secession. After the
gallant Southern record in the war and after such a
lapse of time, any censuring of one section by the other
would be highly inappropriate, and happily such censuring has ceased to be the tone of historical writing.
The purpose of this article has not been to reopen questions of war guilt nor to attempt any conviction or
acquittal of particular leaders at the alleged bar of history. No one section or area had a monopoly of the fateful misunderstandings that led to the tragedy of war.
Whether Lincoln showed supreme wisdom as to Sumter
is a conjectural matter, depending on the unanswerable
question whether voluntary abandonment would, as
some Virginians thought, have promoted both peace
and union. It is rather the unquenchable interest in
Lincoln and everything he did that serves as the reason
for this article. Another reason is the obvious importance


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000045.tif" SEQ="00000045" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="891" N="41" DISPLAYN="41" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=45"/>
WHEN WAR CAME IN I86I

4I

today of restating the needlessness of the quarrels and
irritations that produced the Civil War.
That Lincoln, under pledge to maintain Federal
authority with no need for bloodshed, was drawn by
hard circumstances and by his own sense of duty as
President of the United States into an argument to provision (i.e. to hold) the Charleston fort, which he sought
to do by an expedition which was handled without aggression, is a conclusion which seems to the writer entirely consistent with the contemporary record. It
involves no inconsistency with known facts to conclude
that Lincoln would gladly have avoided an incident at
Sumter if that could have been done without giving
away, as he saw it, the government's whole case. It is
not to be doubted that he turned over in his mind all the
possibilities of the unpromising April scene, including
the possibility that war might come despite efforts to
avoid it. When war did come it turned out that he had
kept the nonaggressive record of his government clear.
In this sense it might be said that the "plan succeeded"
-the United States had not bunglingly thrown the
switch. To say that Lincoln meant that the first shot
would be fired by the other side iffafirst shot wasfired, is
by no means the equivalent of saying that he deliberately maneuvered to have the shot fired. This distinction is
fundamental.
Allan Magruder of Virginia, involved in the President's negotiations with Virginia unionists, disagreed
with Lincoln's April policy while honoring his peaceable motives. Magruder felt that 'Sumter ought to have


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000046.tif" SEQ="00000046" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="888" N="42" DISPLAYN="42" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=46"/>
42     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
been evacuated, but he added: "It seems clear that Mr.
Lincoln had fully resolved on the policy of peace, and
did not mean to permit the war to be inaugurated, if it
were possible... to avert that calamity... All the facts
of the case go to fortify this conclusion" (Atlantic
Monthly, XXXV, 445)

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000047.tif" SEQ="00000047" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="887" N="43" DISPLAYN="43" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=47"/>
THE BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
BY BAYARD TAYLOR
BAYARD TAYLOR is hardly a name today. In his lifetime (1825-1878), however, he was probably as
well known as any literary man in the United
States. Book after book recorded his travels over the
world, personal charm made him a favorite on the lecture platform, and his poems, which filled more than a
dozen volumes, won the praise of critics and readers
alike.
In "The Ballad of Abraham Lincoln" Taylor wrote
in part at least from personal impressions. He lectured
in Springfield in 1854 and 1855; he may have met Lincoln then. At any rate, he saw the President frequently
in Washington during the early part of the Civil War
when he represented the New York Tribune at the
capital. That Lincoln was favorably impressed may be
inferred from the fact that he appointed him secretary of
legation at St. Petersburg, a post which Taylor held
capably for more than a year.
"The Ballad of Abraham Lincoln" was written at
the request of James T. Fields, Boston editor and publisher, for a series of children's picture books. It was first
published by Fields, Osgood  Co. of Boston in 1870.
In 1884 Peter G. Thompson of Cincinnati reprinted it
from the same plates. Both editions are now very scarce,
and the ballad is not included in the one compilation
of Taylor's poetry: The Poetical Works of Bayard Taylor
(Boston, 1i880).
43


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000048.tif" SEQ="00000048" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="880" N="44" DISPLAYN="44" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=48"/>
44       ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
The text of "The Ballad of Abraham Lincoln"
printed here follows the original manuscript in the possession of Oliver R. Barrett, Chicago, Illinois.
THE BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
BY BAYARD TAYLOR
Come, leave the tales you love so well,
Of fairy joy and woe:
Another story I shall tell
Of one whose name you know.
Like him, who was a herdsman's son,
Yet lived to be a king,
His life the highest honor won
Our native land can bring.
His arm was strong, his heart was bold,
His deeds were wise and true;
He did not live in days of old,
But here, at home with you.
And who he was, you can't forget:
You've surely guessed his name;
For all the land is ringing yet
With Abraham Lincoln's fame.
Away in old Kentucky's wild,
Where Nolin's waters flow,
There he was born., a settler's child,
just sixty years ago.
From other settlements removed,
The Indian tribes were near,
And round his father's cabin roved
The brown bear and the deer.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000049.tif" SEQ="00000049" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="401" N="45" DISPLAYN="45" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=49"/>
'(j eAw. ~   ~   yr.  4y e0h-e
I              /
A P F, T   NA, M    I   MEWHAT REDCE
Axs L  ~~ct- Ic~-au/
4A- W-PLTOL~r4  14AL  ac4L~ e,a Y4 4--
A PAGE OF THE ORIGINAL MANUSCRIPT, SOMEWHAT REDUCED


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000050.tif" SEQ="00000050" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="877" N="46" DISPLAYN="46" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=50"/>
46   ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY

Ah! little sport and little joy
In that lone place he knew;
A rugged, tanned, and barefoot boy,
A forest child, he grew.
One blessing, only, cheered his days,A mother, pale and fair,
With kinder heart and gentler ways
Than other women there.
She knew her boy; by many a touch
Of care and watchful love
She did her best-it was not muchTo guide him and improve.
No schools or books were there, to give
Instruction to the youth.,
But yet she taught him how to live
In honesty and truth.
She taught him courage and content,
And patience under pain,
When they had left the settlement
To buy and build again.
And when, at last, the hardships broke
Her strength, awhile she lay;
Of love to God and man she spoke,
And then she passed away.
No church was in the solitudes,
Nor church-yard for the dead;
And so., amid the lonely woods-,
They made the mother's bed.
And little Abraham, weeping there,
Cried: "Mother, I will be
In heart as true, in life as fair
As you have hoped of me!"


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000051.tif" SEQ="00000051" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="878" N="47" DISPLAYN="47" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=51"/>
BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
Beside that grave the boy began
To think, and work, and wait.,To make himself an honest man
And worth a better fate.
Whatever offered to his hand,
On that he set his mind;
There was no boy in all the land
As ready and as kind.
For he would work through sun or snow,
And help, when there was need;
And many a mile he'd gladly go,
To find a book to read.
Few books there were could help impart,
Few teachers could he find:
It was his brave and patient heart
That helped his eager mind.
So year passed onward after year:
The boy grew tall and strong,
And bold of will,-his only fear
To do or suffer wrong.
And now the father, wandering west,
By better promise drawn,
Settled upon the prairie's breast
Beside the Sangamon.
They built themselves a cabin rough,
With walls of logs and clay:
The doors and seats were oak-wood tough,
The beds were prairie hay.
Around the chimney-place they drew
Content., when winter came;
The snow-flakes, whirling down the flue,
Died ere they reached the flame.

47


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000052.tif" SEQ="00000052" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="48" DISPLAYN="48" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=52"/>
48      ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
With scanty space and humblest cheer
The dreary days went by,
Till spring had thawed the frozen year
And warmed the gusty sky.
Then Abraham, strong from steady toil,
Went forth with axe in hand,
And while his father ploughed the soil
He fenced the prairie-land.
Tree after tree, he made them fall,The chestnuts, straight and thin;
With stalwart arm he swung the maul,
And drove the wedges in.
A fence around ten acres rose,
And they who saw it, say
That better, evener rails than those
No man can split to-day.
When all was finished, Abraham said:
"Now, Father, you've a home,
With wood and grass, and meat and bread,
So give me leave to roam!
"I'm twenty-one, and called a man,
And greater grows my need
(As 'twas my own and mother's plan)
To be a man indeed!
"Whate'er I've learned, I'm far behind;
My chances here are few;
And, feed the body, starve the mind,That I shall never do!
"Whatever comes, I will not shirk
My duty clear and plain;
There must be knowledge, must be work,
Which such as I can gain!"


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000053.tif" SEQ="00000053" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="897" N="49" DISPLAYN="49" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=53"/>
BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
Then forth he went. 'Twas hard at first
His bread alone to earn,
While more than hunger, more than thirst,
Was his desire to learn.
He felled the woods, he tilled the land,Hard work and little pay;
Yet honest heart and willing hand
Will always make their way.
The people found that he was true,
That toil to him was light,That what he promised he would do,
And what he did was right.
And soon a flat-boat, laden well,
They gave into his care,
To seek New Orleans, and to sell
The boat and cargo there.
So Abraham, with his river-boys,
Put off, and drifted slow
Past wooded bluffs of Illinois
And castled rocks below.
Missouri's mouth, that stains with mud
The Mississippi's wave,
They passed, and where Ohio's flood
Washes the pirate's cave:Where, westward, woods of cypress stand
In water to the knee:
Where, eastward, rolls the pleasant land
Of fertile Tennessee.
Where came, beyond the deserts born,
Arkansas, bright and blue:
Where Vicksburg rose against the morn,
Beside the dark Yazoo.

49


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000054.tif" SEQ="00000054" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="50" DISPLAYN="50" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=54"/>
50   ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY

On-on, by sun or light of stars
They plied the heavy oar;
Looked out for snags and sandy bars,
And kept away from shore.
So winding with the winding stream,
Still warmer grew the air,
And changed, as in a wondrous dream,
The Southern Land was there!
They saw the rich magnolias grow,
The planter's home to screen:
The ripened cotton shone like snow,
The orange groves were green.
Till every cypress swamp was passed,
And every river bend;
And at New Orleans' wharf, at last,
The voyage had an end.
Then Abraham, faithful to his trust,
The boat and cargo sold,
And home on foot, through mud and dust,
Brought safe the owner's gold.
So trusted afterwards was he,
That all the work he sought
Was offered him, with leisure free
For reading and for thought.
At first, he kept the village store;
But, as his knowledge grew,
The people honored him the more,
And loved, the more they knew.
And when the State election came
For men to make the laws,
They called on Abraham Lincoln's name
To represent their cause.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000055.tif" SEQ="00000055" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="878" N="51" DISPLAYN="51" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=55"/>
BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
In little things a man is tried
Till he is fit for great;
He served his friends., and they with pride
Sent him to serve the State.
Of form uncouth and manners plain,
Yet,, when his voice they heard,
Men felt how sound and clear his brain,
And listened to his word.
Yet more he studied, further rose
From out his place obscure,
Till., working in the path he chose,
He made his fortune sure.
The boy had grown indeed a man,
In power and will complete:
And now a broader life began
To spread before his feet.
His talents first the neighbors knew;
The county knew him then,
And then the State; until he grew
A guide to other men.
His voice was heard in stern debates
Where, eloquent and brave,
He claimed that all our coming States
Should never hold a slave.
His words went ringing through the land
So simple yet so strong,
That soon they roused a mighty band
To meet the threatened wrong.
It was not long before men said:
"He shall our leader be:
His honest heart and good, wise head
Will bring us victory!"

5'


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000056.tif" SEQ="00000056" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="898" N="52" DISPLAYN="52" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=56"/>
52   ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY

They made him then their candidate,
As best of all they knew;
They thought: "So well he served his State,
He'll serve his country too."
Look, where he stands! In thirty years
Since forth from home he went,
From East to West the people's cheers
Hail Lincoln President!
In thirty years the poor young man,
Whose chances seemed so dim,
Stands foremost in the Nation's van,
And all look up to him!
The chosen Chief, he journeyed on,
Received with glad acclaim,
Until to stately Washington
Across the land he came.
There on the marble portico
He took the solemn oath,
No separate North or South to know,
But justly govern both.
Alas! you know what followed then:
How many, led astray
By words and acts of wicked men,
Brought on Fort Sumter's day.
Brought on the day that lit the land
With war's devouring flame,
Till North and South on every hand
To siege and battle came.
You know it all: you can't forget
The names of many a day,
When, armed for death, our blue-coats met
The Southern coats of gray.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000057.tif" SEQ="00000057" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="879" N="53" DISPLAYN="53" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=57"/>
BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
You saw the Union's heroes go
With trump and rattling drum:
And then-in solemn march and slow,
You saw their coffins come.
You saw the Nation spend its life,
Its blood like water poured:
You saw, thank God! to end the strife,
The Union's power restored.
Ah., who can tell how Abraham felt
Through all those fiery years!
How many times to God he knelt,
And prayed for help, with tears!
He said: "The sin of Slavery
Has brought this war and woe:
I now proclaim the black man free,
And I will make him so!"
'Twas done; thenceforth his path was bright,
His cause, as all men saw,
Was that of Freedom and of Right,
Of Union and of Law.
God prospered him, and when his end
Of service was at hand,
The people cried: "He still must mend
The troubles of our land."
They chose him: he renewed the oath
Alike for North and South,
And words that touched the hearts of both
Came kindly from his mouth.
"With firmness in the right we've won,
We stand, whate'er befall,"
Said he_,-"with malice unto none,
With charity for all

53


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000058.tif" SEQ="00000058" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="877" N="54" DISPLAYN="54" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=58"/>
54   ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY

"God has His own high purposes:
As He wills, let it be!
We pray the day may come that sees
The land united, free!"
And scarce a month thereafter passed
Before the earnest prayer
Was heard, and victory came at last,Yea, victory everywhere!
What shouts went up when Richmond fell!
Grant took the sword of Lee.,
And trumpet, cannon, drum, and bell
Announced, "The land is free!"
In Richmond streets among the first
Was Abraham Lincoln then:
He walked where late his name was cursed
By desperate Southern men.
But., chanting their thanksgiving psalm,
The slaves came-, clamorous:
They shouted: "God bless Abraham,He has delivered us!"
They pressed around him as he went,
They laughed and wept for joy,The gray-haired negroes, worn and bent,
The mother and her boy.
Though anxious years had made him sad,
Yet tender was his eye,
And, such an earnest face he had,
Some knelt as he passed by.
Alas! as Moses on the height
Saw Canaan, green and fair,
He knew the truth, and saw the sight
Of Peace he could not share.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000059.tif" SEQ="00000059" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="877" N="55" DISPLAYN="55" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=59"/>
BALLAD OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
He heard the roar of battle die;
The land no more was red;
Then up to heaven there rang a cry:"The President is dead!"
'Twas thus-, in his triumphal hour,
The coward murderer came,
And killed him at the height of power
And fulness of his fame.
Ah, when was ever grief so deep
As that we felt for him!
The memory of it still we keep,
And still our eyes are dim.
A gloom on all the nation fell;
The cities held their breath.,
While muffled drum and funeral bell
Pealed out the march of death.
By millions wept, his burial car
Across the land was drawn.,
To lay him on his prairie far
Beside the Sangamon.
And there, where once the honest youth
His lonely life began,
He sleeps,-the soul of right and truth,
The pure, immortal man.
Wherever men are sore oppressed,
Where hearts in bondage bend,
All mourn for him., in East or West,
For they have lost a friend.
And not his State or land alone
Shall build his future fame:
Through all the world the worth is known
Of Abraham Lincoln's name!

55


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000060.tif" SEQ="00000060" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="887" N="56" DISPLAYN="56" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=60"/>
NEWLY PUBLISHED LINCOLN LETTER
T      HE FOLLOWING letter,believed tobe published here
for the first time, was written to Simeon Francis,
founder of the Sangamo Journal of Springfield.
In 1855 Francis had sold his paper, then, as now, called
the Illinois State Journal, and had removed to Oregon.
At the time this letter was written he was editing the
Daily Oregonian of Portland. Soon after the outbreak of
the Civil War, Lincoln appointed him paymaster with
the rank of major, and in that capacity he served
throughout the war.
The text below follows a photostatic copy in the possession of the Abraham Lincoln Association. The original letter is owned by the Oregon Historical Society.
Springfield, Ills. Aug. 4, I860
Friend FrancisI have had three letters from you-one, a long one, received in
February; one, telling me of the deputation of Mr. Greely' to cast
the vote of Oregon, in the Chicago convention, received a few days
before that convention; and one written since you knew the result
of your Oregon election2, received a few days ago. I have not, till
now, attempted an answer to any of them, because I disliked to
write you a mere note, and because I could not find time to write
at length.
Your brother Allen has returned from California, and, I understand, intends remaining here. Josiah3 is running his J. P. court,
about as when you left. We had a storm here last night which did
1 Horace Greeley, editor of the New rork Tribune, was one of Oregon's five delegates
to the National Republican Convention of I86o.
2 Members of the legislature and state officers were elected on June 4, 1860. At the
election the Democrats, already in the majority, made further gains.
I Another brother.
56


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000061.tif" SEQ="00000061" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="895" N="57" DISPLAYN="57" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=61"/>
NEWLY PUBLISHED LETTER

57

considerable damage, the largest single instance of which, was to
the Withies. A wall of their brick shop building was thrown in, and,
it is said destroyed ten thousand dollars worth of carriages-I have
heard of no personal injury done.4
When you wrote, you had not learned of the doings of the democratic convention at Baltimore; but you will be in possession of it
all long before this reaches you. I hesitate to say it, but it really
appears now, as if the success of the Republican ticket is inevitable.
We have no reason to doubt any of the states which voted for Fremont. Add to these, Minnesota, Pennsylvania, and New-Jersey,
and the thing is done. Minnesota is as sure as such a thing can be;
while the democracy are so divided between Douglas and Breckenridge in Penn.  N. J. that they are scarcely less sure. Our friends
are also confident in Indiana and Illinois. I should expect the same
division would give us a fair chance in Oregon. Write me what you
think on that point.
We were very anxious here for David Logan's election.) I think
I will write him before long. If you see Col. Baker,6 give him my
respects. I do hope he may not be tricked out of what he has fairly
earned.
Make my kindest regards to Mrs. Francis; and tell her I both
hope and believe she is not so unhappy as when I saw her last.
Your friend, as ever
A. Lincoln
4 "About half-past seven o'clock on Friday evening, this city and vicinity were
visited by a heavy storm, the severity of which far exceeded that of any we have experienced this season.-Before seven o'clock its approach was indicated by the dark
masses of clouds rolling up from the West, canopying the whole earth with their gloomy
blackness. Their pent-up fury burst up a few moments after seven, and in twenty
minutes thereafter it was raging with terrific power. Buildings were blown down and
unroofed, trees were uprooted, and shrubbery and grain prostrated to the earth. An
accompaniment by heaven's heaviest artillery added to the terrible effect of the scene.
"The injury sustained by some of our citizens is very severe. The heaviest losers
are the Messrs. Withey, whose carriage manufactory was completely demolished." Illinois State Journal, Aug. 6, i86o
5 David Logan, a son of Stephen T. Logan, Lincoln's second law partner, emigrated to Oregon in 185o, and soon made a reputation in both law and politics. He
was elected to the Oregon legislature in 1854 and to the state's constitutional convention in 1857. At a special election on June 27, 1859, Logan was defeated for representative in Congress by only sixteen votes. In I86o he was again the Republican candidate, but was defeated by 104 votes.
6 Edward Dickinson Baker, Lincoln's long-time friend, was elected United States
Senator from Oregon in October, I86o, by a coalition of Republicans and Douglas
Democrats.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000062.tif" SEQ="00000062" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="871" N="58" DISPLAYN="58" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=62"/>
FAMOUS LINCOLN COLLECTIONS
The Illinois State Historical Library
W ~EL L OVER two hundred autograph letters and
documents of Lincoln constitute the heart of
A)Vthe Lincoln Collection of the Illinois State
Historical Library. Chronologically these range from a
signature on a petition to the Sangamon County Commissioners' Court dated March, 183 i-one year after
Lincoln's settlement in Illinois-to a telegram to Gen.
Nathaniel P. Banks sent from City Point, Virginia, on
April 5' 1865-ten days before his death. In size they
vary from small cards to an eight-page letter. In character and importance they cover the whole range of
Lincoln's writings.
The collection is especially rich in early documents.
Included are a number of poll books in Lincoln's handwriting, testifying to his service as an election clerk at
New Salem; several surveys represent that phase of his
life. Legal documents as early as 1837 illustrate the
beginnings of his professional career, while others show
his steady progress from an obscure practitioner to
leadership at the bar of Illinois.
Many letters relate to matters of outstanding 'importance, both in Lincoln's life and in the affairs of the
nation. The collection contains the remarkable series of
letters which Lincoln wrote to Elihu B. Washburne of
Galena between 1854 and i 86o-a series which could
almost be described as a history of the Republican
58


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000063.tif" SEQ="00000063" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="899" N="59" DISPLAYN="59" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=63"/>
FAMOUS LINCOLN COLLECTIONS

59

Party in Illinois during these critical years. Another
series of letters and telegrams to General McClellan
throws light on one of the most heart-breaking episodes
of the Civil War-the Peninsular campaign-and portrays Lincoln's mounting doubt of his commander's fitness. Numerous letters and telegrams to "Fighting Joe"
Hooker, Gen. John A. McClernand, Gen. Nathaniel
P. Banks and others exemplify Lincoln's relations with
his major commanders.
To designate any single letter or document as the
finest in the collection would be a rash undertaking, but
one of the candidates for this honor would be Lincoln's
letter of August 26, 1863 toJames C. Conkling, together
with the several telegrams which relate to it. This letter,
which was sent to be read at a mass meeting at his old
home, has been described as Lincoln's last stump speech.
Certainly it is one of his greatest political arguments.
Rarely, moreover, did he reach greater heights of eloquence than he did in its conclusion: "Peace does not
appear so distant as it did. I hope it will come soon, and
come to stay; and so come as to be worth the keeping in
all future time. It will then have been proved that
among free men there can be no successful appeal from
the ballot to the bullet, and that they who take such appeal are sure to lose their case and pay the cost. And
then there will be some black men who can remember
that with silent tongue, and clenched teeth, and steady
eye, and well-poised bayonet, they have helped mankind on to this great consummation, while I fear there
will be some white ones unable to forget that with


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000064.tif" SEQ="00000064" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="880" N="60" DISPLAYN="60" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=64"/>
6o     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
malignant heart and deceitful speech they strove to
hinder it."
In printed Lincolniana the collection of the Illinois
State Historical Library consists of approximately 4,000
books, pamphlets, broadsides and cartoons relating
wholly or in major part to Abraham Lincoln, his immediate family, or his ancestry. To describe a collection
of this size in detail is obviously impossible. All that can
be done is to indicate something of its scope and quality
by mentioning a few rare and unusual items.
Of the first (i 86o) campaign biographies of Lincoln
the collection contains at least one edition of all except
three-the very rare Vose life, and one Welsh and one
German biography. On the other hand, two titles are
included which apparently are not to be found in any
of the other large public collections: I. Codding, A Republican Manual for the Campaign (Princeton, Illinois,
i 86o); and an anonymous work in German, Das Leben
von Abraham Lincoln, nebst einer kurzen Skizze des Lebens
von Hannibal Hamlin (Chicago, i186o). Moreover, nearly
all the truly rare items which Lincoln collectors seek
are represented. Without attempting an inclusive list,
one may specify as typical the Fish bibliographies of
I9oo and 19o6; the Oakleaf bibliography; Frederick
Hill Meserve, The Photographs of Abraham Lincoln; Ben:
Perley Poore, The Conspiracy Trial for the Murder of the
President, including the rare third volume; an edition
of this same work in ten parts in paper, no other copy
of which is known to exist; and the folio edition of Tributes to the Memorj of Abraham Lincoln (Washington, 1885).


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000065.tif" SEQ="00000065" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="897" N="61" DISPLAYN="61" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=65"/>
FAMOUS LINCOLN COLLECTIONS

6i

The Illinois State Historical Library has many "association" copies-that is, books "associated" in unusual
or especially appropriate ways with certain individuals
-but there are two in the Lincoln Collection which deserve particular mention. One is Isaac N. Arnold's own
copy of his book, The History of Abraham Lincoln, and
the Overthrow of Slavery. Heavily marked and annotated, this copy was obviously used by the author in the
preparation of his later and better known work, The
Life of Abraham Lincoln. The other book is a copy of
Ward Hill Lamon's The Life of Abraham Lincoln, inscribed and presented by the author to John Hay, and
bearing many of Hay's marginal notes and corrections.
Thus in one book two intimates of Lincoln who wrote
important books about his life are associated.
The Lincoln Collection includes a large number of
prints and photographs and two paintings, by George
H. Story and William Coggswell, from sketches drawn
from life. Excelling the portraits in artistic merit but
lacking their documentary value are six miniatures, five
of Lincoln and one of Mrs. Lincoln, by the late William
Patterson. The work of a fine artist thoroughly familiar
with his subject, these miniatures will preserve a faithful
record of Lincoln's appearance for centuries.
Memorabilia, or what might be called association
articles, can be found almost without end in the collections of institutions and private individuals. Unfortunately, many if not most are of doubtful authenticity. In
the Lincoln Collection, however, are several articles of
established genuineness-Lincoln's shaving mirror; the


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000066.tif" SEQ="00000066" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="891" N="62" DISPLAYN="62" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=66"/>
62     ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
original doorplate from his Springfield home; a pair of
his riding gloves, with a letter from Robert T. Lincoln
to Gen. C. C. Augur stating that he was sending the
gloves as a mark ofappreciation for Augur's sympathetic
aid at the time of the President's funeral. On deposit,
though not the Library's property, is the desk on which
Lincoln wrote his first inaugural address.
Although not considered integral parts of the Lincoln
Collection, the Illinois State Historical Library possesses
several collections of manuscripts which have great
value for the study of Lincoln's life. Most important of
these are the following: (i) the Gen. Christopher C.
Augur Collection, comprising several hundred letters
and papers of a distinguished Union commander; (2)
the Nathaniel P. Banks Collection of approximately
2,000 letters, mainly of the Civil War period, received
by a famous Republican leader and Civil War general;
(3) a collection of ninety-six reminiscent letters and
statements written at the time of the Lincoln Centennial; (4) the complete papers ofJohn A. McClernand,
Springfield lawyer, Democratic leader and Union general, numbering more than I0,000ooo letters and documents; (5) the complete records of the National Lincoln
Monument Association, the organization which built
the Lincoln Monument at Springfield; (6) the Jesse J.
Ricks Collection, comprising more than a hundred important letters of men prominent in American life
during Lincoln's lifetime; and (7) the papers of Richard
Yates, Civil War governor of Illinois.
In addition, the Illinois State Historical Library pos

</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000067.tif" SEQ="00000067" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="883" N="63" DISPLAYN="63" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=67"/>
FAMOUS LINCOLN COLLECTIONS               63
sesses practically complete files of Springfield newspapers-the Sangamo Journal (later known as the Illinois
Journal and the Illinois State Journal), and the Illinois
State Register, the one Whig and Republican, the other
Democratic. These files alone constitute a source of
information for Lincoln's life of almost unparalleled
richness.
P.M.A.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000068.tif" SEQ="00000068" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="878" N="64" DISPLAYN="64" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=68"/>
NEWS AND COMMENT
The Abraham Lincoln Quarterly, of which this is the first number,
supersedes the Bulletin of the Abraham Lincoln Association, first
published in 1923 and issued quarterly since 1927. Like the Bulletin., the Quarterly will appear at intervals of three months, but in
almost every other respect it will differ materially from its predecessor. The Bulletin printed little besides the writings of the secretaries of the Abraham Lincoln Association; the Quarterly will contain frequent articles by other contributors. Each number will contain some original document and news of interest to Lincoln
students and collectors. For the immediate future at least, a series
of articles about outstanding collections of Lincolniana is planned.
A Lincoln photograph will be a regular feature of each number.
The Abraham Lincoln Quarterly is but one manifestation of a new
program upon which the Association has embarked. In the past
the principal effort of the Association has been to discover and
make accessible hitherto unknown facts about the life of Lincoln,
particularly during the Illinois period. Henceforth, without neglecting research, the Association plans to increase its emphasis
upon the interpretation of the facts already accumulated., and at
the same time to bring Lincoln's Presidency more frequently within its purview. The Quarterly is planned as the principal medium
for the accomplishment of this end. Results of original research
will be embodied in separate volumes which will appear on an
average at the rate of one a year. The Abraham Lincoln Association
Papers will be discontinued.
The editors of the Quarterly will welcome the criticisms and suggestions of readers.
James G. Randall., author of the leading article in this issue, is
Professor of History at the University of Illinois. He is the author
of Constitutional Problems under Lincoln (New York, 1926),. and The
Civil War and Reconstruction (Boston, 193 7). An article of his, "Has
the Lincoln Theme Been Exhausted?," which appeared in the
American Historical Review for January., 1936., aroused much comment and has served as a chart for investigators since its publication. Professor Randall is at present President of the Mississippi
Valley Historical Association.
64


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000069.tif" SEQ="00000069" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="889" N="65" DISPLAYN="65" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=69"/>
NEWS AND COMMENT

65

The Lincoln Group of Boston, which is now in its third year,
meets five times a year, usually on the anniversary of some significant date in Lincoln's life. The members read and discuss papers,
participate in round table discussions of controversial subjects, and
occasionally visit places of interest in the vicinity. F. Lauriston
Bullard, chief editorial writer of the Boston Herald, is president of
the group, which has a membership of thirty-eight at present.
As this is written, the Lincoln Group of Chicago has held seventy-seven luncheon meetings since its organization. The group was
formed in 1931 for the purpose of encouraging research in the life
of Lincoln, and to promote the dissemination of information about
him. For the first eight years of its existence, the group's chairman
was Governor Henry Horner of Illinois. Judge John C. Lewe of
Chicago now holds that position. J. Henri Ripstra is executivesecretary. Many notable speakers have appeared before the group
since its organization, and the program for 1940 includes addresses by Fern Nance Pond of Petersburg, Illinois, and M. L.
Houser and L. O. Schriver of Peoria.
In 1936 the Lincoln Group of Chicago issued The Lincoln Group
Papers-a volume of addresses which had been delivered before it.
A second volume is now being prepared for publication.
I---------~ t-~1 -----------
On December 14, during the week when "Abe Lincoln in
Illinois" played in Cleveland, Raymond Massey, who takes the
part of Lincoln in the play, was guest of honor at a luncheon at the
City Club. In addition to Massey, short talks were made by Mayor
Harold H. Burton, Albert Woldman, author of Lawyer Lincoln, and
Anthony L. Maresh, President of the Lincoln Association of Ohio.
After the luncheon many of those who were present visited the
Weddell House, where Lincoln spoke on February 15, 1861, while
en route to Washington.
The Lincoln Association of Ohio, well represented on this occasion, has approximately three hundred members.
Raymond Massey and Anthony L. Maresh were signally
honored when they were presented with Diplomas of Honor by


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000070.tif" SEQ="00000070" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="889" N="66" DISPLAYN="66" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=70"/>
66       ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
Lincoln Memorial University on June 5, 1939. In presenting the
diplomas Dr. Stewart W. McClelland, president of the University,
said: "From the Lincoln standpoint, we prize this Diploma of
Honor higher than an honorary degree. Honorary degrees are
given for a variety of reasons, but only those who have done something genuine in the field of Lincolniana will ever receive this
diploma."
--    *-.,qam-9 --------
Lincoln Memorial University continues to be a focal point of
Lincoln interest. Prof. R. Gerald McMurtry, head of the Department of Lincolniana, states that he has sent the manuscript of his
Lincoln Log Cabin Almanac to the printer, and that the booklet will
be published about mid-February. Prof. Earl Hobson Smith, head
of the Dramatics Department, is the author of a play, "President
Lincoln," which will probably be in print before the appearance
of this number of the Quarterly. The southern premiere of the
photoplay, "Abe Lincoln in Illinois," will be held at Lincoln
Memorial University, probably during the latter part of January,
1940.
Harry E. Barker, known to thousands of collectors as a dealer in
Lincolniana, has in press a booklet dealing with Lincoln's life in
Illinois, which will soon be published under the title, An Hour with
Lincoln. Mr. Barker, long a resident of Springfield, Illinois, now
resides in Los Angeles, where he serves as curator and archivist of
the Lincoln Fellowship of Southern California.
Another member of the Lincoln Fellowship of Southern California who will have a book appear in the near future is Frank
Brooks Cowgill, author of A Trilogy of Lincoln Verse. Mr. Cowgill's
new volume will be entitled Columbia's Martyr and Other Lincoln
Tributes, and will be limited to ioo copies. Orders may be placed
with F. Ray Risdon, Transamerica Building, Los Angeles. Mr.
Risdon is Secretary-Treasurer of the Lincoln Fellowship of Southern California.
The Long Beach (California) Lincoln Club, an active organization, entertained the Lincoln Fellowship of Southern California at
Long Beach on October 14, 1939. Among the several speakers of
the occasion were two men who in their youth had seen Lincoln--


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000071.tif" SEQ="00000071" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="893" N="67" DISPLAYN="67" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=71"/>
NEWS AND COMMENT

67

Col. George Huntington of Long Beach and Dr. F. D. Blakeslee of
Los Angeles. Jessie Boyd Husband is President and John G. Spielman Secretary of the Long Beach Lincoln Club.
Miss Genevieve Young, curator of the Lincoln Shrine, Redlands, California, announces that Lincoln's Birthday in February
will mark the eighth anniversary of the Shrine. At ceremonies to
be held on Sunday, February i I, the principal speaker will be Dr.
Bruce Baxter of Willamette University, Salem, Oregon. Dr. Baxter
will be introduced by Dr. Robert Watchorn who, with his wife
Alma J. Watchorn, presented the Shrine to Redlands.
The Lincoln Group of Wilmington, Delaware, which is defined
by one of its members as "an entirely voluntary association without any charter, by-laws or officers," will hold its annual dinner on
February 12, 1940. The group, in the formation of which the late
Frank G. Tallman of Wilmington was influential, meets once each
year, with about seventy-five individuals present. At the dinner in
1939 Honore Willsie Morrow spoke on the subject, "Sources and
Methods of Writing Lincoln Books." This year the speaker will be
the editor of this magazine.
We are informed by Harcourt, Brace and Company that the
volume of review space accorded Carl Sandburg's The War Years
was unprecedented. Critical opinion, moreover, has been almost
universally enthusiastic. The book had a sale in advance of publication of 8,500 sets; by January I, I940-one month after it was
published-the sale had mounted to 18,ooo sets. In dollar volume,
such a sale is equivalent to 144,000 $2.50 books.


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000072.tif" SEQ="00000072" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="891" N="68" DISPLAYN="68" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=72"/>
R. R. DONNELLEY  SONS COMPANY, THE LAKESIDE PRESS, CHICAGO


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000073.tif" SEQ="00000073" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="789" N="69" DISPLAYN="69" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=73"/>
THE
ABRAHAM LINCOLN
ASSOCIATION
OFFICERS;
LOGAN HAY, President         MARY E. HUMPHREY,Vie President
HENRY HORNER, Vice President  ROBERT E. MILLER, Treasurer
Louis L. EMMERSON, Vice President PAUL M. ANGLE, Secretar
H. E. PRATT, Executive Secretary
DIRECTORS
LOGAN HAY               HENRY M. MERRIAM
PASCAL E. HATCH::ALICE E. BUNNi
J. PAUL CLAYTON         GEORGE W. BUNN, JR.
HENRY HORNER            CHARLES L. PATTON
BENJAMIN P. THOMAS
THE ABRAHAM LINCOLN ASSOCIATION is a not-for-profit corpora
tion which has as its principal purpose the collection and dissemination of information regarding all phases of the life of Abraham
Lincoln. The Association is supported principally by the dues of
its members, which are five dollars annually forjunior members
and library members, and ten dollars annually for sustaining
members. All members receive the Association's publications,
which are The Abraham Lincoln Qarterly and an annual volume on
some phase of Lincoln's life. Titles ofbooksalready published will
be furnished on request.
THE ABRAHAM LINCOLN QUARTERLY
The Abraham Lincoln Quarterly is published four times a year, in
March, June, September and December. It is sent to allmembers
of the Association, and may be subscribed for by non-members
at the rate of three dollars annually.
PAUL M. ANGLE, Editor
GEORGE W. BUNN, JR. and HARRY E. PATT, Associate Editors


</P>
<P>
<PB REF="00000074.tif" SEQ="00000074" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNS" CNF="232" N="70" DISPLAYN="70" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=alajournals;idno=0599998.0001.001;debug=xml;c=alajournals;seq=74"/>
1)


</P>
</DIV1></BODY></TEXT></DLPSTEXTCLASS>