<DLPSTEXTCLASS>
<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245">The American Jewess: Vol. 1, No. 1</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>8 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>University of Michigan Library</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, Michigan</PUBPLACE><DATE>2004</DATE><IDNO TYPE="dlps">TAJ1895.0001.001</IDNO><AVAILABILITY><P>These pages may be freely searched and displayed. Permission must be received for subsequent distribution in print or electronically. Please go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245">The American Jewess</TITLE></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>9 v. : ill. ; 25 cm.  Vol. 1, no. 1 (Apr. 1895)-</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>[Chicago :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>R. Sonneschein],</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>[1895-1899]</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Title from caption.</NOTE><NOTE>No v. 3 issued; none published Oct. 1898; vol. 7, no. 5 erroneously called v. 8, no. 5.</NOTE><NOTE>Copy lacks v. 5, no. 3.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script marcb2tei.xsl on 2004-06-10.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="2"><P>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR). No corrections have been made to the OCR-ed text and no editing has been done to the content of the original document. Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 1 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. Digital page images are linked to the text file.</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>English</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Jewish women -- Periodicals. -- United States</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></HEADER>
<TEXT><BODY>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:1"><BIBL><TITLE>Advertisement</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000002.tif" SEQ="00000002" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="712" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=2"/>
Vomankind===
It will be a Luxury in case of Illness or Misfortune
to have a Deposit of Money in this Savings Bank.
Now is TURN OVER A NEW LEAF And don't
the time to                      put off until
take a bee-line      N TME         tomorrow what you
for the Bank and                      should do today.
open a Savings                      Delays
Account.  BOOK Of ECONOMY.     are dangerous.
LIBRIAy
01 COmoR       Savings Accounts can be opened by Depositing ONE DOLLAR OR MORE at the
Louls SAFE DEPOSIT AND SAVINGS BANK
513 Locust Street....St. Louis, Mo.
Open IEvery Day from 9 A.4. M. to 4.30 P. AT. Satclrday Fvenlings froml 6 to S.
WHENEVER YOU THINK OF_       _      _    _     _
Fine Table China,,
Rich Gut Glassware
Ornamental Porcelains
China Knick-Knacks
ILamps, Etc., Etc.
THINK OF
Columbus Memorial Building...State and Washington Streets,
CHICAUO.




A. M. Rothschild &amp; Co.
''This immense building covers the
entire block on the east side of State
street, from Van Buren to Jacksos,       N   EW
with the exceptios  of forty feet at
the latter corner. It is three hssndred
and sixty feet in length b oie hund —
eed csd fsety-five fee Itdepth           DEPARTMsEeNT
AV          stories in height and has two hundred
A%,            and fifty-two windows on the front.
The Van Buren street corner is already built and will be open for busiThe Most            ness not later than May i. It is ex-   STo       R   E...
pected that by March It 896, the
whole big establishni u i l be inl
Wonderful.ThesStructure will have      AW
Wonderful           a frou t of iron and Fretlch plate glass,  A"
and will have, among other moden      A
Department                   appliances, fourtee b elevators. One       CHICAGO,'
Department             of the features will be an imniense      C    IA      O
electric tower on the Van Buren and
Store in      the    W   orld     Slate steet corer, whih will have          ILL.
Ilearly three thousatld electric lights.



</P><P><PB REF="00000003.tif" SEQ="00000003" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="212" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=3"/>
W, -   -   'i,,-.  -* -  i.  K  3  +,, t'  '  * '  *.  a, *:,  e  h
r:..            f'
*R'.
s~~~ * *?*
v..     * '* *
*'   '   *



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:2"><BIBL><TITLE>April</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000004.tif" SEQ="00000004" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="756" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=4"/>
APRIL.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:3"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Sonneschein, Rosa</AUTHORIND><TITLE>A Modern Miracle.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">1-9</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000005.tif" SEQ="00000005" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="893" N="1" DISPLAYN="1" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=5"/>
VOL.


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.
I.               APRIL, I895.             N
A MODERN MIRACLE.
ROSA SONNESCHEIN.


ro. I.


VERY year, when the Easter
bells ring through the Neutra
Valley, the peasants tell their
children the tale of the "Modern
Miracle." The little ones who hearken
to the story for the first time, clinch their
chubby fists and twitch the corners of
their besmeared lips ominously, and every
time the legend is ended, the little hands
relax and the tiny mouths open wide with
wonder. The following day they timidly
avoid the Jewish boys, and Rachel and
Sarah in their new Easter garments are
vastly admired, but shunned. Another
day and all is forgotten; Jewish and
Christian children again commingle in
merry play.
I will now relate what the peasants
of the Neutra Valley tell their children.
Nestling at the foot of the Carpathians
lies the ancient little town of Zomra.
The inhabitants, like the surrounding
mountains, are a primitive, hardy race.
Nearly two-thirds of the population are
peasants, the remainder Jews, with the
exception of a few aristocrats and beaurocrats, arrogant despots who oppress
with equal cruelty both Jews and peasants. But the tyranny of these visible
masters is infinitely less than that exercised by ignorance and superstition.
Scarce sixteen years ago, when for the
first time the iron steed rushed through
the peaceful Carpathian valley, the
Zomra peasants fell upon their knees,
crossed themselves, and with eyes closed
and teeth chattering, prayed their pater
noster. Not until the puffing and roaring of the locomotive had grown fainter


in the distance, did the most courageous
dare to gaze after the black monster,
which snorting and creaking and belching forth great volumes of gray smoke,
was disappearing among the mountains.
Then they flew back to their huts, and
told their wives and children how the
veritable old Nick had rushed roaring
through the valley. The whole town
was in an uproar.
The Jews alone smiled at the apparition, for tramps had often told them
how the steam engine had revolutionized
the outside world. Some in the community had seen it before; the few
wealthy merchants who bought their
stock in Pesth and Vienna had even
traveled on it. Therefore the Jews remained passive, when on the next day
all the able-bodied masculine peasantry,
armed with scythes and flails, sallied
forth to give battle to the locomotive.
And when they returned with pallid
faces, breathlessly describing how the
great fiery eyes of the monster had
glared at them fiendishly, and the swinging scythes and flails had broken in
thousands of pieces, the Jews laughed
heartily. The more stupid of the peasants slunk away abashed, the smarter
ones shook their thick heads knowingly,
and the few sly ones began to suspect
the true inwardness of the case that:
"Jews and the smoking black devil were
both fashioned from the same brimstone. "
Balmy zephyrs heralded the approach
of spring in the valley, and brought as a
morning greeting the Feast of Easter
r



</P><P><PB REF="00000006.tif" SEQ="00000006" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="2" DISPLAYN="2" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=6"/>
2


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


simultaneously for Jews and Christians.
The shimmering snow on the mountain
peaks alone, sparkling and glittering in
pristine purity, mocked the dancing sunbeams. Through the valley rang resonant the bells, calling the faithful to
mass. As they wended their way to
church, the people cried jubilantly " Our
Savior has arisen," and the Jews preparing for Seder, murmured gratefully,
"The chains of captivity are broken."
But long ere the mass was finished, a
suppressed excitement might have been
observed in the church, and when at its
close the venerable priest, with folded
hands, exhorted them all most earnestly
to implore the Saviour for peace on earth
and good will towards men, the entire
congregation sank on its knees, swayed
by profound emotion. Each understood
the meaning of this prayer. Yesterday
evening the seventeen-year old niece of
the master baker, Honved Lojos, had
suddenly disappeared. The most intense
excitement reigned amongst the peasants.
The Easter bells alone had power to
calm temporarily their turbulent feelings.
But directly after mass, the entire masculine peasantry broke up into searching
parties to scour wood and mountain in
quest of the missing maiden. In the
meanwhile, the women folks chattered
unceasingly in their huts. The Jews in
alarm, sidled furtively through the deserted streets, knowing and fearing the
uncouth rage of the rabble. And thus
evening fell. The pretty Christian with
the long blond braids had not been found.
Glancing timidly about, the Jews went
to the Synagogue; their wives sighed
whilst preparing the Seder and donned
their festal robes in tears. And when,
later, the members of the family sat praying at the table, many a man believed
himself and family near the grave. Full
well they knew how the peasants explained the girl's mysterious disappearance. Did they not still hold firmly to


the ancient superstition that on the holy
Passover, the Jews' ceremonial required
Christian blood?
In the streets, the throng of people
was growing larger and larger. Furious
women, raving men impatiently awaited
the signal for plunder and slaughter.
Suddenly a piercing cry arose amidst the
frantic throng. " Let us hear what Ilma
Holosy has to say," and a thundering
chorus resounded, "Away to Ilma! Away
to the witch! " The shouting, raving,
cursing mass of humanity rolled out
into the open country. Like pallid spectres the Jews cowered in their dwellings.
Soon their muttered prayers fell upon
the death-like silence of the streets, like
distant spirits' sighs.
Far beyond the limit of the town gate,
on the edge of a mountain ravine, in a
crumbling hut embedded in rank weeds,
lived Ilma Holosy. She too had been
fanned by the balmy spring breezes; in
her ears also rang the tolling church
bells. But the clearer their holy clamor
the deeper grew the grim rage in the
furrowed face of the prematurely aged
woman. For her every stroke chimed
out "Revenge." Once she had been
beautiful, this hideous witch of Zomra,
so beautiful that young Israel Ben Levy
had fallen head over ears in love with
her. For two years the love-sick seventeen-year-old youth met the scarce one
year younger girl almost daily in wood
or field, often, too, in the boy's home,
where Ilma kindled the Sabbath fires.
And they never tired of talking again
and again of their great love. Neither
ever gave a thought to the old or the
new faith. Their faith was in each
other-until-thirty-one years ago, on
an Easter morn, when the bells rang
as solemnly as to-day, and the balmy
breezes fanned the bare branches of the
trees just like to-day, Ilma met her Israel
on the street. She was on her way to
church, he to the temple, but instead of



</P><P><PB REF="00000007.tif" SEQ="00000007" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="895" N="3" DISPLAYN="3" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=7"/>
A MODERN MIRACLE.


3


that they both went out into the fields.
There the boy told his sweetheart what
his father had decided upon yesterday.
He must go away, far away, to Pressburg. "And how long must you stay
there? " asked the young girl, trembling
like an aspen leaf.
"Until I am a Rabbi," was his low
reply.
" Rabbi-you, Israel, a Rabbi? " cried
the startled girl, " and what will become
of me?"
The youth's head sank on his breast.
The bells sounded like to-day, and gentle zephyrs fanned the snow-clad mountains. It seemed then, as now, a hideous nightmare. Before she was aware
of it he was gone-gone forever.
Years rolled on. In vain did Ilma
wait for Israel. When at last he returned
he became the chosen Rabbi of Zomra
and-married.
Only once did the girl see the Rabbi's
young wife-a frail, lovely creature. It
was then that the passionate love of the
Christian was transformed into boundless hatred for the Jews.
Once only did Ilma exult jubilantlywhen the Rabbi's young wife was laid to
rest.
Vividly spoke the tolling Easter bells
of the painful past. She still saw herself joyfully watching the funeral procession. Then she fled, away from the
gaze of the people, out into the isolated
hut.
But soon the people came to her.
Thieves, robbers, assassins, the unhappy
and the lovers. She studied the heart
of man and tortured it. The secrets of
the peasantry, the wiles of the nobility,
the hopes of the brides, all lay bare before her. She brewed her draughts for
rich and poor, and soon she became the
dreaded famous witch of Zomra.
And how fared the Rabbi? He, too,
had dwelt with sorrow. Bereft of wife and
son, the years had grudgingly left him


only a child - his grandson, little Jacob,
who, nestling in his grandfather's heart,
had healed the old wounds and now held
sovereign sway. All Zomra knew this.
The woman in the hut thought of it as
she intently listened to the tolling of the
chimes. The long gloomy shadows of
twilight had fallen over mountain and
dale, and with grizzly dishevelled hair
the woman still crouched at the window
of her cheerless abode meditating revenge. The green eyes of the large
gray cat gleamed sympathetically at her
mistress; an ancient raven came hopping nearer. Suddenly subdued singing was heard in the next room. The
cat curved her back in displeasure and
the raven'croaked dismally.
"Silence, girl," cried the witch, " my
pets hate your singing."
The voice in the next room was
hushed, but the raven croaked more and
more shrilly.
" Croak, croak old fellow!" cried the
woman, gnashing her toothless gums.
"Revenge is ours; they shall suffer,bleed,- die!- the whole lot; first the
boy, then he, then-"
Here the cat caught the witch's ragged dress and the raven flew against the
wall. The old woman ran to the door,
hearkening breathlessly. The full moon
was slowly rising. Its mellow rays fell
with enchanting splendor on the ruined
hut and on the weird features of the old
witch as she strode rapidly back to the
window.
"They come, they come!" she cried
triumphantly; and in her worn face
the eyes danced and flashed fitfully,
like glow worms. Cat and raven jumped
up on the window-sill. A dark mass
came slowly moving through the brush.
At last the crowd arrived in front of
the house. The witch tore open her window, and screamed shrilly:." Not a step
nearer! What do you want? "  At the



</P><P><PB REF="00000008.tif" SEQ="00000008" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="892" N="4" DISPLAYN="4" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=8"/>
4


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


head of the throng was Lojos, the leading master baker of Zomra.
"I must speak with you, Ilma," he
shouted in response.
"What do you want?" roughly called
the woman.
"Julcsa disappeared from my house
yesterday; we cannot find her anywhere. '
"How does that concern me? " muttered the woman.
"You shall tell us where the girl is,"
he answered.
" And have not the Jews Easter, today? " asked the woman.
" Yes, yes!" shouted a multitude of
voices.
"Why need you ask me then?"
sneered the witch, laughing shrilly.
A storm of fury shook the crowd. A
thunderous roar arose: "Back, back!
Down with the Jews! "
"Halt! " shouted the witch, snatching
up the cat and jumping out of the window. "Wait until I consult with my
familiars and with the stars."
The multitude remained motionless.
As Ilma stood in the moonlight with
face upturned to the starry firmament,
she inspired a more profound terror than
ever before. At last she threw the cat
high in the air. The creature fell at
her feet.
"Honved Lojos, I must speak to thee
alone. Follow me, the rest can wait,"
said the witch, imperiously, striding into the hut. The tall, muscular form of
the master baker detached itself from
the mass and followed. Ten minutes
after he stepped out again. His pallid,
terrified features shone ghastly in the
moonlight. With shaking knees he approached the people; in his hand he
carried a parcel.
"What's the matter Lojos? What
has happened?" they cried in eager
chorus.
The baker tried to speak, but only


those nearest him heard him. With pale
faces they whispered his words to their
neighbors, and thus the message was
transmitted from mouth to mouth, until
all knew what Ilma had advised Lojos
to do.
Grave and subdued, the peasants returned to town.   As they marched
through the streets of Zomra they beheld the brilliantly illuminated windows
of the Jews. The light still burned in
celebration of the Passover, and the singsong of the last prayer fell on the ears of
the returning peasants. Their glances
grew more and more venomous. Presently the singing Jews also heard the
heavy tread of the peasants. The books
were quickly closed and the lips moved
faintly: " Next year in Jerusalem."
Hardly had Lojos turned his back on
the witch when a violent knocking was
heard in the adjoining room. "Open,
Ilma. Let me out," cried an impatient
voice.
The old woman grinned as she went
to the door and drew back the bolt. A
pretty round face appeared bathed in the
moonlight.
"Oh, Ilma, I must go away from here,
I am afraid," exclaimed the girl, quickly
stepping into the room.
" Of what are you afraid? " said the
woman, gravely.
" I saw and heard everything," stammered the girl.
" Well, and what do you want to do?"
"Go back to my uncle," whispered
the pretty maid with downcast eyes.
"And give up Janko?" asked the
witch sternly.
" But they will kill the Jews," sobbed
the child, pulling at her blonde braids.
"Why need you bother about the
Jews, cried the witch, angrily. " Leave
them to their God. He can save them if
He likes. He or I. We will see who is
more powerful, He or I," laughed the
witch, scoffingly.



</P><P><PB REF="00000009.tif" SEQ="00000009" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="895" N="5" DISPLAYN="5" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=9"/>
5


A MODERN MIRACLE.


I


The girl began to tremble in every
linb.
"Back into your room, little fool,"
commanded the witch. "I told you
yesterday, that nine days you must brew
the draught yourself, and nine nights you
must dream of him or Janko will marry
the Rabbi's Linka. Now I tell it to you
again. But do as you please, go or stay."
The girl shivered under the icy gleam of
those dreadful eyes. The blonde braids
glided from her hands; in vain- the parted
lips strove to utter a sound. Once more
the brown eyes gazed at the witch timidly and beseechingly. Then the eyelids
fell, the blonde head drooped, and utterly subdued, the girl glided back into
her room. Smiling maliciously Ilma
again bolted the door.
The chaste mountain summits had not
yet been kissed by the lips of a new
morn when the door of the Rabbi's
dwelling was opened and Ben Levy
issued forth. Slowly he turned the corner of the house and looked searchingly
up and down the street. Nothing was stirring; the tall, slender, slightly stooped
figure of the Rabbi leaning against the
white wall looked like a spectre in the
early dawn. The cold morning breeze
blew on the pale, clear-cut features, on
which cruel fate had left its impress.
His eyes were fixed on the baker's shop
at the end of the long street, whose
lighted windows shone in the darkness.
The apprentices worked there every
night until the morning broke. During
the Easter week, when the Jews ate no
bread, work, of course, ceased earlier.
Hence, the door opened presently and
six floury apprentices stepped into the
dark street. The tallest and strongest
of them drew a small round brandy
flask from his pocket, took a long pull,
smacked his thick lips and strode whistling up the street. As he neared the
Rabbi's house his gaze was fastened intently on the room occupied by the servant.


"Good-morning, Janko!" said the
Rabbi.
The fellow, who had not perceived Ben
Levy, gave a slight start, but quickly
pulled off his cap responding, " God be
with you, Reverend sir."
"How is Lojos? Did you find Julcsa
yesterday?" inquired Ben Levy, still
leaning against the wall.
" Oh the frivolous hussy ran after her
fellow into the wide world," muttered
the apprentice as he walked on.
The slender fingers of the Rabbi
stroked the long, dark beard framing his
pale face. Gratefully his eyes looked upward and his lips moved as if in prayer.
Then he walked musingly towards the
door. A buxom young girl came rushing toward him.
"It was you, then, Reverend sir,"
cried the girl gasping for breath. "I
was frightened to death when I saw the
front door open."
"Linka, be so kind and send me the
sexton," said Ben Levy not attending to
her words.
"But Reverend sir, little Jacob may
wake up at any moment," protested the
girl.


"I will take care of him. Now hurry
to Jeiteles."
"Be sure you don't let the child cry;
tell him I will be right back," she exclaimed as she started to run. The
Rabbi in the doorway smiled as he looked
after her. " That girl is a jewel. What
would have become of the child without her unceasing care," he said gently
as he entered the house.
Rabbi's Linka, as she was commonly
called in the town, had given her whole
heart to the little one-year-old Jacob the
moment she first beheld him. For six
years she had guarded him like the apple
of her eye. In return, the boy clung to
his nurse with a devotion so passionate that at times it even aroused the
grandfather's jealousy. No one could



</P><P><PB REF="00000010.tif" SEQ="00000010" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="6" DISPLAYN="6" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=10"/>
____                                   _ -


6


THE AMERICAN JEWESS


control and guide the child like Linka.
He came to her with his great and little
troubles and she comforted him as only
a mother would have done. The girl
was a strict Catholic and. very pious.
It was for this very reason, perhaps, that
she so conscientiously fulfilled the Jewish
religous customs in the household. She
placed ceremony above faith.  Hence
she insisted strictly that little Jacob
should minutely observe all the laws,
both mandatory or prohibitive. If he
tore a bit of paper on the Sabbath or
touched a piece of money, she would
immediately rush to the Rabbi and announce the sin, for she firmly believed
the Rabbi alone could propitiate the
angry God of Israel.
She had entered the Rabbi's house as
a girl of sixteen and in the course of time
had involuntarily adopted the language
and gestures of the Jews to such a
degree that strangers frequently took
her for a Jewess, despite her pronounced
Slavonic type. The Rabbi went straight
to the nursery and gazed lovingly at the
sleeping boy whose delicate features were
such a faithful reproduction of his own.
" May the Lord protect thee from the conflicts He has visited upon me,"' sighed the
pious man. His thoughts reverted to
the past; they clung about the brightest
spot of his youth, which afterwards became the darkest. He was very fond of
Ilma, she was dearer to him than any
other girl, but he had not been so seriously infatuated as she. And yet during his entire life, Ilma's fate had beento him a constant reproach. He had earn
estly striven to make her life more pleasant, had employed his full influence to
withdraw her from her loveless existence. He had instigated offerings of
home, money, positions; but, suspecting
the real donor, she had scornfully rejected
everything. "He wants to appease his
conscience," she said furiously gnashing
her gums, "but I will prevent it. He


shall carry the thorn in his heart during life, and when we are both dead it
shall be burnt into him forever." The
woman knew how to torment a great and
noble soul. These were the Rabbi's
thoughts on this lovely Easter morning.
He thought also of his young wife, how
she had suspected the worm gnawing
at his heart, how broken spirited and
crushed she had sunken into her early
grave. And of his little daughter! Had
he not striven faithfully to preserve
that frail being, only to see her shortly
after marriage fall a prey to the great
destroyer? All that a relentless destiny
had left him was this little grandchild
and who could tell what fate held in
store for him. Such were the Rabbi's
thoughts as he stood on this early
Easter morn watching the sleeping child.
Hasty steps awakened him from his
reverie. Panting, pale, and trembling
in every limb, the sexton ran into the
room.
" What has happened, dear Rabbi?"
he cried from the door. Righteous God,
how frightened I was when the Sc/zickse
(Christian girl) awoke me. I was just
dreaming-may no Jewish child dream
the like-God forgive me the sin, but I
saw the whole congregation swimming
in blood. Righteous God! " he shrieked
wringing his hands. " But what else
have we to expect? Do they not believe
firmly that we have butchered the girl? "
"That is why I sent for you. The
girl-'"
" Gracious God! Then she is really
dead," shrieked the little haggard man.
"Do not shout so, or you will wake
up the child," said the servant entering
the room.
" Peace, Jeiteles, and let me speak,"
said the Rabbi sternly. "Julcsa ran after
her lover. Her uncle knows it. That is
why I sent for you. You will immediately place yourself at the door of the
Temple and tell all entering what you



</P><P><PB REF="00000011.tif" SEQ="00000011" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="893" N="7" DISPLAYN="7" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=11"/>
7


A MODERN MIRACLE.


heard. Your wife is to do the same in
the ladies' gallery so that the congregation can praise their God with joy."
Not only did Jeiteles open wide his
little, red-rimmed eyes, but the girl's
clear blue orbs were also fastened in astonishment on the Rabbi, as he so calmly
related the story about Julcsa.
And what a divine service it was on
this first day of Easter! The Jews of
Zomra had never prayed like to-day,
their faces had never been so radiant
with happiness. Every heart beat in
devout bliss. Now the Rabbi's voice
resounds, " For thou our God, our Lord
makest the wind to blow and the dew
to descend." Never had the voice of
the Chasan been so sweet and bell-like
as now when he trilled jubilantly "To
the blessing of all and the curse of none, "
and never were more heartfelt thanks
given than when the entire congregation responded, "Amen."
"To the life of all and the death of
none, " trilled the cantor still more soothingly, more consolingly. And loud and
gratefully the congregation again responded " Amen."
"To the satisfaction of all and the
harm of none," came the joyous trills
from  the Cantor's throat.  " Amen,
Amen, Amen," it echoed from all sides
so that the words of the Rabbi were almost lost. Only the closing sentence reverberated through the wide and lofty
space.
" Thou loosest our bonds and preservest Thy faithfulness." Dim with tears
every eye was raised to the beloved
teacher, every heart felt the hidden
meaning conveyed by these ancient
words. The joyous Easter week had
passed.  The danger which had cast
its dark shadow so threateningly upon
the Jews at the commencement of the
Passover, had been averted with such
unforeseen rapidity that all hearts overflowed with rare feelings of delight.


Young and old rejoiced. Engagements
were celebrated amidst mirth and dance,
lovers teased good-naturedly, friends exchanged frequent visits, the poor were
bountifully remembered; in short, a happy festal air reigned throughout the community.  Thus the last Passover eve
arrived when even the best natured and
most frugal of the congregation had tired
of the matzos, and longed for the first
bite of bread. The children especially
munched at their Easterbread most impatiently.
Rabbi's Linka was just resorting to all
her powers of persuasion to induce little
Jacob to eat his matzos, but the child
continued stubborn, pushed them peevishly away and cried:
" I don't want the matzos any more."
" But, little Jacob," implored the girl,
"you cannot go hungry to bed."
"Why can't I if I like?" cried the
boy pouting.
This argument found the girl unprepared. She meditated a few moments
then began cajolingly: "I will tell you
something, little Jacob. If you will eat
your matzos now, I will give you a
whole big loaf of bread to-morrow evening."  The boy's dark eyes looked
searchingly into the girl's blue ones. A
happy smile broke over his face. "If
you promise, Linka, I believe it; but
don't forget-a whole big loaf with lots
of butter."
"Yes! Yes! Now eat, sweetheart. It
is late."
The boy cast a last furious glance at
the matzos and gobbled them up with
feverish haste, knowing this to be the
only way of getting rid of them. Soon
after his little head sank wearily on the
girl's shoulder.
Linka undressed him tenderly and laid
him in his little white bed. "You must
say your S'chma Isroel, little Jacob, " she
said, shaking him. The red lips moved


i;
il
I
i
II



</P><P><PB REF="00000012.tif" SEQ="00000012" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="892" N="8" DISPLAYN="8" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=12"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


mechanically, the weary eyes closed and
Linka's work for the day was over.
An hour later, Janko, the baker's apprentice, joined her in the kitchen. The
fellow was tall, broad-shouldered and
robust with health and strength. The
girl pretended not to see him and continued sewing. She knew that Janko
loved her and would have loved him in
return if he were not a drunkard. His
hot breath, redolent with the fumes of
alcohol, fanned her cheek now, and his
protruding eyes gloated upon her. "You
do not seem overly pleased with my
visit," he said, coming closer to her and
taking her hand.
" Let me alone, Janko. I must work."
"Work, always work. You shall
work no longer," shouted the fellow
angrily.
"And what else shall I do?" began
the girl, glancing at his heated face.
" Marry me," replied Janko, gravely.
"Marry you!" laughed the girl.
"Now you come to me because Julcsa
ran after some one else," she teased
coquettishly.
"You know I don't care a rap for
Julcsa. You know that I love only
you," declared the young fellow, placing his arm around her neck.
" Yes, yes. I am good enough now,"
continued the girl, teasing and retreating
from him. "If Julcsa hadn't run away
you-"
"Julcsa never ran away at all," interrupted the apprentice.
" Why, you told it to the Rabbi yourself," the girl insisted.
" That is no reason why it should be
true," grinned Janko.
" Then you are a liar, and I will believe
nothing you say," cried the girl, shrugging her shoulders.
The man already excited by brandy
and love grew violent. "You must believe me," he shouted furiously. "You
shall believe me."


" Well, if I must-tell me where Jul
csa is, since you know everything,"
scoffed the girl.
"Julcsa is dead," said Janko, in a
voice that made the girl shudder.
"Janko," she screamed in terror, "you
did not-" she dared not continue.
"Murder her," hissed Janko. "No,
not I, but the Rabbi."
"Miserable wretch, you lie!" cried
the girl, beside herself. " My Rabbi
could not kill a fly."
"Nor does he need flies for his Easter,"
laughed the man loudly, " but Christian
blood that ascends straight to Jehovah's
nostrils. "
"Who told you such nonsense?"
asked the girl.
" Everybody knows that."
"Who told you my Rabbi butchered
Julcsa? " asked Linka sternly.
"Ilma Holosy!"
At the mention of that omniscient
name the girl reeled as if struck by
lightning. She then sobbed and cried,
" Ilma said so, Ilma Holosy! My God!
my God! then it must be true."
Covering her face with both hands
her body shook with sobs. This outburst
of grief drove Janko to his wits' ends,
but recovering himself quickly he sat
down close to the weeping girl.
"Do not cry, do not cry, Linka," he
implored, tenderly pressing his lips to
her neck. At his touch the girl recoiled.
"No nonsense, girl. In a few days
you will be my wife."
"But I don't like you," she sobbed.
"Oh, you will like me, never fear,"
laughed he. "Just wait until I give
you golden chains, diamond rings,
strings of pearls and real corals."  The
tearful eyes of the girl looked up at the
man in alarm.
"Janko, it seems to me you are
crazy," she cried.
"I know what I know," he smiled,
indulgently.



</P><P><PB REF="00000013.tif" SEQ="00000013" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="892" N="9" DISPLAYN="9" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=13"/>
A MODERN MIRACLE.


9


"'Where are you, poor devil, going to
get diamonds and pearls? " she asked.
" That is none of your business if you
only get them," he muttered.
"Janko wants to have gold and jewels," scoffed the girl.
" And you don't, perhaps," cried the
man wrathfully. " Would n't you like
to wear Esther Freund's pearl necklace
and Miriam's corals and Sarah Goldstein's diamonds? "
The girl's eyes gleamed with cupidity.
"And Rosa Meisel's heavy gold
chain," continued the man; "and her
mother's long earrings? Don't you believe they would become you, Linka?"
The girl's breast heaved tumultuously.
" And I tell you you shall wear them.
Believe me, girl," he cried, caressing her.
"But, Janko, you always said you
were poor," she stammered bashfully,
clinging closely to him.
'' And I am poor now. But to-morrow
I will become rich, very rich, and everything will be yours," he cried, drawing
her to his breast.
She hid her head on his shoulder.
"Janko, I can hardly believe it," she
murmured, in a stifled voice.
"You shall believe me," he cried,
pulling her down on his lap.
" But how can it be true, Janko?"
" Can you keep a secret?" whispered
the apprentice.
" Yes," assured the girl.
" If you give me a kiss, I will tell you
a great secret."
The girl's curiosity overpowered her
maidenly reserve. She put up her lips


to Janko, who pressed upon them his
first kiss, so passionate and unending
that the girl had to struggle to disengage herself.
"Now you are mine!" exulted the
love-sick youth. " Now you shall hear
everything."
He bent over her and whispered in
her ear. The girl's face expressed increasing anxiety.
"And what did Ilma advise?" she
asked, flushed and trembling.
The man bent still lower.
Then the girl uttered a piercing shriek
and sank back into her chair. Quick as
a flash the man's hand was over her
mouth.
"Not a word, I say, or it will be your
last," he hissed between his set teeth.
The girl lay in her chair limp and
speechless.
Janko glared at her a few moments and
then departed, with a final recommendation that she observe the utmost caution.
The clock on the kitchen shelf slowly
ticked for ten minutes and then struck
the hour. Aroused by the noise, the
girl raised her head, shuddered, and
with a curious effort rose to her feet.
With lagging steps she dragged herself
wearily up to her room. The first object which met her gaze was the little
iron crucifix hanging against the wall.
Throwing herself on her knees before it
she broke into a passion of sobs. Making the sign of the cross she implored:
"Holy Saviour, have mercy! Help
Help! for Thou alone canst help."
(Continued.)



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:4"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Hirsch, Emil G.</AUTHORIND><TITLE>The Modern Jewess.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">10-11</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000014.tif" SEQ="00000014" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="883" N="10" DISPLAYN="10" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=14"/>
THE MODERN JEWESS.
EMIL G. HIRSCH.


HE last decades of the nineteenth century will probably
live in history as the age of
woman's emancipation. Mighty as are
the changes, both social and political,
which have marked the flying years of
the latter half of this wonderful century,
there is none which in its far-reaching
consequences may be held to surpass the
movement, the impelling motive of which
was to admit woman to a plane of equality with man. What the American and
French revolutions accomplished for the
male half of humankind, this quieter, but
all the more persist- 't.ent struggle, wrought
for their sisters.     -
Every  war has its
heroes. The generals
in this fight will also
live in song and mem- n:
ory.
Ridicule was the
first battery to be silenced. But its shots  I /
once proven to be e     /,/         /
harmless against the
cuirass of a stout resolution, the battle for
recognition was more
than half won. All            EMIL G.
that was needed was
for woman by her own capabilities to
demonstrate her eminent fitness for the
position  coveted  by  her.  Medical
science in league with deep rooted prejudices had long countenanced grave
doubts as to woman's strength to endure
the excitement and withstand the wear
and tear of the fierce race. Her staying
qualities riddled the most strongly fortified demonstrations to the contrary of
her sceptical opponents. Nor did the
other doleful predictions come true.
Woman by entering the lists for public
honors and responsibilities did not sacriIO


fice her womanliness.  Perhaps she
gained in all the essentials that make
up the true woman.  Her self-reliance
and self-consciousness heightened, she
herself learned to put a new and better
value on herself. As an equal, she could
meet father, husband and brother. And
where the responsibilities of motherhood
had fallen to her lot, her broadened horizon conferred on her a rational understanding of the sanctity and importance
of her opportunity. Business and the
professions, no less than literature and
the arts and sciences
have welcomed her to
*.             i full citizenship in their
'      %-;; respective realms.,           Soon, also, the last
citadel will capitulate
\}   before her victorious
/X  ' X  siege; the political: ballot will also be
hers.
The Jewish woman
has felt, with her nonJewish  sister, t h e
/     breadth of a new sky.
/&gt;,      The French revolu&lt;           tion opened before the
Jew the gates of the
Ghetto. To him fell
HIRSCH.         the task of covering
within the span of
few decades the territory which his
neighbors had traversed during hundreds of years.   The   middle ages
ended for the non-Jew with the discovery of America and the protest of
the German Reformation, the child of
the Italian Renaissance and classic humanism. For the Jew, the mediaevalism
only then began. Before his expulsion
from Spain and the persecutions which
the preceding two centuries had brought
for him in their transit, his mind had
been of the most active in the pursuit of
truth and knowledge. But at the very



</P><P><PB REF="00000015.tif" SEQ="00000015" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="898" N="11" DISPLAYN="11" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=15"/>
THE MODERN JEWESS.


II


period when the world around began to
awaken from the mysticism and scholasticism and the credulity of the "dark
ages " the Jew was coerced into sleep
and he was only aroused when trumpets
blaring the "rights of man" laid low
the Jericho of despotism in I789. He
showed himself, however, equal to the
situation. Fewdecades sufficed to change
him from an Asiatic exile, from a distant
age and land, into an active co-operator
in all the channels along which flow the
currents of modern labor and life.
The history of the Jew will be repeated
in the record which the Jewess is about
making for herself. If her father and
brother for long spells of circling time
were doomed to be in the world but not
of the world, the Jewess was barred from
the outer throng and its interests by a
double restriction. She shared the fate
of every adherent of Judaism, but in addition she was under the despotism of
home Orientalism, sanctioned by unyielding religious rigorism. It is true, Jewish history names many of the sex that
shine with the light of beauty and heroism. The prophetic spirit even fell to
the lot of some of the sisters, while
others live on in the fame of wisdom
and learning.  But on the whole, the
Jewish woman's universe was her home.
Her position was not without ideal compensation. The Biblical description of
a true woman reveals a busy and useful,
and what is more, an honored and trusted
station.  To-day, the Synagogue has
ceased looking Eastward. Orientalism
in thought, views and symbols gleans
but a romantic tribute in the reconstituted and broadened Temple of Israel's
God. Into Western life the Jew has
thrown himself. From it he draws his
inspiration, and to it would he contribute  his historic idealism.  And the
Jewess without hesitation follows her
brother's lead. She has turned her eyes
Westward.


Often is the Jewish woman held by
prejudice to be under the spell of Eastern fancies. Upon this mistaken judgment rests the ascription to her of a love
for fineries, gems and loud colors. But
a more serious purpose runs through the
modern woman's life, and the Jewess has
sacrificed with no greater zest than her
non-Jewish sister at the shrine of frivolity. In fact it is the ambition of the
Jewess to be a woman so womanly as to
exclude all qualifying adjectives. Her
Judaism inculcates and emphasizes this
ambition. She would take her place at
the side of her sister in all that makes
for the nobler freedom. Her culture is
no narrower than that after which the
non-Jewess aspires. In the struggle for
fame and position, the Jewish woman,
when predisposition or necessity have
pointed her path in this thorny field,
bears bravely the brunt of the battle,
and is no less anxious and competent
than is woman generally to equip herself for the fray. She has had to conquer twofold difficulties, those arising
from home prejudices and those due to
opposition to her sex generally. Her
Judaism was no passport to willing reception, as it was no godspeed to her at
the threshold of her own parental residence. But she has won the day, in
spite of bias and obsolete misgivings
and capricious interference.
The opportunities for the Jewish
woman to-day to reform her own religious home are many. What the Synagogue now needs foremost is intelligent
enthusiasm. It is woman who owns
this gift. Let her place her new culture
into the service of her old faith and the
winters of indifference will yield to
springtides of young and hopeful life.
At home let her be the priestess of the
Ideal, abroad the prophetess of Purity
and Refinement and through her will Judaism and the Jewish name be exalted
to heights never before attained.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:5"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Mannheimer, Louise</AUTHORIND><TITLE>Nahida Remy.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">12-14</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000016.tif" SEQ="00000016" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="889" N="12" DISPLAYN="12" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=16"/>
NAHIDA REMY.
HER LIFE AND HER WORK, "JEWISH WOMAN."
LOUISE MANNHEIMER.


I K E  a  sunbeam   breaking
through dark and threatening
clouds, like the gentle breeze of
spring after the chilling blasts of winter, like the sweet morning song of the
lark, so comes the genius of Nahida
Remy to touch and cheer our hearts. In
a time of restlessness at home and persecution  abroad  the
book of "Jewish
Woman" came to us
like an angel of consolation and delight.
Nahida Remy, a
Protestant by birth,
is surprisingly well
versed, not alone in
Hebraic, but even in
Talmudical lore. To
write a b ok like
"Jewish Woman"
seems at first sight a
psychological incongruity, something incompatible.  A brief
outline of her life,
however, will show
that her work is the
natural outcome of,
seemingly, trifling in-   MRS.,OUISE
cidents bearing upon an uncommonly
earnest mind, a mind in search of truth,
with the whole ardor of enthusiasm.
Nahida Remy was born in Berlin in
the year I849. Her mother went to
Italy on account of ill health, and entrusted the education of her little daughter, who was then about nine years old,
to an elderly countess in Naples. The
peculiarities and strict religious views of
this lady robbed the child of her natural
cheerfulness and made her pensive.
When twelve years old, she began to
study the Bible, and, at this early age,
I2


formed independent opinions on religion
and its observances. She says, " I loved
the church, but was afraid of the
priests." She received religious instructions from a pastor by the name of
Remy. He was by no means a kind
teacher. One day, during the lesson,
he made a remark, and like a flash came
to her the thought,
"How   good, how
beautiful."  Her face
lit up with a delighted smile.  The
pastor, however, misunderstanding this
expression, took it for
a smile of derision,
and without stopping
to ask, struck her in
the face.
She never returned
to take another lesson.
Her feelings were
deeply wounded and
her mind was tormented by doubts, not
only about the mission
of the servant of God,
who could make such
IANNHEIMER.      a mistake, but, far
worse, about the Deity itself who permitted such mistakes.
She little suspected that this stroke
was to prove the propelling power which
gave her energies their direction.
More than thirty years have elapsed
since that incident, and now she humorously remarks: ''That stroke made a
striking impression on me; it aroused
me from unreasoning faith and childlike
devotion into meditation and critical reflection."  This critical reflectiveness
has grown ever stronger with her, and is
now one of her pronounced characteristics.


1
A:


A



</P><P><PB REF="00000017.tif" SEQ="00000017" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="13" DISPLAYN="13" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=17"/>
NAHIDA REMY.


I3


This is one of the trifling incidents
which one can, psychologically, trace
back as a cause of the work, which is
now the work of her life.
In 1863 her mother took her to Flatow,
a small town in western Prussia, to stay
with on old sick aunt.
In Flatow, Dr. Tobald taught her the
tenets of the creed. He was zealous and
gentle, yet he could not induce her to
accept certain dogmas of the church.
He was astonished at her mental grasp,
at her knowledge of the Bible, but at
the close of her studies declared that as
long as she did not assent to all the doctrines of the creed, he could not confirm
her.
Her friends urged her to comply with
the usage of the church, and we find her,
about a year later, in Berlin, receiving
religious instruction from the venerable
clergyman who had baptized her, General Superintendent Karl von Buechsel.
She writes to me: "The confirmation
never took place. To this day I cannot
persuade myself to pronounce the apostolic confession of faith on account of
innermost religious love of truth. "  What
a fearless, clear, logical mind must it be
that prompted such an utterance!
Years passed.  Nahida had given
proof of decided talent in drawing and
painting. She wished to perfect herself
in art and select it as her profession.
Peter Cornelius himself gave her lessons;
but lack of means forced her to abandon
this plan of life. Her mother believed
that she had a talent for the stage, and
so, for years, she had to test the bright
and dark sides of stage life. She was
not successful. Her retiring disposition
taken for pride, proved an obstacle, yet
she could not overcome her timidity.
In i873 she was married, in Berlin, to
the art critic, Dr. Max Remy, a nephew
of the Pastor Remy who had once been
unkind to her.
With a sigh of relief she bade adieu to


the stage, happy to assume the duties o
the household. Her mind, however, was
too vigorous to remain inactive. The
literary atmosphere in which she now
moved at the side of her husband, gave
her a new impulse for poetical work.
I say a new impulse, for already, in the
year 1869, as a girl of twenty years, she
had written, under a nom de plume, a
comedy, " Die Rechnung ohne Wirth,"
which was successfully performed at the
Burgtheatre in Vienna. Three years
after her marriage, in I876, she wrote
her first drama, "Constance," in 1879
a second one, " Die Grafen von Eckardstein."
But new trials came. Her husband
fell dangerously ill, and for a long time
he was confined to the sick room. She
who had been his co-worker became
now his substitute, writing for the Vossishe Zeitung, and for  Westermann's
Monatshefte.  Besides this she did no
literary work at this time. She was too
loving a wife to entrust the nursing ot
her sick husband to other hands, and
considered, as every thoughtful woman
does, the care of her household her first
and paramount duty.
In the year I88I the angel of death
entered the peaceful home and relieved
the sufferer from all his pains.
This long sickness had exhausted their
small means, and Nahida Remy found
herself alone and poor. But her energy
did not forsake her, she worked on undismayed, and, at last, her efforts were
crowned with well deserved success.
In I886 her "Sicilianishe Novellen"
were published, and in I890 her historical novel "Geheime Gewalten," both
being very favorably received by the
public as well as by the press.
About this time, Nahida Remy began
to read Jewish history and Jewish literature with all the earnestness for which
she is distinguished. The well known



</P><P><PB REF="00000018.tif" SEQ="00000018" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="889" N="14" DISPLAYN="14" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=18"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


scholar and philosopher, Dr. Lazarus,
guided her studies.
And what created the first impulse to
these studies? It was antisemitism. The
poison could not contaminate a mind so
noble and pure, it turned into a blessing.
She writes to me: The prevailing antisemitism is revolting to my sense of
justice, and I concentrate all my powers
in the endeavor to enlightenz Christendom
and to arouse a conciliatory feeling.
This is the spirit that animates Nahida
Remy, who gave to the world the book
"Jewish Woman," a book just as remarkable for the absence of every prejudice as for its thorough scholarship.
For this work she gives ample proof
of her exhaustive researches. Patiently
and lovingly she has wandered and
gleaned in the fields of Jewish history
and Jewish literature, nothing escaped
her keen eye. She is familiar with the
Haggada, as well as with Niemeyer,
Zunz, Jost, Kaiserling and Jellinek,
with Renan, Conte, Guiliari, Munk,
Shleiden, as well as with a host of other
renowned writers on Judaism and Jewish
history.
This vast material which she has diligently collected, she combines into an
organic unit, animating it with her genius.
The mind of the reader follows with
close interest the subject matter, while
the aesthetic sense is delighted with the
graceful garb in which it is presented.
Her style is simple, clear, melodious,
and yet full of vigor.
The lucidity of her diction is partly
due to the simple, long and short sen

tences that she uses in preference to
periodic structures, which often render
German prose intricate and obscure.
Another element adds perspicuity to
her writing: her skillfully arranged and
well rounded paragraphs.
Her fundamental idea is: "To understand woman one must study the history
of her slavery; to judge correctly Jewish
woman, one must compare her with the
women of other ancient nations.
Accordingly she begins with the investigation of the social relations of the
women among the different old nations,
and shows how deplorable their condition was, even among the Romans and
the classical Greeks.
The early Christian idea about woman
and marriage, she denounces with a boldness that reminds one of the boldness of
Martin Luther when he wrote and nailed
to the church door in Wittenberg his
ninety-five propositions denouncing the
sale of indulgences by the Pope.
She brings conclusive proof, citing the
writings of the apostles and saints, that
Christendom can not lay claim as having emancipated woman. She closes the
chapter by saying: "'Nothing can more
strikingly show the early Christian's disregard for woman than the following
assertion of Saint Tertullian in his treatise " De Resurrectione." (About resurrection.) He says: "The resurrected
will lose all their blemishes and defects,
the blind ones will see, the lame ones
will walk, and the women will rise from
the dead as - men."
(Conltinued.)



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:6"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Moses Dr. Adolph</AUTHORIND><TITLE>The Position of Woman in America.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">15-20</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000019.tif" SEQ="00000019" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="895" N="15" DISPLAYN="15" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=19"/>
THE POSITION OF WOMAN IN AMERICA.


DR. ADOLPH MOSES.


The American people have carried into practice the lofty ideals which the
prophets and poets of Israel cherished
regarding woman. In some respects the
American practice may be said to have
improved on the Hebrew ideal. If the
American nation had done nothing else
for the progress of humanity than to
have at last redeemed woman from the
state of legal, social and intellectual inferiority in which she had been kept
from time immemorial, it would be entitled to rank among the great civilizing
powers of the earth. To have broken
the fetters which the age of savagery
had forged for her, which the age of
barbarism had riveted upon her, with
which even the most advanced nations
continued to enchain her, is a contribution of immeasurable value made by
America towards the world's civilization. The moral, mental, social and
legal emancipation of woman has, in a
sense, doubled the working forces of
civilization. Before all the faculties of
woman were liberated by the American
people from the narrowing and crippling
restraints imposed upon her by inherited
savage customs and barbarous ideas,
only one-half the human race - the male
half- was given full opportunity to develop all the powers of heart and mind;
only one-half was allowed to engage in
the higher pursuits of life, to be standard-bearers of the world's accumulated
knowledge, to be producers of new
thought, representatives of creative art,
master-builders of the temple of humanity. From the beginning of man's career on earth till about one hundred
years ago a fatal madness seemed to possess all the tribes of men, causing them
to confine one-half of all human beings
exclusively to the duties and works of
the household. The blundering stupid

ity and heartless cruelty of man, as he
came forth from the hands of nature, as
he was molded by the brutal forces of
savagery, and as he was hardened by
the cruel usages and debasing ideas of
barbarism, shows itself most hideously
in the degrading treatment which woman, the fairest and gentlest of creation's children, received at the hands of
the stronger sex in nearly all lands and
times. The story of woman's wrongs,
of her unrequited, excessive toil, of the
indescribable physical and moral abuse
of which she was a victim, of her enforced ignorance, of the blighting contempt in which she was held, forms a
chapter of shame and iniquity in the
annals of mankind. "By their fruits
ye shall know them." And we ought
to judge of the tree of past humanity
by the bitter fruits of misery and degradation which it bore to womankind.
To the savage ancestors of modern
nations woman was what she is to the
savage Indian and Australian of to-day:
she was a mere beast of burden, bought
like any other chattel from her owner,
her father. She was abused in every
way, cruelly beaten, often starved, and
not seldom killed by an enraged man-animal. To the barbarian, woman was and
is a slave, or at best a plaything which
he throws away after it has become old
and worn and lost its charms for him.
Even after civilization had advanced in
other respects, women continued to be
held in subjection and contempt. The
women of Greece passed their lives in
seclusion and ignorance. The Roman
matron was the property of her husband.
She, with her children, together with
the slaves, formed the family, which
was under the absolute sway of the
pater-familias. He could kill his wife, as
well as his children, with impunity.
15



</P><P><PB REF="00000020.tif" SEQ="00000020" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="16" DISPLAYN="16" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=20"/>
I6


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


German writers have long fabled about
the high position occupied by women
among the ancient Germans. But impartial historical research has proved
this assertion to have no foundation in
fact. The weakness of ancient civilization lay mainly in this fact. Half of the
population of a country, and in some
regions even a greater proportion of it,
consisted of slaves and of the free-born
people, one-half again, the women, virtually lived in a state of domestic servitude. Thus, their intellectual powers
became dwarfed through the total absence of education. Their moral sensibilities and faculties became sadly
stunted, because they did not breathe
the bracing air of personal freedom,
because they lacked the sustaining and
uplifting forces of self-respect, and the
invigorating influences derived from the
world's esteem. Even a Plato and an
Aristotle, not to speak of a host of other
writers, expatiate like Hindoo and Chinese authors on the moral obliquity of
women.
Wherever and whenever, therefore, the
iron rules and restraints within which
woman was held imprisoned came to be
loosened through the co-operation of internal and external causes, it did not
result in the flowering of her mental
powers, nor in an ennobling and strengthening of her character. On the contrary,
there ensued a frightful state of general
licentiousness. All the old barriers broke
down, there being no restraining ethical
forces in the national religion; there
opened a yawning abyss of demoralization which swallowed the nations, and all
the glory and pride of their civilization:
their statues and paintings, their poetry
and philosophy.
Thus were woman's wrongs avenged
by the inexorable Nemesis of history.
The life of paganism was vile in almost
all moral respects, but vilest of all it
proved to be in its treatment of woman.


By degrading woman, heathenism poisoned the well-spring of life. The seers
of Yahve saw the root of the world's
evils in the demoralizing beliefs and
practices in paganism. They were not
content to lop off here and there a branch
of the Upas tree, they laid the axe to its
very root, to the baneful heathen theory
of nature and man, of God and the soul.
The prophets of Israel proclaimed a new
theory of nature and man, of God and
the soul. This theory, once embodied
in habits and institutions, is bound to
save mankind from a returning deluge of
destruction by immoral forces, and to
redeem woman from the curse inherited
from savage ancestors and barbarous
times.  They taught the unity of all
life in God, they proclaimed the sacredness of all life, because it flows from
the holy fountain of His creative being.
They brought the message to mankind
that all men, without distinction of race
or sex, were children of their Heavenly
Father; that woman was made no less
than man in the spiritual image of His
will, and fashioned in the likeness of
His wisdom and love. In the image of
God He made them both, man and
woman, He created them. Having a
Godlike nature like man, she possesse
like Him an infinite, moral dignity. She,
too, is but little less than a God. The
free development of her reason, the untrammeled use of her free will, the cultivation of her mental powers, the unfolding of all the moral wealth of her soul, is
an inalienable right inherent in her by
the grace of her God-descended humanity, by virtue of her indestructible, ethical personality.
The absolute equality of women with
man is clearly contained in the cardinal
conception of the great revolutionary
heroes of humanity, the prophets of
Israel. Nor did their ideas concerning
woman remain barren theories in the
minds of the worshipers of Yahve.



</P><P><PB REF="00000021.tif" SEQ="00000021" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="17" DISPLAYN="17" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=21"/>
THE POSITION OF WOMAN IN AMERICA.


7


Women are recorded to have been judges
and prophetesses; the spirit of God was
believed to inspire them; they spake
with the voice of authority to the people and the rulers. This fact goes far to
prove that woman was held in high regard in Israel, that she occupied a posi-:tion of dignity and influence high above
that assigned to her even by the most
*civilized pagan nations. Yet, though
the position of woman in Israel was
higher, though her lot was happier than
among the other ancient nations, the
Hebrew practice and common law regarding her was far from keeping pace with
the Hebrew ideal. There were too many
ineradicable habits of thought and feeling, too many old institutions, such as
polygamy, which held on tenaciously
to life, refusing to give way to the revolutionary ideas and ideals, with which
they formed so glaring a contrast. Great
reformatory ideas rarely succeed in becoming fully realized in the land where they
first make their appearance. Thus the
ideas and ideals which, after thousands
of years, were to embody themselves
and celebrate their greatest triumph in
America went forth from Zion, and migrated from people to people, and from
age to age, pleading in the name of God
and humanity for the dignity, the intellectual elevation, the social equality of
woman. But the hardness of man's
heart, the coarse selfishness of the middle ages, the universal oppression of the
weak, the brutal spirit of militarism,
belief that physical strength and physical courage constituted the highest virtue, offered the most stubborn resistance
to any attempt at innovation in this direction, and caused men to listen with
a contemptuous smile to the pleadings
made on behalf of women. The so-called
age of chivalry contributed nothing
toward the amelioration of her condition and the uplifting of her life. It
merely put an artificial and illusive


paint on the face of the prevailing barbarism. It produced a large number of
love-songs, in which an unnatural and
exaggerated homage was paid to her
beauty, but it effected no moral or social
good; on the contrary it resulted in a
disgraceful corruption of morals.
The age of rationalism or enlightenment in Europe brought partial relief
and some gleams of light to the women
of the higher classes, but the great mass
of womankind in the Old World have to
this day continued to live in a state of
social and mental inferiority. You can
still see in the streets of Dutch and Belgian cities, and in other European countries, a woman harnessed to a cart-together with a dog; you can still see in
parts of Germany and Austria, and other
civilized lands, a woman hitched together
with a bullock to a plow behind which
the husband is walking. The American
who passes some time in Austria, observes with a sense of horror women
carrying a heavy load of brick on their
shoulders, with which they climb up on
ladders to the second and third stories of
buildings. The European peasant does
not hold his wife in much higher esteem
than does the Indian savage. To lose
his cattle will break his heart, but he
readily consoles himself for the loss of
his wife. It was reserved for the American people to bring about the redemption
of woman from the curse of ages, from
the yoke which paganism and barbarism
had put on her neck.
The scarcity of women in America till
about a generation ago, has done something to effect this greatest social revolution. But it has done far less than is
usually ascribed to it by European
observers. It was the great principle
which animates and vitalizes the American commonwealth. It is the intensely
realized idea of an infinite moral dignity
inherent in every human soul; it is the
belief that every human being possesses,



</P><P><PB REF="00000022.tif" SEQ="00000022" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="888" N="18" DISPLAYN="18" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=22"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


by the grace of his Godlike nature, the
right and duty to develop all his powers,
and to use them for the attainment of
his happiness. It is the conviction
firmly rooted in the heart of the whole
people, that personal freedom of action
is vouchsafed to every individual by the
eternal laws of justice; it is these cardinal conceptions that have delivered woman in America from the state of mental and social inferiority in which she
has been kept through countless ages;
it is these ideas that have at last placed
her on a level with manl, and opened to
her all the avenues of human activity.
With that fearless consistency in carrying right principles to their best practical conclusion, which characterizes the
American, he said to himself: " Has not
woman an immortal soul like man? Is
she not crowned with the attributes of
reason and free will like man? Is she
not a child of God, an image of the Most
High, like man? Shall we regard her
as belonging to a lower kind of humanity? Shall we believe our mothers, to
whom we owe the noblest qualities of
our being, inferior to their sons? Shall
we deem the partners of life, whose love
blesses us, whose purity ennobles us,
whose devotion is our shield and buckler, whose strength of will upholds
us in days of darkness, shall we think
her undeserving of equal rights and
equal privileges with us? Shall our
daughters, whose loveliness is the light
of our eyes, whose sweetness is the joy
of our life, whose angelic affection is the
solace of our days, shall they not be
allowed to penetrate the innermost chambers of the sanctuary of knowledge, and
to fall heirs to the world's wisdom?
Shall women, to whom we owe the best
part of our spiritual and moral life, be
forced to observe silence concerning matters of high spiritual and ethical import? "
The genius of the American people


has cried aloud, and its voice is still
reverberating from one end of the civilized world to the other: " Make a highway for woman, remove every obstacle
from her path, let every mountain of
inequality and injustice be made level, let
every valley of ignorance and prejudice
be raised. Let her move on with man to
ever nobler ends. Let her, in loving
harmony with him, work out the salvation of the race; let her gather knowledge
and with the arrows of her light, chase
darkness from the earth, let her help to
uproot evil and plant social light and
truth. Let her, too, grapple with the
great problems of humanity, and with
her love and wisdom aid in giving them
a peaceful solution. Let all her powers
grow and expand, and be added to the
working forces of civilization. Let a
crown of honor be placed on her head,
let her be clothed with the royal garments of virtue and be girt with the
magic girdle of loving kindness and
grace." To-day the American woman
has become the highest representative of
womanhood. She has been placed on
the very highest pinnacle of social honor.
The American people have surrounded
her person with the safeguards of universal esteem. Woe betide the man who
should insult the dignity of woman, or
offend her ear with the breath of impurity. The consciousness of being the
queen of social honor has given to the
American woman a dignity of bearing,
a graciousness of demeanor, a noble
spirit of self-possession and self respect,
such as in the Old World is to be observed only in the women of the highest
ranks.
There is a spirit of self-reliance in the
American woman, a capacity for selfhelp, a firmness of purpose, a grasp of
the practical affairs of life, which make
her contrast so strangely and advantageously with the shrinking, timid and
helpless women of the Old World. At



</P><P><PB REF="00000023.tif" SEQ="00000023" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="19" DISPLAYN="19" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=23"/>
THE POSITION OF WOMAN IN AMERICA.


I9


the same time there is in the American
woman an idealism, a deep religious
sense, an almost mystic yearning after
spiritual illumination, an aspiration after
the higher attainments, an ambition to
be abreast with the culture of the time,
and in close touch with the best thought
of the ages. Along with these qualities
there goes a keen and helpful sympathy
with human suffering, a sense of horror
and of responsibility at the sight of
physical deterioration, of mental deformity and moral degradation, a sleepless
desire to leave the world better, wiser
and happier than she found it. Such is
the character of the American woman, as
it has been formed by the American people, or rather as it has been molded by
the great principles which are the soul of
the American commonwealth. Of all
the members of society she has reaped
the largest harvest of benefits, since this
continent has been changed from a habitation of howling savages into the seat
of the most progressive civilization. Yet
she is no idle beneficiary, a mere pensioner of the American people. Much as
America has done for her, she has done
and is doing as much more for America.
She is enriching, ennobling and spiritualizing the life of the American nation.
America is called by Europeans the
land of a purely material civilization.
We are accused of being steeped in materialism. It is said of us that we worship no other god but the almighty dollar.
That we are able to refute these reproaches as utterly baseless, is mainly
due to the ideal forces which perennially
issue from the soul of the American
woman, and give our national and individual life a higher meaning and purpose. While a ceaseless battle is being
waged by the men for the possession of
material wealth, woman keeps watch over
the holy ark of the ideal, and ministers
as priestess in the sanctuary of Godseeking humanity. It is she that upholds


and upbuilds the temple of religion in
this country. The wholesome and growing religious life of the nation derives its
vital powers from the enthusiasm, devotion and self-sacrificing activity of women. She is the chief agent in inaugurating, preserving and improving the institutions of philanthropy in this country.
She organizes and carries on most of the
works of charity which alleviate the
misery of countless thousands, and save
innumerable persons from physical and
moral perdition. Two-thirds of the
charities of our land would languish and
die were she to refuse to lend them her
energy, time and influence. The American woman looks upon herself as the
chosen adversary of evil, and fights it
with all her characteristic bravery and
tenacity of purpose. She has declared
war upon intemperance, and will yet
root it out of the land. The women of
America are found among the foremost
champions of social justice and political
purity. Two great reforms, which rerecently took place in the administration
of New York, were effected solely by the
moral courage, the unconquerable persistence, and the irresistible eloquence of
a noble woman. Let the cause of humanity, in whatever guise, cry out for
defenders, and you will see women fighting in the front ranks, and bearing the
brunt of the battle.
The American people is being richly
rewarded for having opened all the avenues of knowledge to women, for putting
them on a footing of absolute equality
with men as regards education. The
arduous and unremunerative work of educating the young is almost exclusively
carried on by women in our public
schools. The kindness and generosity of
the American character is largely to be
traced back to the softening and humanizing influence exercised by the female
teachers on the plastic mind and impressionable heart of the young. The gen


</P><P><PB REF="00000024.tif" SEQ="00000024" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="20" DISPLAYN="20" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=24"/>
20


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


eral high culture of the American women
acts as a constant stimulative and leavening force on the minds of men. The
unbounded esteem in which they are
held reacts most beneficially on the behavior of the male population. Their
presence curbs rudeness and represses
vulgarity. The feelings and manners of
the Americans are becoming in the
best sense of the word ever more feminine, gentle, generous, pure and sweet.
Such are the ethical, educational and
intellectual services which woman is
rendering the American people, in return
for the redemption wrought for her. No


eye can foresee the wonders and blessings
which the moral superiority of her character, her religious enthusiasm, her intense hatred of evil, her fervid love of
good, will bring forth in future.
Incalculable are the influences which
the example and the exalted position of
the American women are exerting on
the life of the women of the Old World.
The American woman is the coming type
of womanhood throughout the civilized
world. It is her manifest destiny to form
womanhood in her own image and after
her likeness.


THE DEPARTED.
RUTH WARD KAHN.
Not only they who are dead are passed away;
I've friends whose voice I yearn for, and whose
smile
Could change my tears to gladness, but whose
touch
Will never lighten heart of mine again,
And yet they are not dead.
Not only those who are dead are gone away,
No funeral train was sweeping past,
No martial music, or low, mournful dirge,
And yet I saw them pass out of my life,
Smiling and beck'ning as they went,
But to return to me on earth no more.
Not alone the dead are the departed;
For lo! one whom I met and loved iu later life,
With hope's fresh blossoms on his boyish brow
Came close to me and looked into my eyes
And bade me follow-but I could not go-and
so he, too, is gone.
Gone, all of them, forever, 'tho we may meet,
As seaweed may meet seaweed blown by angry
wind or tideA smile, a recognition, and then lost
Among the seething mass of foam forever.
For they who are dead may vigils keep
Over their true and faithful friends,
And joy to know their gladness, and grieve to
know their pain.
But they whom life hath separated
May moan and weep and stretch out empty
hands,
But only winds and waves reply, and they but
mock us.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:7"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Kahn, Ruth Ward</AUTHORIND><TITLE>The Departed.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">20</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000024.tif" SEQ="00000024" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="20" DISPLAYN="20" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=24"/>
20


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


eral high culture of the American women
acts as a constant stimulative and leavening force on the minds of men. The
unbounded esteem in which they are
held reacts most beneficially on the behavior of the male population. Their
presence curbs rudeness and represses
vulgarity. The feelings and manners of
the Americans are becoming in the
best sense of the word ever more feminine, gentle, generous, pure and sweet.
Such are the ethical, educational and
intellectual services which woman is
rendering the American people, in return
for the redemption wrought for her. No


eye can foresee the wonders and blessings
which the moral superiority of her character, her religious enthusiasm, her intense hatred of evil, her fervid love of
good, will bring forth in future.
Incalculable are the influences which
the example and the exalted position of
the American women are exerting on
the life of the women of the Old World.
The American woman is the coming type
of womanhood throughout the civilized
world. It is her manifest destiny to form
womanhood in her own image and after
her likeness.


THE DEPARTED.
RUTH WARD KAHN.
Not only they who are dead are passed away;
I've friends whose voice I yearn for, and whose
smile
Could change my tears to gladness, but whose
touch
Will never lighten heart of mine again,
And yet they are not dead.
Not only those who are dead are gone away,
No funeral train was sweeping past,
No martial music, or low, mournful dirge,
And yet I saw them pass out of my life,
Smiling and beck'ning as they went,
But to return to me on earth no more.
Not alone the dead are the departed;
For lo! one whom I met and loved iu later life,
With hope's fresh blossoms on his boyish brow
Came close to me and looked into my eyes
And bade me follow-but I could not go-and
so he, too, is gone.
Gone, all of them, forever, 'tho we may meet,
As seaweed may meet seaweed blown by angry
wind or tideA smile, a recognition, and then lost
Among the seething mass of foam forever.
For they who are dead may vigils keep
Over their true and faithful friends,
And joy to know their gladness, and grieve to
know their pain.
But they whom life hath separated
May moan and weep and stretch out empty
hands,
But only winds and waves reply, and they but
mock us.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:8"><BIBL><TITLE>Inside the Walls of Jerusalem</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">21</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000025.tif" SEQ="00000025" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="846" N="21" DISPLAYN="21" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=25"/>
INSIDE THE WALLS OF JERUSALEM.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:9"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Chopin, Kate</AUTHORIND><TITLE>Cavanelle.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">22-25</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000026.tif" SEQ="00000026" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="878" N="22" DISPLAYN="22" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=26"/>
CAVANELLE.
KATE CHOPIN.


WAS always sure of hearing
something pleasant from Cavanelle across the counter. If
he was not mistaking me for the freshest
and prettiest girl in New Orleans, he
was reserving for me some bit of silk, or
lace, or ribbon of a nuance marvelously
suited to my complexion, my eyes or my
hair! What an innocent, delightful
humbug Cavanelle
was! How well I
knew it and how
little I cared! For
when he had sold
me the confection
or bit of dry-goods
in question, he
always began to
talk to me of his
sister Mathilde, and
then I knew that
Cavanelle was an
angel.
I had known him
long enough    to
know    why   he
worked   so faithfully, so energetically and without
rest-it was be-                KATE
cause Mathilde had
a voice.  It was because of her voice
that his coats were worn till they were
out of fashion and almost out at elbows.
But for a sister whose voice needed only
a little training to rival that of the nightingale, one might do such things without incurring reproach.
"You will believe, madame, that I
did not know you las' night at the
opera? I remark' to Mathilde 'liens!
Mademoiselle Montreville in the baignoire of the Chopin's!' an' I only rec'nize
my mistake when I finally adjust my
22


opera glass..... I guarantee you will
be satisfied, madame. In a year from
now you will come an' thank me for
having secu' you that bargain in a
poult-de-soie.... Yes, yes; as you
say, Tolville was in voice. But," with a
shrug of the narrow shoulders and a
smile of commiseration that wrinkled the
lean olive cheeks
beneath the thin
beard, "but to hear
that cavdtina render' as I have heard
it render' by Mathilde, it is another
affair! A quality,
madame,     that
moves, that penetrates. Perhaps not
yet enough volume, but that will
accomplish itself
with time, when
she will become
more   robus' in
health. It is my
intention to sen'
her for the summer to Gran' Isle;
that good air an'
HOPIN.             surf bathing will
work miracles. An
artiste, voyez vous, it is not to be treated
like a human being of every day; it
needs des pelits soins; perfec' res' of body
an' mind; good red wine an' plenty.... oh yes, madame, the stage; that
is our intention; but never with my consent in light opera. Patience is what I
counsel to Mathilde.  A  little more
stren'th; a little dev'lopment of the
chest to give that sozpcon of compass
which is lacking, an' gran' opera is what
I aspire for my sister."
I was curious to know Mathilde and



</P><P><PB REF="00000027.tif" SEQ="00000027" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="895" N="23" DISPLAYN="23" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=27"/>
CAVANELLE.


23


to hear her sing; and thought it a great
pity that a voice so marvelous as she
doubtless possessed should not gain the
notice that might prove the step toward
the attainment of her ambition. It was
such curiosity and a half-formed design
or desire to interest myself in her career
that prompted me to inform Cavanelle
that I should greatly like to meet his
sister; and I asked permission to call
upon her the following Sunday afternoon.
Cavanalle was charmed. He otherwise would not have been Cavanelle.
Over and over I was given the most minute directions for finding the house.
The green car-or was it the yellow or
blue one? I can no longer remember;
But it was near Goodchildren street, and
would I kindly walk this way and turn
that way. At the corner was an ice dealers. In the middle of the block, their
house - one-story; painted yellow; a
knocker; a banana tree nodding over the
side fence. But indeed, I need not look
for the banana tree, nor the knocker, the
number nor anything, for if I but turn
the corner in the neighborhood of five
o'clock I would find him planted at the
door awaiting me.
And there he was! Cavaneile himself;
but seeming to me not himself; apart
from the primitive entourage with which
I was accustomed to associate him.
Every line of his mobile face, every gesture emphasized the welcome which his
kind eyes expressed as he ushered me
into the small parlor that opened upon
the street.
" Oh, not that chair, madame! I entreat you. This one, by all means;
thousan' times more comfortable."
" Mathilde. Strange; my sister was
here but the instant ago. Mathilde!
DZi es tu donc?" Stupid Cavanelle! He
did not know when I had already guessed
it-that Mathilde had retired to the adjoining room at my approach, and would


appear after a sufficient delay to give an
appropriate air of ceremony to her greeting.
And what a frail little piece of mortality she was when she did appear! At
beholding her I could easily fancy that
when she stepped outside of the yellow
house, the zephyrs would lift her from
her feet and, given a proper adjustment of the balloon sleeves, gently waft
her in the direction of Goodchildren
street, or wherever else she might want
to go.
Hers was no physique for grand opera
-certainly no stage presence; apparently so slender a hold upon life that the
least tension might snap it. The voice
which could hope to overcome these glaring disadvantages would be phenomenal.
Mathilde spoke English imperfectly,
and with embarrassment, and was glad
to lapse into French. Her speech was
languid, unaffectedly so; and her manner
was one of indolent repose; in this respect offering a striking contrast to that
of her brother. Cavanelle seemed unable
to rest. Hardly was I seated to his satisfaction than he darted from the room and
soon returned followed by a limping old
black woman bringing in a sirop d'orgeat
and layer cake on a tray.
Mathilde's face showed feeble annoyance at her brother's want of savior vivre
in thus introducing the refreshments at so
early a stage of my visit.
The servant was one of those cheap
black women who abound in the French
quarter, who speak Creole patois in preference to English, and who would rather
work in a petit menage in Goodchildren
street for five dollars a month than for fifteen in the fourth district. Her presence,
in some unaccountable manner, seemed
to reveal to me much of the inner working of this small household. I pictured
her early morning visit to the French
market, where picayunes were doled out



</P><P><PB REF="00000028.tif" SEQ="00000028" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="895" N="24" DISPLAYN="24" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=28"/>
24


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


sparingly, and lagniappes gathered in
with avidity.
I could see the neatly appointed dinner table. Cavanelle extolling his soup
and bouillie in extravagant terms; Mathilde toying with her papabolle or
chicken-wing, and pouring herself a
demi-verre from her very own half bottle
of St. Julien; Pouponne, as they called
her, mumbling and grumbling through
habit, and serving them as faithfully as
a dog through instinct. I wondered if
they knew that Pouponne "played the
lottery" with every rare " quarter " gathered from a judicious management of
lagniappe.  Perhaps they would not
have cared, or have minded, either, that
she as often consulted the Voudoo priestess around the corner as her father confessor.
My thoughts had followed Pouponne's
limping figure from the room, and it was
with an effort I returned to Cavanelle
twirling the piano stool this way and
that way. Mathilde was languidly turning over musical scores, and the two
warmly discussing the merits of a selection which she had evidently decided
upon.
The girl seated herself at the piano.
Her hands were thin and anaemic, and
she touched the keys without firmness
or delicacy. When she had played a
few introductory bars, she began to sing.
Heaven only knows what it was; it
made no difference then, nor can it make
any now.
The day was a warm one, but that did
not prevent a creepy chilliness seizing
hold of me. The feeling was generated
by disappointment, anger, dismay and
various other disagreeable sensations
which I cannot find names for. Had I
been intentionally deceived and misled?
was this some impertinent pleasantry on
the part of Cavanelle? Or rather had not
the girl's voice undergone some hideous
transformation since her brother had


listened to it? I dreaded to look at him,
fearing to see horror and astonishment depicted on his face. When I did look,
his expression was earnestly attentive
and beamed approval of the strains to
which he measured time by a slow, satisfied motion of the hand.
The voice was thin to attenuation, I
fear it was not even true. Perhaps my
disappointment exaggerated its simple
deficiencies into monstrous defects. But
it was an unsympathetic voice that never
could have been a blessing to possess or
to listen to.
I cannot recall what I said at partingdoubtless conventional things which were
not true.  Cavanelle politely escorted
me to the car, and there I left him with a
hand clasp which from my side was tender with sympathy and pity.
" Poor Cavanelle! poor Cavanelle!"
The words kept beating time in my
brain to the jingle of the car bells and the
regular ring of the mules' hoofs upon
the cobble stones. One moment I resolved to have a talk with him in which
I would endeavor to open his eyes to the
folly of thus casting his hopes and the
substance of his labor to the winds. The
next instant I had decided that chance
would possibly attend to Cavanelle's affair less clumsily than I could. "But
all the same,"' I wondered, ' is Cavanelle
a fool? is he a lunatic? is he under a
hypnotic spell?"  And then-strange
that I did not think of it before-I realized that Cavanelle loved Mathilde intensely, and we all know that love is
blind, but a god just the satne.
Two years passed before I saw Cavanelle again. I had been absent that
length of time from the city. In the
meanwhile Mathilde had died. She
and her little voice - the apotheosis of
insignificance were no more. It was
perhaps a year after my visit to her that
I read an account of her death in the



</P><P><PB REF="00000029.tif" SEQ="00000029" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="25" DISPLAYN="25" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=29"/>
CAVANELLE.


25


Picayune paper. Then came a momentary pang of commiseration for my good
Cavanelle. Chance had surely acted
here the part of a skillful though merciless surgeon; no temporizing, no half
measures. A deep, sharp thrust of the
scalpel; a moment of agonizing pain;
then rest, rest; convalescence; health;
happiness! Yes, Mathilde had been
dead a year and I was prepared for great
changes in Cavanelle.
He had lived like a hampered child
who does not recognize the restrictions
hedging it about, and lives a life of pathetic contentment in the midst of them.
But now all that was altered. He was,
doubtless, regaling himself with the halfbottles of St. Julien, which were never
before for him; with, perhaps, an occasional petit souper at Moreau's, and there
was no telling what little pleasures beside.
Cavanelle would certainly have bought
himself a suit of clothes or two of modern fit and finish. I would find him
with a brightened eye, a fuller cheek, as
became a man of his years; perchance,
even, a waxed moustache! So did my
imagination run rampant with me.
And after all, the hand which I
clasped across the counter was that of
the self-same Cavanelle I had left. It
was no fuller, no firmer. There were
even some additional lines visible
through the thin, brown beard.
"Ah, my poor Cavanelle! you have
suffered a grievous loss  since we
parted." I read in his face that he remembered the circumstances of our last
meeting, so there was no use in avoiding the subject. I had rightly conjectured that the wound had been a cruel
one; but in a year such wounds heal
with a healthy soul.
He could have talked for hours of
Mathilde's unhappy taking off, and if
the subject had possessed for me the


same touching fascination which it held
for him, doubtless, we would have done
so, but" And how is it now, mon ami? Are
you living in the same place? running
your little menage as before, my poor
Cavanelle? "
"Oh, yes, madame, except that my
Aunt Felicie is making her home with
me now. You have heard me speak of
my aunt-No? You never have heard
me speak of my Aunt Felicie Cavanelle
of Terrebonne! That, madame, is a
noble woman who has suffer' the mos'
cruel affliction an' deprivation since the
war.-No, madame, not in good health,
unfortunately, by any means. It is why
I esteem that a blessed privilege to give
her declining years those little comforts
ces peiits soins that is a woman's right
to expec' from men."
I knew what des petits soins" meant
with Cavanelle: doctors' visits, little
jaunts across the lake,friandises of every
description showered upon "Aunt Felicie," and he himself relegated to the
soup and bouillie which typified his prosaic existence.
I was unreasonably exasperated with
the man for awhile, and would not even
permit myself to notice the beauty in
texture and design of the mousseline de
laine which he had spread across the
counter in tempting folds. I was forced
to restrain a brutal desire to say something stinging and cruel to him for his
fatuity.
However, before I had regained the
street, the conviction that Cavanelle was
a hopeless fool seemed to reconcile me
to the situation and also afforded me
some diversion.
But even this estimate of my poor
Cavanelle was destined not to last. By
the time I had seated myself in the Prytania street car and passed up my nickel,
I was convinced that Cavanelle was an
angel.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:10"><BIBL><TITLE>Mrs. Hannah G. Solomon.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">26-27</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000030.tif" SEQ="00000030" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="893" N="26" DISPLAYN="26" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=30"/>
MRS. HANNAH G. SOLOMON.


Mrs. Hannah G. Solomon, whose portrait is here presented, is the founder
and first president of the National Council of Jewish Women. Mrs. Solomon is
not only a notable leader of intellectual
society in Chicago, but also a representative Jewess of America.
Born and bred in the western metropolis, this American Jewess combines in
her, marked individuality and the elements of energy and enthusiasm so char-.acteristic of her native city.
She is one of the ten children born to


the late Michael Greenebaum, an enthusiastic pioneer of Radical Reform
Judaism.   Permitting his children an
individual liberty rarely met with in
the older generation of Jews, Michael
Greenebaum succeeded in instilling into
the minds of his sons and daughters enthusiastic adherence to their ancestral faith. Associating fraternally
with Christians, admiring and assisting
them in their noble works of charity,
Mrs. Solomon preserved the strong Jewish affinities which now guide her in the



</P><P><PB REF="00000031.tif" SEQ="00000031" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="27" DISPLAYN="27" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=31"/>
MRS. HANNAH G. SOLOMON.


27


education of her three lovely children.
Exceedingly happy in the large circle of
relatives and entirely devoted to her
home, Mrs. Solomon still finds ample
time to cultivate a select coterie of
friends, as well as to attend to the various
duties necessitated by the many societies
to which she belongs.  To quote her
own words: "It is only a question of
how a women employs her time. I believe one can work for humanity without
neglecting the home. I superintend my
children's lessons, especially their musical training, as I believe with my
lamented father, that music exercises a
most beneficial influence in the home."
Since her fifteenth year, Mrs. Solomon
was actively engaged in organization
work of sectarian and non-sectarian character. At present she is a prominent
member of the Woman's Club of Chicago,


of the Sewing and the Personal Service
Societies.  She belongs to the Young
Ladies' Aid Society, is on the Lodging
House Committee, was elected a member of the Civic Federation, serves on the
Executive Committee of the Jewish Publication Society, and also belongs to the
Publication Committee of the American
Congress of Liberal Religions. At present Mrs. Solomon is devoting all her
energy and intellect to further the interest of the " National Council of ewish
Women," a branch of the National
Council of Women of the United States,
embracing a membership of over 800,000
women. Mrs. Solomon attributes her
remarkable success in organization work
to the fact that in all her endeavors she
was greatly assisted by the unselfish and
untiring efforts of her own sex.


REPORT OF THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF JEWISH WOMEN.
MRS. HANNAH G. SOLOMON, PRES.


HE National Council of Jewish
- Women is probably the youngest national organization in the
Council, having just passed its first birthday. It has early been trained in the
way it should walk, having in October
received and accepted an invitation to
join the National Council of Women. It
is the first religious organization of
women of our faith, and is an outgrowth
of the Congress held in our city during
the World's Fair in connection with the
World's Parliament of Religions.
The Congress was the first national
gathering of Jewish women and the idea
of a permanent organization originated
in the committee having it in charge.
The difficulty we experienced in reachilng Jewish women for organized effort
made it apparent that a national organi

zation was necessary to obviate such difficulties in the future. At the last
session of a most successful Congress,
the following resolutions were adopted
upon which to base our constitution:
Resolved, That the National Council of Jewish women shall
I. Seek to unite in closer relations women
interested in the work of religion, philanthropy
and education and shall consider practical
means of solving problems in these fields.
2. Shall encourage the study of the underlying principles of Judaism, the history, literature and customs of the Jews and their bearing
upon their own and the world's history.
3. Shall apply knowledge gained in this study
to the improvement of the Sabbath-schools and
in the work of social reform.
4. Shall secure the interest and aid of all influential persons in arousing the general sentiment against religious persecutions wherever,
whenever and against whomsoever shown, and
in finding means to prevent such persecutions.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:11"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Solomon, Hannah G.</AUTHORIND><TITLE>Report of the National Council of Jewish Women.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">27-31</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000031.tif" SEQ="00000031" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="27" DISPLAYN="27" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=31"/>
MRS. HANNAH G. SOLOMON.


27


education of her three lovely children.
Exceedingly happy in the large circle of
relatives and entirely devoted to her
home, Mrs. Solomon still finds ample
time to cultivate a select coterie of
friends, as well as to attend to the various
duties necessitated by the many societies
to which she belongs.  To quote her
own words: "It is only a question of
how a women employs her time. I believe one can work for humanity without
neglecting the home. I superintend my
children's lessons, especially their musical training, as I believe with my
lamented father, that music exercises a
most beneficial influence in the home."
Since her fifteenth year, Mrs. Solomon
was actively engaged in organization
work of sectarian and non-sectarian character. At present she is a prominent
member of the Woman's Club of Chicago,


of the Sewing and the Personal Service
Societies.  She belongs to the Young
Ladies' Aid Society, is on the Lodging
House Committee, was elected a member of the Civic Federation, serves on the
Executive Committee of the Jewish Publication Society, and also belongs to the
Publication Committee of the American
Congress of Liberal Religions. At present Mrs. Solomon is devoting all her
energy and intellect to further the interest of the " National Council of ewish
Women," a branch of the National
Council of Women of the United States,
embracing a membership of over 800,000
women. Mrs. Solomon attributes her
remarkable success in organization work
to the fact that in all her endeavors she
was greatly assisted by the unselfish and
untiring efforts of her own sex.


REPORT OF THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF JEWISH WOMEN.
MRS. HANNAH G. SOLOMON, PRES.


HE National Council of Jewish
- Women is probably the youngest national organization in the
Council, having just passed its first birthday. It has early been trained in the
way it should walk, having in October
received and accepted an invitation to
join the National Council of Women. It
is the first religious organization of
women of our faith, and is an outgrowth
of the Congress held in our city during
the World's Fair in connection with the
World's Parliament of Religions.
The Congress was the first national
gathering of Jewish women and the idea
of a permanent organization originated
in the committee having it in charge.
The difficulty we experienced in reachilng Jewish women for organized effort
made it apparent that a national organi

zation was necessary to obviate such difficulties in the future. At the last
session of a most successful Congress,
the following resolutions were adopted
upon which to base our constitution:
Resolved, That the National Council of Jewish women shall
I. Seek to unite in closer relations women
interested in the work of religion, philanthropy
and education and shall consider practical
means of solving problems in these fields.
2. Shall encourage the study of the underlying principles of Judaism, the history, literature and customs of the Jews and their bearing
upon their own and the world's history.
3. Shall apply knowledge gained in this study
to the improvement of the Sabbath-schools and
in the work of social reform.
4. Shall secure the interest and aid of all influential persons in arousing the general sentiment against religious persecutions wherever,
whenever and against whomsoever shown, and
in finding means to prevent such persecutions.



</P><P><PB REF="00000032.tif" SEQ="00000032" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="28" DISPLAYN="28" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=32"/>
28


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


The rigorous winters of I893-94 called
most of us to active philanthropic work
and somewhat delayed the drawing up
and adoption of the National Constitution. Officers had been elected from
among the members of the Chicago
Congress Committee, with full power to
act. On the 2d of January, I894, the
National Constitution and the Constitution for local sections were adopted. The
National Constitution provided for an
executive committee consisting of its
officers, one vice-president for each state
and ten directors. It provides for two
standing committees, one on Religion
and one on Philanthropy. Each section
patterns its board after the National
Board. The standing committees consist of five members, three residing in
one city, one member-at-large and one a
member of the National Board. The
committee on religion has a sub-committee on Sabbath-schools, also composed
of five members. The committees on
philanthropy and religion prepared each,
a course of study to be followed by every
section. These were supplemented by
the Board, printed and distributed, one
to each member of the Council. They
provide a complete course of study in
religion, in philanthropy, a bibliography
and a complete list of subjects for papers
for the general meetings.
Each section is divided into reading
circles of ten or more members, each circle having a leader.
The religious program for this year
provides for the study of Jewish History
beginning with the Babylonian Captivity
and ending with the Christian Era. A
syllabus prepared by Prof. Richard Gottheil is used as a guide, yet leaders are
free to follow their own plans if they so
desire. In addition, a portion of the
Bible is studied and discussed. In some
cities Bible lectures are given once a
week by the Rabbis. The circles meet
twice each month. For those who de

sire a broader field of study, an extensive
course of reading has been prepared.
The philanthropy program provides
for the study of the latest and best
methods.
The National Council stands for preventive philanthropy, personal service
and organization in charity. Its method
this year has been to distribute the best
pamphlets upon these lines which it
could obtain. In December it distributed four monographs issued by the New
York Charity Organization. One on
the "New Charity on the Old," Rev.
H. L. Wayland; " Methods and Machinery of the Organization of Charity," by
Alex. Johnson; " Duties of Friendly Visitors," by Mrs. Lowell; "Personal Service," by Mrs. Putnam. We are happy
to say that these pamphlets have not
suffered the usual fate of these documents to be put in the waste paper basket without reading. They have been
read and discussed in the circles.
In January we distributed the report
of the Philanthropic Summer Work of
the Chicago Section of the National
Council of Jewish Women and a leaflet
on the " Elise Frank fund for the education of orphans in Homes." Our next
pamphlet will be one on "Manual
Training," which is being prepared for
us by Prof. G. Bamberger of the Jewish
Manual Training School of Chicago.
The members of the Standing Committee on Religion are: Mrs. Minnie D.
Lewis, of New York; Miss Sarah Lyons
and Miss Lillie Hershfield, of New York;
Miss Mary Cowen, of Philadelphia; Miss
Julia Felsenthal, of Chicago.
The members of the Committee on
Philanthropy are: Mrs. C. S. Benjamin
chairman; Mrs. I. M. Appel, Mrs. S.
Holzman, all of Denver; Miss Julia
Richmond, of New York, and Mrs. Witkowsky, of Chicago.
General meetings of each section are
held once a month. Every three months.



</P><P><PB REF="00000033.tif" SEQ="00000033" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="29" DISPLAYN="29" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=33"/>
REPORT OF THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF JEWISH WOMEN. 29


the meetings must be held at such time
when those of its members who are wageworkers may attend. At the general
meetings two papers are presented and
discussed, one on religion and one on
philanthropy. The topics are taken from
the list prepared by the National Board.
Each section prepares its program for
the season and submits it to the National
Board. Each section reports once a
month to the Board, so that it is kept
in touch with its work.
The annual due is one dollar, one-half
of which is paid into the National treasury, the other into the local. All funds
for special philanthropic work are raised
by voluntary subscription.
The National Council has a membership of fifteen hundred, the sections
being in Chicago, Alleghany, Quincy,
Newark, Baltimore, Duluth, St. Paul,
Minneapolis, New York, Denver, Philadelphia, Kansas City and Cincinnati.
The first section to organize outside of
Chicago was in Quincy. Mrs. I. H.
Lesem is the president of this flourishing organization, which, although small
in number, is doing fine work in study.
There are three sections in Minnesota,
organized under the direction of Mrs.
Nina Morais Cohen, the able vice-president of that state. One is in Duluth and
West Superior, of which Mrs. I. Van
Baalen is president. A large sum of
money was raised by giving a charity
ball, the proceeds of which are being
used for philanthropic work. Mrs. Cohen
is president of the Minneapolis section,
which is doing serious study work and
has an exhaustive program prepared. A
committee has been appointed to investigate the need and possibility of establishing free kindergartens. In St. Paul, Mrs.
H. Haas is president. The section, in
addition to the study work, expects to
devote itself to work among the children of the poor.
Mrs. Pauline H. Rosenberg, the excel

lent vice-president of Pennsylvania, is
president of the Pittsburg section. This
has one hundred and ten members. At
a meeting held there December 4, a
set of resolutions was offered and unanimously passed recommending that the
sum of $I,200 be raised among the Jewish residents of Pittsburg to be presented
to the Free Kindergarten Association,
for establishing a new school. At the
last meeting the Chairman of the Committee, Mrs. A. L. Weil, presented her
report, and the sum of $I,630 which had
been collected was presented to the officers of the Free Kindergarten Association. The new school is to be called the
Columbian, in honor of the Pittsburg
Council. Their other work has been to
improve the condition of the Sabbathschool and to establish an infant class.
This section has also an interesting program and numerous study circles. Philadelphia section, Mrs. S. B. Fleisher,
president, has but recently been organized, with the assistance of Miss American, the corresponding secretary of the
National Board, and promises to be very
successful.
Of the New York section Mrs. Kohut
is president, but owing to the absence
from the city of most of the officers the
work was delayed until almost recently.
Several interesting meetings have been
held, notably one at which a paper on
Working Girls' Clubs was read, which
was discussed by Miss Grace Dodge and
others. The work promises to grow and
be very efficient, both in religion and
philanthropy.
In Baltimore Mrs. Bertha Rayner
Frank is president. The section has
seventy-four members. Interesting papers have been presented looking to the
practical solution of philanthropic problems, one on Personal Service, the discussion aiming to provide means of procuring work and better dwellings for the
poor.



</P><P><PB REF="00000034.tif" SEQ="00000034" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="30" DISPLAYN="30" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=34"/>
30


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


The Newark section, Mrs. Theresa
Grotta, president, was one of the first to
organize. Excellent papers and lectures
form the program of this section.
Mrs. Carrie S. Benjamin, the vicepresident of Colorado, is president of the
Denver section, which, next to Chicago,
has the largest membership of any. It
has a number of study circles, which are
largely attended. Its general meetings
have been very successful. It has established a free Kindergarten and Sundayschool among the poor, does work in the
Industrial school, in the evening schools,
arranges evening entertainments for the
poor, and has a large committee for visiting the charitable institutions and for
personal service.
Kansas City and Cincinnati organizations are just coming into being, the
names of the presidents, Mrs. S. Lieberman, of Kansas City, and Miss Clara
Block, of Cincinnati, assure success in
these cities.
The Chicago section, of which Mrs.
Conrad Witkowsky is president, has two
hundred and fifty members, one honorary life member, Mrs. Ellen M. Henrotin, the president of the Federation of
Women's Clubs, for whose encouragement and assistance in our Congress work
we are deeply thankful. There are ten
study circles with from ten to twenty
members in each. One of these circles
pursues its work in German. The general meetings are very successful. It
has decided upon two lines of philanthropic work, the first that of charity
organization. To this end it called a
conference of Jewish Women's Charity
Organizations in Chicago, of which there
are twenty-six, and after considerable
work a conference committee has been
created made up of two members of each
organization. This committee has agreed
upon one plan of records and is now
considering the plan of visitation. It is
hoped that in time we will have a com

plete charity organization. For its special philanthropic work the Chicago section has established a summer sewing
school. Girls from ten to fourteen years
of age are taught sewing and employed
to sew garments for the poor. They are
paid twenty-five cents a day for five days
of each week during the summer months.
Fifty children were employed last summer and each was given an outing of
two weeks in the country. A teacher
was paid to teach them and one accompanied them to the country. The amount
of money which this cost was less than
$I,ooo and was raised by voluntary subscription. It is hoped that enough money
will be provided this year to extend the
work, and that a class of boys as well as
girls, may be benefited. The study work
of the Council is by no means narrow.
Such programs as the following are
the work of the circles: "Myths of
Creation," the "Myths of the Greeks,"
"Norsemen," "Germans,"     Character
Study, "Eve," Milton's Creation, " Lilith." The following are some of the
subjects for papers at general meetings:
"From   Fetichism  to  Monotheism,"
" Saul," Browning's poem, the "Biblical
Saul," the "Attitude of Women of Leisure to her Wage-earning Sister." " Institutional vs. Home Influence.""  I am
a man, nothing in human life can fail
to have its interest for me."
Thus, the first three portions of our
resolutions have been acted upon. The
last, that relating to religious persecution,
is a work for the future. That there is a
broad field for all religious organizations
in this work needs only Russia and Armenia to prove.
It is deplorable that state etiquette
compels us to wear smoked glasses when
signing treaties, that our statesmen are
kept in a ferment if a seal is taken on the
wrong side of an imaginary fence, our
armies kept in training less a few feet of
ground in the heart of Africa should fall



</P><P><PB REF="00000035.tif" SEQ="00000035" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="31" DISPLAYN="31" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=35"/>
REPORT OF THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF JEWISH WOMEN. 31


to the wrong country and thus disturb
the equilibrium of the earth's axis to
such an extent that it would lose its
bearings. Yet we patiently wait while
a monarch disregards all laws of humanity; we permit him to throw upon our
shoulders the task of feeding, clothing
and educating subjects whom he has
pauperized, and whom he will only care
for when he can prove them guilty of
state crimes, or until he grows better
humored. Let us hope for the poor Armenian's sake that the Turk will prove a
better Mohammedan than his mighty
neighbor was a Christian.
Let us also hope that in the twentieth
century the serious questions of theatre
hats and balloon sleeves may have been
satisfactorily solved, and our statesmen
can give proper attention to international
treaties, and that they will negotiate
only with nations treating subjects with
some regard for the dictates of humanity.
What our organization will accomplish in the future is a little difficult to
predict. We are receiving every possible encouragement from our Rabbis, and
should women desire to enter the ministry there will be no obstacle thrown in
their way.
Te hope to assist in establishing a
summer school where the best may be
taught to an intelligent audience, one
composed of thoroughly prepared students. The amateur has here a legitimate field, that of appreciative audience
to the scholar, to encourage and make


possible the production and teaching of
the very best.
We hope also to enter the missionary
field. Our work will be among the poor
and ignorant of our own faith. We will
not attempt to make inferior in quality
Jews out of inferior in quality Christians
with food and clothes and Christmas
trees, nor will we attempt to proselyte
among any of the historic faiths, feeling
quite skeptical as to the sort we would
get, judging by inference in our own case.
We do not wish to be understood as
underestimating the magnificent work
done for humanity by those heroes, the
Christian missionaries among the savage
and barbarous. But it is a sad statement that two hundred thousand dollars
should be spent annually in converting
Jews, for such converts are neither loss
nor gain to any faith, and I make not a
single  exception.  A  warm, well-fed
Christian is more desirable than a cold
hungry Jew, yet when we have two hundred thousand dollars to spend in missionary work we will not supply tenants
for the particular region reserved for
Jewish residents in mansions in the sky,
but put up strong, good, sanitary tenement houses on earth.
As members of the National Council
of Women we hope to keep in touch
with the work of the Women of our land,
and are always ready to join hands in
any work for the good of men, regardless
of creed.


IF I KNEW.


If I knew the box where the smiles were kept,
No matter how large the key,
Or strong the bolt, I would try so hard,
'Twould open, I know, for me.
Then over the land and the sea, broadcast,
I'd scatter the smiles to play,
That the children's faces might hold them fast
For many and many a day.


If I knew a box that was large enough
To hold all the frowns I meet,
I would like to gather them, every one,
From nursery, school and street,
Then folding and holding I'd pack them in,
And turning the monster key,
I'd hire a giant to drop the box
To the depths of the deep, deep sea.
-Maud Wyman.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:12"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Wyman, Maude</AUTHORIND><TITLE>If I Knew.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">31</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000035.tif" SEQ="00000035" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="31" DISPLAYN="31" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=35"/>
REPORT OF THE NATIONAL COUNCIL OF JEWISH WOMEN. 31


to the wrong country and thus disturb
the equilibrium of the earth's axis to
such an extent that it would lose its
bearings. Yet we patiently wait while
a monarch disregards all laws of humanity; we permit him to throw upon our
shoulders the task of feeding, clothing
and educating subjects whom he has
pauperized, and whom he will only care
for when he can prove them guilty of
state crimes, or until he grows better
humored. Let us hope for the poor Armenian's sake that the Turk will prove a
better Mohammedan than his mighty
neighbor was a Christian.
Let us also hope that in the twentieth
century the serious questions of theatre
hats and balloon sleeves may have been
satisfactorily solved, and our statesmen
can give proper attention to international
treaties, and that they will negotiate
only with nations treating subjects with
some regard for the dictates of humanity.
What our organization will accomplish in the future is a little difficult to
predict. We are receiving every possible encouragement from our Rabbis, and
should women desire to enter the ministry there will be no obstacle thrown in
their way.
Te hope to assist in establishing a
summer school where the best may be
taught to an intelligent audience, one
composed of thoroughly prepared students. The amateur has here a legitimate field, that of appreciative audience
to the scholar, to encourage and make


possible the production and teaching of
the very best.
We hope also to enter the missionary
field. Our work will be among the poor
and ignorant of our own faith. We will
not attempt to make inferior in quality
Jews out of inferior in quality Christians
with food and clothes and Christmas
trees, nor will we attempt to proselyte
among any of the historic faiths, feeling
quite skeptical as to the sort we would
get, judging by inference in our own case.
We do not wish to be understood as
underestimating the magnificent work
done for humanity by those heroes, the
Christian missionaries among the savage
and barbarous. But it is a sad statement that two hundred thousand dollars
should be spent annually in converting
Jews, for such converts are neither loss
nor gain to any faith, and I make not a
single  exception.  A  warm, well-fed
Christian is more desirable than a cold
hungry Jew, yet when we have two hundred thousand dollars to spend in missionary work we will not supply tenants
for the particular region reserved for
Jewish residents in mansions in the sky,
but put up strong, good, sanitary tenement houses on earth.
As members of the National Council
of Women we hope to keep in touch
with the work of the Women of our land,
and are always ready to join hands in
any work for the good of men, regardless
of creed.


IF I KNEW.


If I knew the box where the smiles were kept,
No matter how large the key,
Or strong the bolt, I would try so hard,
'Twould open, I know, for me.
Then over the land and the sea, broadcast,
I'd scatter the smiles to play,
That the children's faces might hold them fast
For many and many a day.


If I knew a box that was large enough
To hold all the frowns I meet,
I would like to gather them, every one,
From nursery, school and street,
Then folding and holding I'd pack them in,
And turning the monster key,
I'd hire a giant to drop the box
To the depths of the deep, deep sea.
-Maud Wyman.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:13"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Wise, Julius, M.D.</AUTHORIND><TITLE>Popular Science and Medicine</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">32-35</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000036.tif" SEQ="00000036" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="889" N="32" DISPLAYN="32" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=36"/>
ceteOPULAR           CIIZFNCII
AND
#,1       EDICINE
CONDUCTED BY JULIUS WISE, M. D.


In treating scientific subjects in a
popular manner, it is safest to take it for
granted that the reader is not familiar
with technical words or terms.  It is
easy to make the mistake of being impressively profound or abstruse, but it
is not so light a task to write with a
simplicity that will assure clearness.
However, I will endeavor in the limited
space placed at my disposal each month
by the editor of THE AMERICAN JEWESS,
to be as plain in my style of writing as
the subjects under consideration permit.
Indeed, I am more than a little afraid
that in my desire to avoid being heavy
and tedious I may run into the other
extreme, and be accused of lacking the
dignity demanded by custom in the
treatment of subjects of so serious a
character.
It is not my intention to adopt any
especial system in conducting what may
be designated the "Popular Science,
Medical and Sanitary Department" of
this magazine, but I will from month
to month hold informal chats with my
readers upon scientific, medical and sanitary topics, leaving it to time and circumstances to develop specific characteristics, if there are to be any. If in
the course of time I can succeed in
establishing between my readers and
myself an intimacy which will make
them sufficiently well acquainted to feel
at liberty to take a part in these chats,


it will be to me a source of great pleasure, and let us hope, of benefit to them.
There are many things of importance
constantly occurring in the scientific
world that are of general interest, and
sure to become topics of conversation in
cultured circles, where all are supposed
to be sufficiently conversant with them
to take a part in their discussion. In
the fields of medicine and sanitation
much is to be gleaned that can be placed
before the reader in a popular form. It
will not be my object to make doctors
out of the subscribers of THE AMERICAN
JEWESS, still there is a great deal of
medical and hygienic information that
can be conveyed in simple language and
be made to prove both interesting and
useful to the lay reader.
Notwithstanding much that is said
and written at the present time, but
little advance has been made in the science of medicine. As far as the giving
of drugs for the cure of disease is concerned, we are not much wiser than our
forefathers. Of course, great progress
has been made during the present century, especially the last half of it, in
what is more properly called the "art of
medicine."  In the application of mechanical means, as in surgery, there
have been great improvements and discoveries.  Many new  operations have
been successfully undertaken, and surgical diseases hitherto considered invari



</P><P><PB REF="00000037.tif" SEQ="00000037" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="33" DISPLAYN="33" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=37"/>
POPULAR SCIENCE AND MEDICINE.


33


ably mortal, have been found to yield
readily to the skillful surgeon. Diseases
formerly unknown or obscure have been
made recognizable by improved methods
and instruments and surgical interference
with the best results is now undertaken
where it would not have been dreamed
of fifty years ago. Much has been
learned as to the cause and nature of
diseases, and there have been long strides
in the diagnosing of them, but it remains
true that we know no more of how to
cure diseases with medicines than was
known fifty, a hundred, or a thousand
years back. On the other hand, most
wonderful progress must be credited to
the present century when it comes to the
prevention of sickness. The list of preventable diseases grows longer every day,
and the science of sanitation is now so
well understood, that it is not too much
to say that if the established laws of
sanitary science could be enforced there
would be no sickness at all. People
would die only of old age, and the average expectation of life would be lengthened to a period that would parallel the
days of the Biblical patriarchs.  If,
therefore, we desire to remain healthy, or
to become so if we are not, it is to sanitation and not to medication that we
must look.
Health is the sine qua non of happiness
here on earth. Without it all the other
gifts of the gods are showered upon us
in vain. Like many other truths, this is
very trite, but one would be inclined to
doubt its being true in witnessing the
general disregard of the accepted cannons of sanitary science. There is no
one thing, for instance, so surely dependent upon another as is beauty upon
health; yet nothing is more common
than to see a woman having recourse to
artificial means to make herself goodlooking, sparing neither time, patience
nor expense to accomplish her object.
Yet, at the same time, she is neglecting


the commonest and most essential laws
of nature-the very laws which are intended to subserve the purpose for which
she is striving. I have seen young girls
in the ballroom with elbows covered with
powder to hide the scurf that has formed
upon them as a result of insufficient bathing. In the same way women plaster
their faces with cosmetics to hide conditions of the skin that would not be present had the bath been properly used, and
that could be cured by recourse to the
same simple means. There is an anecdote current of a French duchess who
consulted a physician, and he, fearing
that his advice might offend, confided in
the husband. The latter felt some delicacy in telling his wife what the doctor
had advised, but happening into her
dressing room one day when she was absent found a valuable set of pearls
lying upon the dressing table. The duke
quietly picked up the jewels, and lifting
the lid of the bath tub, dropped them in.
There was a great to-do, but neither detectives nor anybody else could find a
trace of the lost pearls. About a month
after the mysterious disappearance her
ladyship concluded to take a bath, and
of course the missing property came to
light. The duke confessed, and the
duchess, let us hope, took the hint. I
have known instances where apparently
refined women had to be instructed to
use a special kind of soap, in a special
manner, and at specified intervals, as the
only way of getting them to bathe their
children with sufficient frequency.
Air, light, water and exercise are indispensable to good health, and consequently to good looks. But it is not
necessary to take them as if they were
medicines, as is done by many people.
There are no individuals more unpleasant to themselves and to others than
those who are constantly doing something for the benefit of their health.
The nasty-clean people find their coun


</P><P><PB REF="00000038.tif" SEQ="00000038" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="34" DISPLAYN="34" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=38"/>
34


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


terparts in the unhealthily hygienic individuals. It is not necessary to eat
with a pair of scales at the table, or
make a fetish out of the thermometer.
The very poorest form of exercise is that
taken for the sake of exercise alone.
The normal individual needs nothing of
that sort. Nine-tenths of all men and
women get all the exercise they need in
the performance of their regular duties.
But the procuring of proper air, light
and water are subjects of the utmost importance, both in public and private hygiene. Public sanitation is, therefore,
one of the first duties of a good citizen,
and it may be said right here, that few
duties are more neglected. The prevalent indifference to municipal corruption
and inefficiency which characterizes the
American people, makes itself nowhere
more manifest than in connection with
sanitary affairs. The fond mother who
trembles at the very names of smallpox,
scarlet fever or diphtheria, and uses every
precaution that wealth and intelligence
can procure or suggest to protect her
children, has all her efforts neutralized
by the criminal folly of those who should
be guardians of the public health. Her
own home and its immediate surroundings may be a model of hygienic prudence, but perhaps it is around the corner, or it may be in some distant part
of the city, that the tenements and the
hovels of the unfortunate poor are breeding every form of contagious and infectious disease. No chain is stronger than
its weakest link, and as long as one
single center of corruption is left in a
community the rich are equally in danger with the poor. Public sanitation is,
therefore, of importance to the mother,
even if she have no higher motive than
self-protection. The accumulations of
filth in the lowest slums of the city, the
case of contagious disease in the most
distant and humble quarter, concern her
as much as if they were next door to her


own home. To the man of business it is
of importance that his city shall have
the reputation of being a healthy one; a
low death rate for a town is an attraction
for permanent settlers and transient visitors. The mere rumor of a contagious
disease in a city is sufficient to keep custom and customers away. The loss in
money and trade sustained last winter
and spring by the merchants of Chicago
in consequence of the prevalence of
smallpox in the city would a thousand
times over have covered the expense of
keeping the disease away.
None of us can afford to neglect the
duties devolving upon us as citizens,and
it is one of the most hopeful signs of the
times that women are beginning to interest themselves actively in public sanitation.  Their superior conscientiousness
and natural sense of order and cleanliness may accomplish much that has been
hitherto neglected. The stupid indifference of the men is extremely discouraging to sanitarians who have the welfare
of the entire community at heart, and
they hail with pleasure the evidences of
growing interest in all questions of municipal government, especially of public
health, displayed by the women. In this
branch of science a wide field opens itself
to the alleged weaker sex, and I am inclined to think that there will be less opposition by the men to their entering it
than has been the case with the other
professions. Sanitary science as a profession is a comparatively new thing; in
this country it can scarcely be said to
exist at all. But it is bound to have a
great future, and it will afford an additional outlet for ambitious women. A
knowledge of medicine is not at all necessary in this department of science, although our professional sanitarians in
this country have hitherto generally
been doctors-and a precious poor lot
they have been; I once defined sanitarians as men who had failed in physic,



</P><P><PB REF="00000039.tif" SEQ="00000039" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="886" N="35" DISPLAYN="35" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=39"/>
POPULAR SCIENCE AND MEDICINE.


35


and the definition was not far from the
truth. But the profession of sanitation
is growing too big to remain in the hands
of broken-down doctors and wire-pulling
politicians. They have controlled the
health departments too long alreadythat's why such poor results have been
obtained. The outlook now, however,
is brighter, and with women fitting
themselves for the work of sanitation we
may look for the great benefits which
are sure to flow from the proper study
and application of the science.
' [To this Department our readers are invited
to direct all questions on health and beauty, to
which the Doctor will cheerfully respond.ED.]


During the heated term when the intestinal canal is prone to riotous conduct
-in other words when gastrointestinal
troubles abound, dependent in a majority
of cases upon an acid fermentative condition of the bowels, the habitual use of
the effervescent lithia-potash water, or
" Garrod Spa," of Dr. Enno Sander, will
be found to serve admirably as a curative and prophylactic measure.
In infants and children it is a splendid
substitute for lime-water, being more
agreeable when used as a drink, or added
to milk.
"It is not only a pronounced alkali,
but being carbonated it enlivens all fluids
to which it may be added."-Dr. I. N.
Love in tlie Medical Mirror.


I



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:14"><BIBL><TITLE>Music and Art</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">36-37</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000040.tif" SEQ="00000040" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="892" N="36" DISPLAYN="36" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=40"/>
4 ~~
11 I
a'~ "I


In no community of the world is the
impulse of a generous support of musical and dramatic art stronger than it is
among the Jewish people. This is particularly true of the Jewish-American
people, who have from the earliest development of music and drama in the
United States, ever been found actively
and generously fostering its development
and contributing to its permanent establishment. Nor is this strange, when we
recall the immortal composers and great
musical and dramatic artists who have
been given to the world by the Jewish
race. The hearts of the masses of that
people have been attuned to the melody
of song, and have throbbed with sympathetic emotion in unison with all the
phases of the dramatic illustration of
life, since the day stars sang together in
the dim ages of the far East.
With the Jewish woman music is, and
ever has been, a passion, from the "Psalm
of Life " softly sung at the baby's cradle
to the appreciation of those glorious harmonies of the great tone poets, which
in their beauty, majesty and exaltation
touch the souls even in superior spheres.
THE AMERICAN JEWESS, therefore,
would be incomplete without the expression of special regard in this direction,
and its aim will be to so treat matters
musical and dramatic as to include in
each number a condensed yet adequate
review of musical and dramatic events
as they occur.
36


Generally speaking, in the United
States the current season has not been
a successful or satisfactory one in a pecuniary sense. The prevalent depression
succeeding the panic, and the corresponding scarcity of money, served to make
the path of the artist and the manager
alike peculiarly trying.  The season
opened last autumn, therefore, with
considerable misgiving, an apprehension
which by this time is found to have been
justified, as for years past the proportion
of unremunerative enterprises of an arttistic character has not equalled the unsatisfactory showing of the present year.
The same may be said of dramatic organizations, of which a larger number
have been called in from the road or
have actually disbanded than was ever
known in the history of the theatrical
profession in the country.  Notwithstanding this, the season has proved an
interesting one and marked by the appearance and performances in the United
States of not a few renowned artists from
abroad, and by the continued popularity
of established public favorites at home.
In the summary of entertainment,
Grand Opera under the direction of
Abbey, Schoeffel &amp; Grau, of course,
takes first rank. The opera is an unfailing drawing card.  Notwithstanding commercial depression or financial
stringency, and the fact that it is a
decidedly expensive luxury, the organization is a magnificent one, and the



</P><P><PB REF="00000041.tif" SEQ="00000041" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="37" DISPLAYN="37" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=41"/>
MUSIC AND ART.


37


phenomenal success of last season is repeated this year. The splendid character of the organization has everything to
do with this, for the time is past when
the public will patronize "the single
star" organizations of years ago. Today it is necessary to create for the public an organization unrivalled in point
of renowned soloists, adequate supporting artists in subordinate roles, a really
large, musical and well-trained chorus,
and an orchestra sufficient in numerical
strength and musical proficiency to supply the grand orchestral, the frame work
of the standard operas, both old and new.
With such artists as Mme. Melba,
Emma Eames, Nordica, Schalchi, Jean
de Reszke, Edward de Reszke and Maurel, such a repertoire of Grand Opera is
given in Chicago as equals the most brilliant seasons in New York, in Paris, in
London or in Vienna. Thus Chicago
has enjoyed, indeed has fairly revelled in
grand opera, and the great Auditorium
has been filled night after night with
audiences representative in character,
and cordial to enthusiasm; audiences
in all the bright array of superb dressing,
scintillating with the lustre of gems, radiant in beautiful colors, a splendid sight
in itself.
An entirely original and interesting
dramatic attraction which has provoked
more than usual curiosity and has been
received with marked attention was


" The Manxman," by Mr. Wilson Barrett. The peculiar interest in this drama
was due to the fact that it is his own
dramatization of Mr. Hall Caine's celebrated novel of the same. It is based
upon a very strong and unusual story;
a story which deals mercilessly, as Mr.
Caine always does, with susceptibilities
of human affection and the weaknesses
of human passion. Its production in the
United States has been one of the notable
events of the present amusement season.
Think of it, the stately and historic
McVickers', the stage so often trod by
the classic Booth and the melodramatic
Jefferson, to say nothing of all the illustrious stars of the past, recently accommodated itself to the roaring lions and
the trained tigers of the Hagenback circus. Well, so much for tradition andbusiness.
For the rest, the play-going public has
again been delighted with the admirable
performances of that accomplished character actor, Otis Skinner, who, it would
seem, at a single bound shines out in
worthily deserved stellar rank, having
by sheer force of personal genius and
consummate taste accomplished more
in the short span of two or three seasons
than some of the laurel crowned veterans of the earlier stage achieved in
a painful and ambitious lifetime.


JJ



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:15"><BIBL><TITLE>The Woman who Talks</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">38-41</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000042.tif" SEQ="00000042" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="893" N="38" DISPLAYN="38" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=42"/>
THEi WOAN......WMno TALKS


The Woman who Talks desires to
make her best bow to her sisters, the
Women who talk, and begs to inform
them that this department is not intended for her exclusive occupation. On
the contrary, she is more than willing to
share it with all women who talk. They
are to make use of these columns for the
ventilation of all subjects pertaining to
woman: social, domestic, religious, literary, political, philanthropic, and so
on-ad infinituz. For the housekeeper's instruction especially, we bespeak
the aid of the ladies. Recipes which
have been tried and not found wanting,
will meet with grateful appreciation.
We would further request the obliging
contributors of cookery recipes to make
them very explicit, as we are aiming to
instruct the inexperienced at the outset of
the thorny road, not the past mistresses
of household science. Cook Books may
be very well for the knowing, but as regards the tyro, they are largely on a par
with "The Complete British Housewife," the property of charming Mrs.
Rokesmith, nee Wilfer. "The Complete British Housewife," however sound
a Britain at heart, was by no means an
expert Britain in expressing herself with
clearness in the British tongue, and
sometimes might have issued her directions to equal purpose in the Kamchatkan language. "'There was likewise a
coolness on the part of the British Housewife, which Mrs. John Rokesmith found
highly exasperating; she would say
38


'Take a salamander,' as if a general
should command a private to catch a
Tartar. Or she would casually issue
the order 'Throw in a handful of something,' entirely unattainable."  Household recipes for everything necessary to
keep a mansion, from turret to foundation stone, contents and inhabitants inclusive, "beautiful, entire and clean,"
will also be heartily welcome. I trust the
experienced will take pity on the ignorant and give them the benefit of their
superior advantages or training.
I intend to do considerable talking
myself, but I hope, dear ladies, whenever
you find me talking through my hat, as
the popular phrase has it, you will, without unnecessary ceremony, call me down
promptly. The Woman who Talks
makes no pretensions.  Observe her
meek and lowly title; safely entrenched
behind its non-committality, she may
well defy the shafts of stinging criticism.
Were I of the ultra-advanced I might
have styled myself, " The woman who
knows,the woman who thinks, the woman
who criticises, the woman who sees, feels,
hears, smells, smokes." But bearing in
mind the advice of one of the Wise Men
of Greece, I knew myself, and concluded
I could truthfully assure an expectant
public that I can talk. Of what pray?
That remains to be seen. To this delightful pastime, I once more invite the
co-operation of my sisters from all parts
of the compass. Nor would I exclude
the dominant sex from these edifying



</P><P><PB REF="00000043.tif" SEQ="00000043" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="39" DISPLAYN="39" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=43"/>
THE WOMAN WHO TALKS.


39


chats, and to encourage the faint of heart
I quote from Lord Beaconsfield: " Talk
to woman as much as you can. This is
the best school. This is the way to gain
fluency, because you need not care what
you say and had better not be sensible."
Is this not a toothsome sop, oh Cerberus!
*  * *
And the cry of the distressed mistress
is once more heard in the land. Her
burden is greater than she can bear.
Oh, those inefficient servants! She
cannot get a cook as is a cook, or a
housemaid as is a housemaid, as for
washing-a universal groan ascends.
Various remedies have been suggested
for this lamentable state of affairs. The
press has opened wide its columns to
numerous suggestions and plans for
training servants in the way they should
work. And when these schools are in
full swing let us fervently trust they will
start similar ones for the training of
mistresses. She who would command
must know how to serve. She who
would be obeyed must command intelligently. It is impossible for a mistress
ignorant of the first principles of housekeeping to gauge correctly the length of
time it takes to carry out a given command. She complains of the servant's
slowness; the harrassed drudge waxes
insolent, is discharged and then-da capo.
"I am so discouraged with my upstairs girl, I don't know what to do.
She's a perfect snail. She actually took
three hours to clean this room this morning," and my hostess sighed profoundly.
I glanced about the apartment. Double
curtains, lambrequins, upholstered furniture, rugs, pictures, bric-a-brac run
riot, tidies, drapes, etc. etc., galore.
" I should call her a rapid worker."
"No, really?"
" Yes, really. Did you ever attempt
cleaning this room yourself? I know I
could n't possibly do it in less time."


" Well, perhaps you are right. But it
does seem an awful long time."
"Bridget, I don't like the way you
cook rice."
" What the matter with it, mum?"
" It's too soggy. The grains ought
to be separate."
"Yes 'm."
And poor Bridget, whose culinary
skill was developed in a log cabin in the
peat bogs of Ould Ireland, descends to
the kitchen greatly edified. If, however, Mrs. Croesus would know something besides fault finding and give
Bridget a practical lesson in rice cooking, she would inspire a feeling of respect
in that benighted minion which no number of diamond rings sparkling on useless fingers will ever accomplish.
* * *
Young ladies, you who intend to get
married, and you who don't, let me now
have a little confab with you.  Marriage is not all love and dove, kiss and
bliss, the "Duchess" and ilk to the contrary, notwithstanding. It also has its
business aspects. In the matrimonial
co-partnership, the duties of each are as
clearly defined as in any other business.
The man must earn the funds and the
woman, in the office at home, must invest these funds with prudence and intelligence, so that the wheels of the
household machinery may run without
undue friction. If your husband should
fail to support you, you would justly
consider yourself an aggrieved woman.
And if you fail to properly shoulder your
share of the burden, is he not equally
entitled to consider himself an aggrieved
man? Nobody would think for a moment of taking unto himself an inefficient, incompetent partner. Remember,
dear girls, in marriage you are full partners with equal rights, but also with
equal duties, equal responsibilities.
Should you not feel called upon to dis


</P><P><PB REF="00000044.tif" SEQ="00000044" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="40" DISPLAYN="40" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=44"/>
40


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


charge these duties faithfully, then do
not marry.   Nowadays the woman
who doesn't marry is not such an unenviable creature after all. I, personally, am a great advocate of marriage,
mainly as an excellent school of discipline. But as the great majority of women, married or single, must keep house
sometime during their earthly sojourn,
it is as well for them to prepare properly
and in good season for their inevitable
destiny. The art and science of housekeeping in all its branches should be
part of the school curriculum for every
girl. For it is a science and should be
raised to its proper dignity as such.
The spasmodic and haphazard fashion in
which it is of necessity acquired by most
women to-day, is a sad commentary on
our much vaunted civilization. There
is no royal road to it; it comes not by
inspiration, neither does it drop like the
gentle dew from heaven.   " When I
have to do it, I'll know how," quoths
the foolish virgin. Why waste your
time studying French. When you get
to France you'll know how. And in the
meanwhile, unsavory messes burden the
tables of many a family in this land of
plenty and the immense army of dyspeptics is daily receiving new recruits.,      * &gt;
The New Woman! the New Woman!
is the cry on every side. But where, oh
where, lingers the New Man? Is he
looming on the horizon, or will the
feminine phcenix still have to content
herself with the Old Specimen?
The deed is done. That grave and
dignified body, the legislature of California, has sat in judgment on feminine
head-gear in places of public amusement
and, with true masculine discrimination,
condemned it wholesale. Inoffensive
bonnets, toques, alsatian bows, together
with the flaring cart-wheels of the nod

ding, hearse-like plumes-all the pretty
toggery crushed in one fell swoop.
" Whole hog or none " is evidently the
motto of the California law makers.
Sisters, pause and reflect! Where will
this interference end?
What is the logical outcome of this
gratuitous meddling? Is it possible that
our bicycle bloomers are in danger? To
arms, to arms!
In the benighted ages, when the
pointed toes of the gallants' shoes grew
so long that they had to be worn tied up
at the knee, the law stepped in and curtailed them-the shoes, not the gallants.
When the English conquered the
Highlanders, some time or other, a law
was passed to compel those hardy mountaineers to wear breeches. They wore
them-hanging on sticks thrown over
their shoulders.
Have we returned to the dark ages?
"Is civilization a failure?"
Had the California Solons consulted
with me, as was their bounden duty, I
would have saved them much trouble
and expense. A little diplomatic talk
with the leaders of fashion, those mighty
potentates whom the feminine populace
ollows like sheep the bell-weather, and
the bloodless victory would have been
won. That Mrs. Nonentity must obey
implicity the mandates of Mrs. NewRich is a time-honored American institution. "The birds can fly and why
can't I?"
*  * *
But in all seriousness, the reckless
disregard of others' comfort displayed by
thoughtless women in theatres admits of
a very simple remedy. The fault lies
with the theater management, which
should provide the greatest comfort possible for its patrons. A polite attendant
to inform wearers of obstructive hats
that it is against the rule of the theatre,
and to take such hat in charge would
soon obviate all difficulties.  If it is



</P><P><PB REF="00000045.tif" SEQ="00000045" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="891" N="41" DISPLAYN="41" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=45"/>
THE WOMAN WHO TALKS.


4I


feasible in the London and Paris Opera
Houses to demand that gentlemen seeking admission to certain parts of the
house should appear in full evening
dress, surely a simple regulation for the
public benefit can offer nothing objectionable here.
We congratulate the California bill
'against high hats on meeting with greater
success than the average bill for high
hats.
About once every two weeks I sally
forth, betimes, from my suburban home,
and, armed with a list as long as a yard
stick, proceed to invade the State street
citadels of trade. On my last shopping
expedition I was commissioned to buy a
dinner set for a friend's wife in the country. My limit was rather low, but the
artistic display in the windows of Pitkin
&amp; Brooks' establishment in the Columbus Memorial Building was too tempting and I entered. Imagine my surprise
when I found numberless dinner sets to
suit all tastes and all lengths of purses.
My selection was quickly made and I
proceeded to revel in the many lovely
objects around. My admiration was
particularly directed to the deeply cut,
brilliant cut-glass, the delicately tinted
Austrian gilded glass, the magnificent
specimens of the potter's art in the ornamental pottery room, the Royal Copenhagen art porcelain which carried off
first honors at the Exposition, and last
but not least, the Holland Delft ware
ornamented with copies of famous paintings by the old Dutch Masters.
Additional hints and suggestions on
this or any other subject will be gladly
received. Any letters addressed to "W.
W. T.," care AMERICAN JEWESS, 3756
Ellis avenue, Chicago, will meet with
prompt attention.


Mrs. Minna Neuer, the gifted German
writer, whose book of poems ought to be
in every Jewish family of culture, is
ready to receive subscription orders for
THE   AMERICAN    JEWESs at 52 First
street, New York.
All other German and English books
in the market can also be ordered from
Mrs. Minna Neuer, who, on application,
will forward a price list of current works.
* * *
Kind Reader! ponder, think and send
us for publication io names of Jewesses
you consider the most prominent ill the
United States. By trying to do this you
will find how little we know of each
other, and how convenient it will be to
have an organ through which we will become better acquainted with one another.
* * *
THE AMERICAN JEWESS cordially invites every charitable organization in
every Jewish community conducted or
assisted by women to send us annual
reports for free publication.
" Body Rested, Mind at Ease."
That is what it is when traveling on the fast
trains of the Chicago, Milwaukee &amp; St. Paul
Railway; besides there is no chance to "' kick,"
for the accommodations are up to date, the
trains keep moving right along and get there
on time. These lines thoroughly cover the
territory between Chicago, La Crosse, St. Paul,
Minneapolis, Aberdeen, Mitchell, Sioux Falls,
Sioux City, Yankton, Council Bluffs, Omaha
and Northern Michigan. All the principal
cities and towns in that territory are reached
by the "St. Paul" lines, connecting at St.
Paul, Council Bluffs and Omaha with all lines
for points in the far west. Write to F. A. Miller, Ass't Gen'l Pass'r Agent, Chicago, Ill., for
one of their new map time tables and a brochure giving a description of the Compartment
Sleeping Cars. Tickets furnished by any coupon ticket agent in the United States and
Canada. The finest dining cars in the world
are run on the solid vestibuled, electric-lighted
and steam-heated trains of the Chicago, Milwaukee &amp; St. Paul Railway.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:16"><BIBL><AUTHORIND>Weill, Harry Elder</AUTHORIND><TITLE>Juvenile Department: The Ghost of the McPherson Mansion.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">42-43</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000046.tif" SEQ="00000046" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="897" N="42" DISPLAYN="42" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=46"/>
THE GHOST OF THE McPHERSON MANSION.


My father was the owner of a large
general merchandise store in a town of
Southern Ohio. Winter evenings all
the old men of the village would gather
there and sit around a great cannon stove
and tell stories of their early days, which
were always full of hairbreadth escapes.
As soon as my lessons were finished, I
hurried down to the store and listened
with breathless interest to these tales of
adventures.  In this way I heard stories that usually made my blood run cold,
and icy shivers creep down my spinal
column. In fact I was so frightened at
times that I was afraid to go home alone.
At eight o'clock sharp I usually started
homeward.   One evening, I remained
curled up behind the counter until after
nine o'clock, when I was discovered, and
was told to go home at once. I had just
been listening to a weird story in connection with my own home, which at
one time belonged to the McPherson estate. So I started out rather timidly,
and went along whistling as all boys do
when walking alone. I had a long way
to go. We lived on the outskirts of the
little village high up on a hill that overlooked the famous Scioto Valley and the
river of the same name. I had to pass
a small sheet of water known as Lake


Darling and the old cemetery. At any
minute I expected that the white tombstones would be hurled at me by some
invisible denizen of the graveyard. I
always felt more courageous after having
passed the silent city of the dead; I
dreaded this portion of my journey, and
breathed more freely when the cemetery
was behind me. No sooner had I left
the store, than the story related this very
evening began to haunt me. It was
about the McPherson Mansion Ghost, as
it was seen more than once many years
ago. I will tell you the weird tale,
after having related my awful experience
on the way home that eventful night.
Nearing the graveyard, I was almost
frightened to death by something white,
jumping right out in front of me. I ran
for dear life, as fast as my legs would
carry me. But the faster I ran, the
larger the apparition became; it was always at my side, keeping pace with me.
Finally I arrived home hatless and
breathless and scared out of my wits. I
gave the door-bell a sudden jerk, pulling
out door-knob and wire.  My frantic
efforts to be heard brought my mother
quickly to the door. She saw my excitement, and asked the reason of it.
While relating my experience, the ghost



</P><P><PB REF="00000047.tif" SEQ="00000047" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="765" N="43" DISPLAYN="43" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=47"/>
THE APE FAMILOY.4


4


ran into the open doorway. It was Tom,
a tame, white rahhit helonging to onr
neighhor.
After recovering from my fright, I
hegged mother to tell me all ahont the
ghost story, of which I knew some frag

ments. This she was rather loath to do,
hot after I told her that I had heard
part of it in the store, she related the
following:
(Conlinued.)


THE APE FAMILOY.
FCEo OF A0 CHIMPA.NZEE. This is an excellent pictsure of the Chimspanzee, displayissgto the greatest advantage ths issosnsss frnotal ridge oboves the eys as weell as tiss great ears fos wehich it is ssotsd. The large, slitlike osouth wsith the sotended loosen lip, the length of the uppen lip, the misishapens nose uud ths deep-set eyes,
are ult brosght out seith the snost faithful exactitude.
(Fruos Bnehm's' Life of Animasnl, by persmissiosn uf A. N. Marquis &amp; Co., Chicugo, I11.1


Among the ancients, the Egyptians
and Hindoos seem to have heen the only
ones who showed a certain affection for
the Apes. The old Egyptians chiseled
their likeness in indestrnctihle porphyry
and modeled the images of their gods
J,  after them; the old Hindoos huilt them
honses and temples, a practice which
their descendants are still following.
Solomon imported several monkeys from


Ophir and the Romans kept them, in their
honses as pets, dissected them in their
anatomical studies, sometimes used them
in fights with wild heasts, hot never
came to he on very friendly terms with
them, and like Solomon, never thoughit
them to he anything else than ani mals.
The Arahians go a little further: they
think them Men, who for their sins have
heen condemned hy Allah to hear the



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:17"><BIBL><TITLE>The Ape Family.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">43-46</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000047.tif" SEQ="00000047" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="765" N="43" DISPLAYN="43" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=47"/>
THE APE FAMILOY.4


4


ran into the open doorway. It was Tom,
a tame, white rahhit helonging to onr
neighhor.
After recovering from my fright, I
hegged mother to tell me all ahont the
ghost story, of which I knew some frag

ments. This she was rather loath to do,
hot after I told her that I had heard
part of it in the store, she related the
following:
(Conlinued.)


THE APE FAMILOY.
FCEo OF A0 CHIMPA.NZEE. This is an excellent pictsure of the Chimspanzee, displayissgto the greatest advantage ths issosnsss frnotal ridge oboves the eys as weell as tiss great ears fos wehich it is ssotsd. The large, slitlike osouth wsith the sotended loosen lip, the length of the uppen lip, the misishapens nose uud ths deep-set eyes,
are ult brosght out seith the snost faithful exactitude.
(Fruos Bnehm's' Life of Animasnl, by persmissiosn uf A. N. Marquis &amp; Co., Chicugo, I11.1


Among the ancients, the Egyptians
and Hindoos seem to have heen the only
ones who showed a certain affection for
the Apes. The old Egyptians chiseled
their likeness in indestrnctihle porphyry
and modeled the images of their gods
J,  after them; the old Hindoos huilt them
honses and temples, a practice which
their descendants are still following.
Solomon imported several monkeys from


Ophir and the Romans kept them, in their
honses as pets, dissected them in their
anatomical studies, sometimes used them
in fights with wild heasts, hot never
came to he on very friendly terms with
them, and like Solomon, never thoughit
them to he anything else than ani mals.
The Arahians go a little further: they
think them Men, who for their sins have
heen condemned hy Allah to hear the



</P><P><PB REF="00000048.tif" SEQ="00000048" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="874" N="44" DISPLAYN="44" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=48"/>
44


THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


form of Apes, their outward appearance
seeming to them to be a curious blending of devil and Man.
Our own manner of thinking is not
very different from that of the Arabians.
Instead of recognizing them as our next
of kin we only see in them caricatures of
ourselves, and condemn them without


A single look at the skeletons of a Man
and an Ape shows us the difference in
their respective structures, though this
difference is only conditional. At any
rate it is wrong to term the Apes illshaped, as people usually do. There are
beautiful Apes, and there are very ugly
ones; the same is true of Men, for an


PROFILE OF CHIMPANZEE.-This picture shows to good advantage the large slit-like mouth, the
mild and gentle eye and the quaintly shaped nose that are peculiarities of the Chimpanzee. While
decidedly unattractive there is absent the ferocity that marks the countenance of the Gorilla. And
indeed the Chimpanzee has a disposition that is gentle and kind except when it has suffered from
privation, or age and infirmity overcome it.
(From Brehm's Life of Animals, by permission of A. N. Marquis &amp; Co., Chicago, IlI.)


mercy, finding only those kinds attractive that show the least likeness to a
human being, while those in which the
likeness is more distinct excite our disgust. Our aversion to the Apes is based
as well on their physical as their mental
traits.  They resemble Men both too
much and too little. While the human
body shows perfect harmony, that of the
Ape often seems a repulsive caricature.


Eskimo, a Bushman or a native of New
Holland is by no means a model for a
statue of Apollo. Apes taken by themselves are very well endowed animals;.
it is only when compared with the highest developed Men that they appear to
be caricatures of the superior being.
We must concede that the Apes are
malicious, cunning, choleric, vindictive,.
sensual, quarrelsome, irritable and peev


</P><P><PB REF="00000049.tif" SEQ="00000049" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="894" N="45" DISPLAYN="45" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=49"/>
THE APE FAMILY.


45


ish; on the other hand, we must take
into account their cleverness, their good
humor, their gentleness, their trust in,
and kindness to Man, their amusing
social qualities, their cheering earnestness, their courage and their readiness
to stand by each other in case of need,
even against superior enemies, and their
inclination to play and tease. In one
respect they even rise to greatness, and
that is in their love for their offspring,
their pity for the weak and defenseless,
not only of their own family and kind,
but even of other animals.
The social life of the Apes is a very
attractive one for every observer. There
are but few kinds which live singly; the
majority prefer to live in small troops or
bands. Each of these latter selects a
permanent home of greater or less extent. The choice as a rule falls on a
country that seems favorable in all respects. There must be something to eat,
or else they emigrate. In a poor country
forests near human dwellings seem to be
regarded as paradisaical; the forbidden
tree does not trouble the Ape's conscience, so long as the apples on it are
toothsome. Plantations of sweet corn
and sugarcane, fields of onions, orchards
and banana trees are preferable to anything else; villages also are liked, where
anybody chastising the robbers has to
dread the superstition of the inhabitants.
As soon as the band has come to a conclusion about a place of habitation, the
real life of the monkeys begins, with all
its joys and sorrows, its quarrels and its
-cares. The oldest and strongest male is
made the chief; this dignity is not conferred by universal suffrage, but by long
and hard fights with the other aspirants,
that is, with all the old males. The
longest teeth and the strongest arm prevail. Whoever does not submit himself
good-naturedly, is brought to his senses
by a few cuffs, bites and scratches, and


the crown is to the strong; in his teeth
is wisdom.
THE GORILLA.
The Girrilla, Nj ini, or in the language
of the natives, Mpungo ( Gorilla gina),
the sole representative of the family of
the Gorillas, is scarcely smaller but a
great deal broader in the shoulders than
a full-grown Man. The height of a male
reaches on an average from sixty to seventy-two inches; the width of the shoulders thirty-eight inches. The females are
smaller. The length and strength of the
trunk and the upper extremities, the
large size of the hands and feet, the middle fingers and toes of which are joined
by membranes, form the most prominent
characteristics. The most striking features in the large head, which because of
the shortness of the neck and its powerful muscles seems to be set immediately
on the trunk, are the prominent arches
of the eyebrows, the eyes lying deep in
their sockets, the broad, flat nose, and
the large mouth, bounded by thick lips
and provided with a fearful set of teeth.
The hair is rather long, shaggy, of dark
colors, gray, brown or reddish. The
face is left free from hair to the eyebrows,
as also the ears and the hands and feet
laterally and at the extremities.
IN this Department the young in spirit,
as well as the young in years, are invited
to lay their offerings at the shrine of THE
AMERICAN JEWESS, and it is to be hoped
that many will come forward, not only
with the first fruits, but also with the
fruits of many seasons.
The children are especially invited to
contribute to this Department original
anecdotes, stories, poems, occurrences of
school and Sabbath-school life.-ED.
WANTED-ADVERTISING AGENT IN NEW YORK.
A thoroughly competent and reliable advertising
agent in New York City. Write, giving full particulars.



</P><P><PB REF="00000050.tif" SEQ="00000050" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="773" N="46" DISPLAYN="46" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=50"/>
A FAMILY OF GORILLAS.-This picture represents a family of Gorillas, the month or two old babv ill the
foreground, at the feet of its watchfil mother, while the ever-alert father is keeping guard from a perch of
strong viniss sThe mother's face is placid, because she knows the father's ear is never closed and that his tlighty
arm will protect her antd the helpless little ole, whose dreamlly face expresses entire satisfaction. It is a most
graphic ands faithful delineation of a life-like scene in the great hot fortst in Equatorial Africa, and portrays in
pleasisng-measure,the home life of these creatures so greatly resembling Man. Fierce and intractable as is the
Gorilla, he is liind toi his wife and children, protecting them from all enemieu s -d careful in providing for their
comfort. (Gorilla gini.)
(From Brehm's Life of Animals, by permission of A. N. Marquis &amp; Co. Chicago, Ill.)



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:18"><BIBL><TITLE>Editor's Desk.</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="pg">47-51</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000051.tif" SEQ="00000051" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="892" N="47" DISPLAYN="47" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=51"/>
EDITOR'S DESK.


W ITH the decline of our century
American architecture is evidently on the ascent. This fact is demonstrated by the skyscrapers first introduced in Chicago, and now massively
rooted in every large city in the Union.
The proudest monument of nineteenth
century architecture, though, has vanished from off the face of the earth. The
magnificent "White City" lives now
only in the memory of the millions who
saw its wonders. Soon every trace of it
will be totally gone, and in a few years
the magnitude and vastness of the buildings will sound to the growing generation like a fairy tale. Already, to-day,
the average stroller in Jackson Park fails
to locate the exact spot of the Marvel
Palaces. How will it be a few years
hence?
Memory is treacherous, and statistics
not always at hand. We would therefore propose to the Park Commissioners
of Jackson Park to erect, if not monuments of stone and mortar, at least handsome tablets outlining the space occupied
by each Exposition Palace.  Chicago
owes this historical record to posterity,
as well as to the millions who never saw
the Columbian Exposition, but will undoubtedly at one time or another be
guests of the Western metropolis. The
future visitor to Jackson Park ought at
least to be able to form a mental vision
of the past, by having outlined to him
the immense space occupied by the
most magnificent architecture of the
nineteenth century.
RS. KATE CHOPIN whose gifted
pen contributes to our initial number a delightful sketch of Creole life, is
one of the most interesting and unique
writers of the fin de siecle. Since the
appearance of her book " Bayou Folk,"
a collection of most charming tales,
Kate Chopin has become an acknowl

edged literary power.  The Hartford
Courant gives it as its opinion "that
these Louisiana sketches will be in time
of value as historic documents."
The Portland Transcript says: " These
Creole and Acadian tales are so fine that
no words save 'charming' and 'fascinating' will serve to describe them."
Review of Reviews.  " This is decidedly one of the best volumes of short
stories which has appeared for some
time. They might remind some readers
of certain finished bits of Maupassant
and other French ' short story ' masters."
Boston Beacon.~ "Such books as this
are to be reckoned as among the choicest
productions of our native literature.
They have the simplicity and grace of
perfect truth."
And so does the Press sing the praises
of Kate Chopin's "Bayou Folk."  "A
No-Account Creole," published a few
months ago by the Century, added a
great deal to the fame of the author,
who from all sides received expressions
of warmest praise.  But the most remarkable of all the delightful sketches
is, perhaps, " Disiris Baby," which was
first published in Vogue and set the
critics wild with enthusiasm.
Mrs. Chopin is a regular contributor
to The Atlantic, The Century, Vogue,
Harper's, Youth' s Comrpanion, Ladies'
Home Journal, Wide Awake, and other
prominent journals of America.
It is therefore with gratification and
just pride that THE AMERICAN JEWESS
presents to its readers " Cavanelle, " and
the portrait of the author.
OT what has happened, but what
is recorded makes history.  To
measure correctly the importance of
events of which we ourselves are the
witnesses seems absolutely impossible.
It is therefore difficult to predict with



</P><P><PB REF="00000052.tif" SEQ="00000052" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="818" N="48" DISPLAYN="48" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=52"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.
D. Crawford &amp; Co....ST. LOUIS, MO...
]'   ARE SHOWING THE LATEST WEAVES IN
US -     Silk and
Colored
Dress Fabrics
at at
'                         GCrepons
Princess Crepes
etc., etc.
Can be found on Crawford's counters, and in
CRAWFORD'S GREAT BAZAAR
EVERYTHING IN....
DRY GOODS
HOUSE FURNISHINGS
MILLINERY
SUITS, WRAPS
*              ETC., ETC....ALL AT BOTTOM        PRICES...
Crawford's New Spring Catalogue mailed Free on application



</P><P><PB REF="00000053.tif" SEQ="00000053" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="896" N="49" DISPLAYN="49" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=53"/>
EDITOR'S DESK.


49


certainty the eftect which the National
Council of Jewish Women may have
upon the mental and religious development of American Jewesses. The historical significance of the event cannot
be realized by those who see, hear and
enact it.
The realization of new and lofty ideas
is often ridiculed by contemporaries,
whom the sober verdict of history will
have obliterated long before the fruit of
a noble purpose has fully ripened. The
National Council of Jewish Women is
the fruit of the religious parliament held
in Chicago during the World's Columbian Exposition. Then it was that for
the first time the representatives of
the principal religions of the world
came together, each expounding the
truths of his own faith. Strange to
say, the most enthusiastic utterances of
great and brilliant orators failed to shake
the rooted convictions of any delegate
in the superiority of the faith he represented. On the contrary, we firmly believe that each representative of the
great religious parliament left it, heart
and soul firmly set upon the purpose to
further more than ever the doctrines of
his own faith. We judge this by the.enthusiasm manifested since then by
every creed to expand and foster its religious work.
Still a good deal was gained. From
the parliament of creeds has sprung the
parliament of deeds.   Metaphysical
questions may yet divide the disciples
of various faiths, but they are destined
to be forgotten in the philanthropic endeavor of almost one million women to
better the condition of sex, sect and section. This movement is a mighty wave
of civilization and the Jews of America
may justly feel proud of the gifted and
noble women who recently represented in
Washington the National Council of
Jewish Women. We think they have
carried forth the torch that will become


the beacon light for the Jewesses of
America.
W   E HAVE received the twenty-first
annual report of the Union of
American Hebrew Congregations. It is
an interesting document, revealing the
steady progress and the high standing of
the institution, demonstrating the active
support of 128 congregations; it records
the generosity of numerous individuals,
and signifies the unselfish work of its
teachers and the able management of its
officers.
The institution is financially in a flourishing condition. But by far more liberal are the bequests of deceased sisters
than the contributions of living ladies.
Among the 342 annual contributors we
find but seven women; as pupils, teachers and officers, of course-none. Befitting the pious character of the Union,
the spirit of peace and harmony prevailed throughout its proceedings.
The burning words of Mr. Leo N. Levi,
uttered at the convention held in New
Orleans, gives a glow of warmth to the
published report. We wish there were
many such enthusiastic laymen as Mr.
Leo N. Levi, and as capable supporters
of Judaism. But why should a man so
well informed as he query the teachers of
" What Judaism is? " when even we can
discern that Judaism is Monotheism pure
and simple, embodied and practiced as a
religion by a people who in their solemn
march through history have been a living
protestation against idolatry and unbelief. It is a visible factor of the spiritual
conception of an eternal Creator, and for
that reason it remains the same, no matter in what form the ancient belief is practiced.
Annexed to the report of the union of
American Hebrew Congregations is that
of the Biennial Conference of the Hebrew Sabbath School Union. Some fifty
schools are now members of this body.



</P><P><PB REF="00000054.tif" SEQ="00000054" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="768" N="50" DISPLAYN="50" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=54"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


Swift —Strong —Handsome.            7
ABSOLUTELY THE BEST.
STRICTLY UP TO DATE IN EVERY PARTICULAR.
Five Models —Ladies' and Men's
$85.00 and $100.00 —18 to 25 pounds
ELE ANT-FORTYVPAGEICATALOGLUESE-NT
MONAROH" CYCLE LMFG. CO.
LAKE AND HALSTED-'STS.,        280 WABASH AVENUE,
CHICAGO.
C. PDORTLAND  TORONTOC



</P><P><PB REF="00000055.tif" SEQ="00000055" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="881" N="51" DISPLAYN="51" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=55"/>
EDITOR'S DESK.


Among the delegates assembled at New
Orleans was one lady. We cannot account for the absence of women at so important a conference. Surely in matters
of education women ought to be consulted. Mothers send their children to
school, and those who teach them are
mostly women. We would suggest that
the tutors form a National Union of
Hebrew Sabbath School teachers, to
meet whenever and wherever the Hebrew Sabbath School Union of America
is in session. Such a body could give
practical hints to those who theoretically prepare their studies. Meanwhile
we invite all teachers to ventilate this
subject through our columns; make the
articles brief and to the point; sign
them or not, but have your little say on
"Sabbath School Education."
CHICAGO JEWISH TRAINING
SCHOOL.
''HE Mardi Gras Carnival to take
1 place April 4, at the Auditorium,
for the benefit of the Jewish Training
School, will again demonstrate Chicago's unbounded generosity in assisting a noble cause. The officers of the
school are:
President-Henry L. Frank.
Vice-president-Mrs. Levy Mayer.
Recording Secretary-Dr. Joseph Stolz.
Financial Secretary-Herman Hefter.
Treasurer-Mrs. Leo Fox.
Directors-W. N. Eisendrath, Dr. E. G.
Hirsch, Sidney Lowenstein, A. Kopperl, Leopold Schlesinger, Mrs. Flora M. Kahn, Mrs. N.
Loeb, Mrs. B. Mandel, Mrs. M. Rosenbaum,
Mrs. Joseph Rosenthal, Mrs. C. Stettauer and
Mrs. E. Witkowsky.
The preparations for the Carnival give
promise that every feature of the grand
festival will be carried out on an elaborate
and artistic scale. To whom the credit
is due can be gathered from the following names, constituting the various committees.
Managing Committee-M. R. Wineman,
chairman; Louis Eckstein, vice chairman;


Mrs. F. M.'Kahn, secretary; Mrs. E. Mandel,
treasurer.
Hall-Norman Florsheim, chairman; Louis
Stumer, Fred Mandel and Leo A. Loeb.
Printing-Louis Eckstein, chairman; M. R.
Wineman, M. L. Ash and Leon V. Becker.
Tickets-Mrs. Levy Mayer, chairman; Sidney Loeb, Harry Pflaum and Willie Willharte.
Entertainment and Music-W. S. Rothschild,
chairman; Louis Eckstein, M. J. Spiegel, Sol
Bloom and L. M. Stumer.
Banquet-Louis A. Kohn, chairman; Henry
K. Strauss, Sol L. DeLee and W. Florsheim.
Prize —Louis rStumer, chairman;   Sidney
Lowenstein, Frank E. Mandel and Sam J.
Marks.
Box-M. Hirsh, chairman; M. R. Wineman,
Leo A. Loeb and Sol Bloom.
Press-L. Eckstein, chairman; Lessing Rosenthal, Hugo Pam  and A. L. Austrian.
AOENTS WANTED.
Reliable agents for THE AMERICAN JEWESS wanted
in everycityofthe Union. Tel, I favorable. Write at
once to this office, with references.
AGENT IN LONDON, ENO.
Wanted-A representative and agent for this magazine ill London. Address, with references, this office.
Extreme long waist, with patent loop eyelets. Made in....
WHITE,
FRENCH DRAB N       Price,.00
~
BLACK SATEEN
For sale at all leading dry goods stores.



</P></DIV1>
<DIV1 NODE="taj1895.0001.001:19"><BIBL><TITLE>Advertisement</TITLE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="vol">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="iss">1</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="mo">April</BIBLSCOPE><BIBLSCOPE TYPE="year">1895</BIBLSCOPE></BIBL><P><PB REF="00000056.tif" SEQ="00000056" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="706" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=56"/>
THE AMERICAN JEWESS.


[YMAN, ER~lG &amp;f Co.
J-ewelers
anDiamond
llerchants
CHOICE SILvrzRWARE_ rOR
WE-DDING GWrTS
-Send for Illustrated Catalogue of SILVER NOVELTIES
CoLuMBUS MEMORIAL BLDG.
State &amp; Washington Sts:, CHICAGO
NAHIDA REMY'S
"THE JEWISH WOMAN"
TRANSLATED BY
LOUISE MANNHTEIMER
TABLE OF CONTENTS
I Chap'er-Antiquity.
0         Christian Idea about Woman sod
Marriage.
3          tsh and tshoh.
4          Temperaentrt and Talmud.
5          Biblical Women.
6         Jewish Queens.
7         In the Dark Middle Ages.
8          More Light.
9    Practical Culture Work.
to         Sarah Copia Sullami.
ifI   The Mother.
[2         The Sacred Language.
13         Apostates.
14    The Daughters of Daniel Itzig.
t5         Art Among Jeswish Women.
i6         Jewish Literary Work.
17         Jewish Benefactresses.
iS8        The Modern Jewess.
PRICE, $1.50
O~doetreocivedat office of The Ameerican Israelite,
icinc~nati, and office of The Amnerican JewessRoomt
300 Monon Building, 32 Dearborn Street, Chicago.
1A AdisouantcOf 2percent.owitlbe allowedon orders of
ore dazen oc more. Ordercutcntbecaccompanied by
-raft or moneyoredr.


Dr. 5. Pollizer
Imperial Health
Commissioner and
Consulting
Physician....CARLSBAD....
Well known in Europe and America, invites Americans to avail themselves of his
assistance and advice while at Carlsbad.
English spoken.
*.-LE:SSI4G~ MOUSE:...


Send Your Address
And I will send you a lovely
Souvenir
Book... Free


= -G.
E -
':0;1S
(P 10
I.,.
S-&gt;,.,.4
0
In0
E. 0., a. 1


The Real Secret of
Beauty=~oe thr Complexion,Haeds,PFaceand Hair,
inthe Ithousands oft iostoeces is found in
the perfetet action prodoced by the use of the real, honest,
proe, onadolterated Thistle Preparations. Poe sole at alt
first-clatss air Stores and Drggists.
Sale Manufacturer... LENA 0. AUSTRIAN,
Laboratney, 138 35th Street,
Wholesole tDepots:      Chicagn, Ill.
roller &amp; Poller Co., Morrison. Plomoer &amp; Co



</P><P><PB REF="00000057.tif" SEQ="00000057" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="859" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=57"/>
Foreman
Shoe Co.
N. W. Corner
State and Madison Sts.
"One Profit from
Maker to Wearer."


ORDERS BY MAIL WILL RECEIVE
PROMPT AND
CAREFUL ATTENTION.


Remember the Name
It means the highest perfection in
Candymaking.    You'll find a flavor,
a delicacy, a taste of absolute purity
in Huyler's Confections very rarely
attained.............


Spring Style IN
Popular Footwear
AT Popular Prices
Now Ready.


181 La Salle St.,        2132 Michigan Ave.,
Business Men's Branch.     South Side Branch.
161 State Street, Chicago.
-— Branches of 863 Broadway...New York ---


-


Atlas Ftre Assurance Co., England.
North German Fire Ins. Co., Hamburg.
Transatlantic Fire Ins. Co., Hamburg.
Rochester German Ins. Co., N. Y.
German Fire Ins. Co., Pittsburg, Pa.
Lloyd's Plate Glass Ins. Co., New York.
ESTABLISHED 1873
h(CbeLF1A L


Telephone Main
— 2094 —


Fine==
Catalogue and Book
Printing....
Established 1867.
E. Rubovits &amp; Son,


Printers....
Stationers
Engravers


189-191 La Salle Street...CHICAGO


163 and 165 Fifth Avenue,
f%                CHICAGO.
Binders...
Blank Book
Mlakers...


ADOLPH,OEB,EO A. LOEB
Louis BECKER


TELEPHONE MAIN
1353



</P><P><PB REF="00000058.tif" SEQ="00000058" RES="600dpi" FMT="TIFF6.0" FTR="UNSPEC" CNF="806" N="" DISPLAYN="" HREF="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?cc=amjewess;idno=taj1895.0001.001;debug=xml;c=amjewess;seq=58"/>
Anheuser=Busch..........
Brewing Ass'n                              St. Louis, Mo.
BREWERS OF   FIN       B[E   R     EXCLUSIVELY
Our Brands:                                      Largest
ftnheuser- Busch                                      Brewina
Standard                                             Gapacitu
The Orioinal                                      ol anU Breweru
Budweiser                                      in the World
The Faust                                       2,000,000
The Munhener                                         Barrels and
The                                          100,000,000
Premium Pale                                             Bottles
The Exquisite                                        a Year






Our Motto in Buying Brew Materials is:
"NOT HOW CHEAP, BUT HOW GOOD"



</P></DIV1>
</BODY></TEXT></DLPSTEXTCLASS>